<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C65-1005">
<Title>MACIIINE TRANSLATION AND CONNECTEDNESS BETWEEN PHRASES</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="5" end_page="5" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
6. Compound phrases.
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The composing of two or more primitive phrases in compound phrases can be performed by the usual logical means (e.g.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> by means of logical conjunctions &amp;quot;even&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;if,...theno..&amp;quot; eventually of other analogous conjunctions like &amp;quot;but&amp;quot; and similar, or by mo~ns of negation and quantors) in a v~ll-known way, or c~n be perfomed by the pure linguistic expressive means. Both these kind~ may be arbitrarily interchanged by the successive composing. null Similtaneously, it is decisive that the composing of single primitive phrases corresponds with the composing of their syntactical and, of course, semantical chsrac~eristicso Besides, there are mostly composed such two phrases that have some word in common, or where some word is repeated. This fact is necessary to be distinguished especially by composing the corresponding rharacteristics, or - what is in substance the sam~- it is necesser~ ~ to join to ar~ word-characteristic c the symbol express~.ng a va&amp;quot; l riable for the basic for.ms of word, so that we shall write X,c 1 v,,here we can put for X the real basic forms of words.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The composing of primitive phroses in compound phrases belong to the field of the synthesis of phrasesdeg If we, for instance~ want to say that some man reads s book and simultaneously that he reads quickly and~ in addition, that this book is good ~nd even very good, we can express it in the following cnmound phrases P = (which is zramm~tically the form of the sentence) &amp;quot;m~n reads quickly a very good book&amp;quot;deg The syntax of this phrn~e is n~t evidently ewpress~d b$&amp;quot; the logical meansdeg In the considered case the following primitive phrases are P1 &amp;quot;Po = &amp;quot; reads quickly&amp;quot;, concerned: = &amp;quot; a ma reads a book, P~ = &amp;quot;good book&amp;quot; and P4 = &amp;quot;very good&amp;quot;o From these phrases the compound phrase is put togethcro If we use the function h fcr single words of the considered phrase, we get successively h\[a man\]=~man, Cl\] , h\[quicklyl=Lquick, c2.7 , hEreads I =L-read, C3~o.. ' ,,,,h\[a book\]=~book,, cJ~where Cl, C2,ooo , 0 6 are the correapondine syntactical characteristicsdeg Analogously when we use the fun ction k we get the semantical characteristics of single wordsdeg The syntactical characteristics of single (separate) primitive phrases PI' P2' P3' P4 are successively CI,C2,C3,C4, , , , , , , ,L&amp;quot;3, e3, ) C3 = (D?5,C 51 ~ ~W6, c6. I) and C4 = ~:;4' c4.~ '\[WS' c5.~ )deg At the same time, there is very important that some variables W i occur simultaneously in two primitive phrasesdeg Thereby is, namely, expressed the circumstance that by these two phraes is told something of the same fact and just this circumstance plays the decisive role at stating the constents-connection among more phrasesdeg If we started from the given phrase &amp;quot; a man quic1~ly reads a very good book&amp;quot; we would find the mentioned four primitive phrases as follows: first we would use for single words the function h and k and then we would find for every word of the mentioned phrase, which can be the basic predicate of some primitive phrase (it can be found out of its semnatical characteristics and by the semantical characteristics of the primitive phraes) further words belonging to it in a certain primitive phrase, ioeo which take places of the considered predicate and this occurs only ~ulfk 21 in comparison of the syntactical characteristics of words frcm the given phrase with the syntactical characteristics of a certain investigated primitive phrasedeg For instance, in our case~ if we have found out according to the semnatical characteristic that the word &amp;quot;reads&amp;quot; is two-placed predicate, we would find out the syntactical characteristics cf such primitive phraes, the basic word of which was just the two-placed predicate. Then we have kncwn what syntactical characteristics of words and - as far as the word-order is concerned - where there are to be found, so that we find out whether the investigated primitive phrases are in the given phrase includeddeg When finishing it for all these words, we shall find it successively for all primitive phrases that in the given phrase are compriseddeg In such a way is, namely, depicted the analysis of the compound phrase, not composed by the logical means. If there are used the logical means, then the given phrase is decomposed like in the logicdeg Rut it is necessary to mention in addition, that for the economy-reasons and for saving the number of syntactical characteristics of the primitive phrases, it is convenient to work often with incomplete characteristics onlyo The question is, whether we shall include two primitive phrases&amp;quot; a man reads a book&amp;quot; And &amp;quot;the man read a book&amp;quot; into one (incomplete) syntactical characteristic, or into two different and naturally complete -ones. The incompleteness wi\]l consist in the failing fact on number (and si~ni\]arly it woula be in other phraes with data on gender and case), but naturally there would not fail ~ulik 22 the datum on coincidence in number between ,,a man&amp;quot; and ,,reads or ,,the man&amp;quot; and ,,read&amp;quot; because this fact will be ~.~st decisive for the incomplete characteristics.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The possibility of the use of incomplete syntactical characteristics by the synthesis is, of course, also evident. If we want to make the whole synthesis of the compound phrase independent on proper meanings of single words, then we can givG in the syntactical characteristics neither the gender nor the number, because both of them are defined differently no sooner than by the choice of the basic form (because in many cases genders are steadily fixed). But even here it is not the matter of principle but the matter of effectivity.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 7. Sementica! dependence and connectedness.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> As, sccording to the supposition, there is denoted in every primitve phrase its basic predicate which always stands in front of parantheses in its semantical characteristic (for instance at Q(x,y) Q is the basic predicate) it is possible to define the semantical dependence among the words of the primitive phrase by the demand that the basic predicate a!v~ays depends on all other v;ords that occur in ti~e phrase, i.e. on its arguments (e.g. Q deoends on x and on y) Just so Ous~ii-ed v~'ould be the definition that, on the con~.~r$~deg 7, ell argtm~ents depend on the basic predicate.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> If we demonstrate this semantical dependence on a diorama, _ =~.,~ drav: the connectin C !in~, provided },~ith, an arrow-head, directir~ from an argument to a basic predicate* At the same time, ~ul~k 23 of course, accordi~ to the position of separate words - if they are more to the left or to the right -we discern always the word-order. Four primitive phrases from the preceeding paragraph are deomstrated in the following diagramm: We say that the sem~tical dependence is concerned because this relation ~o~ the basic predicate and its arguments, expressed just by the theorem that objects denoted by the arguments are in relation defined by the basic predicate, is quite initial definition referri~ evidently to the reality. The semantical dependence does not refer to a~thing else than to the fact of te!li~ somethi~ of somethi~ (on the mathematical level the fact of telli~ ~l.~ ~ ~,~) can be transferred only on the basic relation of the adherence to the set) when one passes from the predicate Q to the binary relation Q~ and puts down (x,y)@Q~).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> We say further that in the primitive phrase the basic predicate is directly connected with any of its arguments, i.e. two words of the primitive phrase cohere together when either the first depe~s on the second, or the second on the first. ~hen illustrating the direct connectedness we can use the s~e diagrmr~ like when il!ustrati~ the dependence, but we do not pay attention to arrow-heads. Thus, evidently in P &amp;quot;man&amp;quot; is directly connected ~ulik 25 by the referrin means (there are e.g. pronouns, definite articles and si~:~!ar), but sometimes these are concealed and in this case it will be necessary to complete the text (or not to admit such a text at all). If there are everywhere the referring means expressed, they are possible to be used for further identification of the v~ords of single diagran~Is for separate p~ras~s ~analogously as it was mentioned at the primitive phrases), and thereby to get the diagramms of the semantical dependence, eventually even the dependence for the whole text.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> In the case of the whoie-text-diagr&amp;v~ two cases are possible: either there is a com~ected graph and then we say that the connected text is concerned, or this graph is disconnected and then we say that the text is disconnected. But, any disconnected text splits, in a natural way, into its connected components and it is evident that it will be possible to translate these components independently on themselves (because they do not cohere together semantically).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> Therefore we can concern only a connected context T.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> According to the section 2 T = (SI.S 2. ...Sk), where S i are sentences and we remind that the condition (2) resp.(5) is not al!ways satisfied, because e.g. sometimes it is necessary to know 3 how the sentence S I was translated, when we want to translate correctly the sentence $2~ But now it is simple to see that there is exactely one word WI in S I and ~2 in S 2 such that W I and W 2 are directly connecteddeg Therefore we may express a hypothesis that it is sufficient to store same informations conoerning the single word W I instead of the whole translation of S I. ~ulik 26 In other words these informations concerning W I are the necessary context, when we want to translate conectly $2o It is similar in other casesdeg '~at concerns the translation of the particular sentences which are decomposed into the primitive phrases the main principales are described in \[4.\] , because it is easy to indtroduced to each primitive phrase a corresponding as in a phrase structer grammar il\]o rule bullk 2 7</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

