<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J91-4001">
<Title>An Efficient Natural Language Processing System Specially Designed for the Chinese Language</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The use of computers to process natural languages has been the research goal of many scientists and engineers for many years, and significant improvement in technologies in recent years has brought such goal closer to reality. While substantial efforts have been made to process natural languages, especially several western languages such as English, and many powerful computational models and algorithms have been pro- null * Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Dept. of Computer Science and Information Engineering, National Taiwan University -~ Dept. of Computer Science and Information Engineering, National Taiwan University :~ Dept. of Electrical Engineering, National Taiwan University SS Dept. of Modern Linguistics, Cornell University, NJ P Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan  O 1991 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 17, Number 4 posed and widely used (Gazdar et al. 1987), very little work has been done with the Chinese language, which more than a quarter of the world's population use as a native language. This is probably due to the fact that the structure of the Chinese language is quite different from western languages like English and, therefore, the experience in processing western languages cannot necessarily be directly applied to the Chinese language. Jiang (1985) proposed a preliminary Chinese parsing prototype system based on the METAL system, while Lin (1985) and Lin et al. (1986a, 1986b) also developed a Chinese natural language processing system with special considerations on the phenomenon of empty categories in the Chinese language. Yang (1987) presented a method using semantic constraints to reduce ambiguity in Chinese sentence analysis. H. H. Chen et al. (1988) proposed a logic programming approach considering Chomsky's Goverment-Binding theory to cope with movement transformations in Mandarin Chinese.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> In the following, some special syntactic phenomena of the Chinese language that significantly affect the design of the present system are first summarized in Sections 2 and 3, and a brief description of the present system and the structure of the linguistic knowledge base is then given in Section 4. The several new approaches, including the direction-selective chart and the head-driven chart parser, the bidirectional look-ahead approach, and the heuristic scheduling policy, are described in detail in Sections 5, 6, and 7, respectively. Sections 8 and 9 then present the improved design of the raise-bind mechanism to cope with the problem of movement transformation and empty categories. Some preliminary experimental results are discussed in Section 10, and concluding remarks and future research directions are finally given in Section 11.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

