<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J03-1005">
<Title>c(c) 2003 Association for Computational Linguistics Word Reordering and a Dynamic Programming Beam Search Algorithm for Statistical Machine Translation</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="98" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This article is about a search procedure for statistical machine translation (MT). The task of the search procedure is to find the most likely translation given a source sentence and a set of model parameters. Here, we will use a trigram language model and the translation model presented in Brown et al. (1993). Since the number of possible translations of a given source sentence is enormous, we must find the best output without actually generating the set of all possible translations; instead we would like to focus on the most likely translation hypotheses during the search process. For this purpose, we present a data-driven beam search algorithm similar to the one used in speech recognition search algorithms (Ney et al. 1992). The major difference between the search problem in speech recognition and statistical MT is that MT must take into account the different word order for the source and the target language, which does not enter into speech recognition. Tillmann, Vogel, Ney, and Zubiaga (1997) proposes a dynamic programming (DP)-based search algorithm for statistical MT that monotonically translates the input sentence from left to right. The word order difference is dealt with using a suitable preprocessing step. Although the resulting search procedure is very fast, the preprocessing is language specific and requires a lot of manual [?] IBM T. J. Watson Research Center, Yorktown Heights, NY 10598. E-mail: ctill@us.ibm.com. The research reported here was carried out while the author was with Lehrstuhl f &amp;quot;ur Informatik VI, Computer Science Department, RWTH Aachen.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> + Lehrstuhl f &amp;quot;ur Informatik VI, Computer Science Department, RWTH Aachen, D-52056 Aachen, Germany. E-mail: ney@informatik.rwth-aachen.de.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  Computational Linguistics Volume 29, Number 1 work. Currently, most search algorithms for statistical MT proposed in the literature are based on the A [?] concept (Nilsson 1971). Here, the word reordering can be easily included in the search procedure, since the input sentence positions can be processed in any order. The work presented in Berger et al. (1996) that is based on the A [?] concept, however, introduces word reordering restrictions in order to reduce the overall search space.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The search procedure presented in this article is based on a DP algorithm to solve the traveling-salesman problem (TSP). A data-driven beam search approach is presented on the basis of this DP-based algorithm. The cities in the TSP correspond to source positions of the input sentence. By imposing constraints on the possible word reorderings similar to that described in Berger et al. (1996), the DP-based approach becomes more effective: when the constraints are applied, the number of word re-orderings is greatly reduced. The original reordering constraint in Berger et al. (1996) is shown to be a special case of a more general restriction scheme in which the word reordering constraints are expressed in terms of simple combinatorical restrictions on the processed sets of source sentence positions.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  A set of four parameters is given to control the word reordering. Additionally, a set of four states is introduced to deal with grammatical reordering restrictions (e.g., for the translation direction German to English, the word order difference between the two languages is mainly due to the German verb group. In combination with the reordering restrictions, a data-driven beam search organization for the search procedure is proposed. A beam search pruning technique is conceived that jointly processes partial hypotheses according to two criteria: (1) The partial hypotheses cover the same set of source sentence positions, and (2) the partial hypotheses cover sets C of source sentence positions of equal cardinality. A partial hypothesis is said to cover a set of source sentence positions when exactly the positions in the set have already been processed in the search process. To verify the effectiveness of the proposed techniques, we report and analyze results for two translation tasks: the German to English Verbmobil task and French to English Canadian Hansards task.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The article is structured as follows. Section 2 gives a short introduction to the translation model used and reports on other approaches to the search problem in statistical MT. In Section 3, a DP-based search approach is presented, along with appropriate pruning techniques that yield an efficient beam search algorithm. Section 4 reports and analyzes translation results for the different translation directions. In Section 5, we conclude with a discussion of the achieved results.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

