<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J03-2004">
<Title>c(c) 2003 Association for Computational Linguistics A Probabilistic Account of Logical Metonymy</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="266" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Much work in lexical semantics has been concerned with accounting for regular polysemy, that is, the regular and predictable sense alternations to which certain classes of words are subject (Apresjan 1973). It has been argued that in some cases, the different interpretations of these words must arise from the interaction between the semantics of the words during syntactic composition, rather than by exhaustively listing all the possible senses of a word in distinct lexical entries (Pustejovsky 1991). The class of phenomena that Pustejovsky (1991, 1995) has called logical metonymy is one such example. In the case of logical metonymy additional meaning arises for particular verb-noun and adjective-noun combinations in a systematic way: the verb (or adjective) semantically selects for an event-type argument, which is a different semantic type from that denoted by the noun. Nevertheless, the value of this event is predictable from the semantics of the noun. An example of verbal logical metonymy is given in (1) and (2): (1a) usually means (1b) and (2a) usually means (2b).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1">  (1) a. Mary finished the cigarette.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> b. Mary finished smoking the cigarette.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> (2) a. Mary finished her beer.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> b. Mary finished drinking her beer.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> [?] Department of Computer Science, University of Sheffield, Regent Court, 211 Portobello Street, Sheffield S1 4DP, UK. E-mail: mlap@dcs.shef.ac.uk.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> + School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh, 2 Buccleuch Place, Edinburgh EH8 9LW, UK. E-mail:  Computational Linguistics Volume 29, Number 2 Note how the events in these examples correspond to the purpose of the object denoted by the noun: the purpose of a cigarette is to smoke it and the purpose of a beer is to drink it. Similarly, (3a) means a problem that is easy to solve, (3b) means a language that is difficult to learn, speak, or write, (3c) means a cook that cooks well, (3d) means a soup that tastes good, (3e) means someone who programmes fast, and (3f) means a plane that flies quickly.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7">  (3) a. easy problem b. difficult language c. good cook d. good soup e. fast programmer f. fast plane  The interpretations of logical metonymies can typically be rendered with a paraphrase, as we have indicated for the above examples. Verb-nouns are paraphrased with a progressive or infinitive VP that is the complement of the polysemous verb (e.g., smoking in (1b)) and whose object is the NP figuring in the verb-noun combination (e.g., cigarette in (1b)). Adjective-noun combinations are usually paraphrased with a verb modified by the adjective in question or its corresponding adverb. For example, an easy problem is a problem that is easy to solve or a problem that one can solve easily (see (3a)).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> Logical metonymy has been extensively studied in the lexical semantics literature. Previous approaches have focused on descriptive (Vendler 1968) or theoretical (Pustejovsky 1991, 1995; Briscoe, Copestake, and Boguraev 1990) accounts, on the linguistic constraints on the phenomenon (Godard and Jayez 1993; Pustejovsky and Bouillon 1995; Copestake and Briscoe 1995; Copestake 2001), and on the influence of discourse context on the interpretation of metonymies (Briscoe, Copestake, and Boguraev 1990; Lascarides and Copestake 1998; Verspoor 1997). McElree et al. (2001) investigated the on-line processing of metonymic expressions; their results indicate that humans display longer reading times for sentences like (1a) than for sentences like (1b). There are at least two challenges in providing an adequate account of logical metonymy. The first concerns semi-productivity: There is a wealth of evidence that metonymic constructions are partially conventionalized, and so resolving metonymy entirely via pragmatic reasoning (e.g., by computing the purpose of the object that is denoted by the noun according to real-world knowledge) will overgenerate the possible interpretations (Hobbs et al. 1993). For example, the logical metonymies in  (4) are odd, even though pragmatics suggests an interpretation (because real-world knowledge assigns a purpose to the object denoted by the NP): (4) a. ?John enjoyed the dictionary.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> b. ?John enjoyed the door.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> c. ?John began/enjoyed the highway.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> d. ?John began the bridge.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12">  Sentence (4a) is odd because the purpose of dictionaries is to refer to them, or to consult them. These are (pointlike) achievements and cannot easily combine with enjoy, which has to be true of an event with significant duration. Domain knowledge assigns doors, highways, and bridges a particular purpose, and so the fact that the sentences in (4b)-(4d) are odd indicates that metonymic interpretations are subject to conventional constraints (Godard and Jayez 1993).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13">  Lapata and Lascarides Logical Metonymy The second challenge concerns the diversity of possible interpretations of metonymic constructions. This diversity is attested across and within metonymic constructions. Metonymic verbs and adjectives are able to take on different meanings depending on their local context, namely, the noun or noun class they select as objects (in the case of verbs) or modify (in the case of adjectives). Consider the examples in (1), in which the meaning of the verb finish varies depending on the object it selects. Similarly, the adjective good receives different interpretations when modifying the nouns cook and soup (see (3c) and (3d)).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> Although we've observed that some logical metonymies are odd even though pragmatics suggests an interpretation (e.g., (4c)), Vendler (1968) acknowledges that other logical metonymies have more than one plausible interpretation. In order to account for the meaning of adjective-noun combinations, Vendler (1968, page 92) points out that &amp;quot;in most cases not one verb, but a family of verbs is needed&amp;quot;. For example, fast scientist can mean a scientist who does experiments quickly, publishes quickly, and so on.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> Vendler (1968) further observes that the noun figuring in an adjective-noun combination is usually the subject or object of the paraphrasing verb. Although fast usually triggers a verb-subject interpretation (see (3e) and (3f)), easy and difficult trigger verb-object interpretations (see (3a) and (3b)). An easy problem is usually a problem that one solves easily (so problem is the object of solve), and a difficult language is a language that one learns, speaks, or writes with difficulty (so language is the object of learn, speak, and write). Adjectives like good allow either verb-subject or verb-object interpretations: a good cook is a cook who cooks well, whereas good soup is a soup that tastes good. All of these interpretations of fast scientist, difficult language,orgood soup seem highly plausible out of context, though one interpretation may be favored over another in a particular context. In fact, in sufficiently rich contexts, pragmatics can even override conventional interpretations: Lascarides and Copestake (1998) suggest that (5c) means  (5d) and not (5e): (5) a. All the office personnel took part in the company sports day last week.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> b. One of the programmers was a good athlete, but the other was struggling to finish the courses.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> c. The fast programmer came first in the 100m.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="18"> d. The programmer who runs fast came first in the 100m.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="19"> e. The programmer who programs fast came first in the 100m.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="20"> The discourse context can also ameliorate highly marked logical metonymies, such as (4c): (6) a. John uses two highways to get to work every morning.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="21"> b. He first takes H-280 and then H-101.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="22"> c. He always enjoys H-280,  d. but the traffic jams on H-101 frustrate him.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="23"> Arguably the most influential account of logical metonymy is Pustejovsky's (1991, 1995) theory of the generative lexicon. Pustejovsky avoids enumerating the various senses for adjectives like fast and verbs like finish by exploiting a rich lexical semantics for nouns. The lexical entry for an artifact-denoting noun includes a qualia structure: this specifies key features of the word's meaning that are in some sense  Computational Linguistics Volume 29, Number 2 derivable from real-world knowledge but are lexicalized so as to influence conventional processes. The qualia structure includes a telic role (i.e., the purpose of the object denoted by the noun) and an agentive role (i.e., the event that brought the object into existence). Thus the lexical entry for book includes a telic role with a value equivalent to read and an agentive role with a value equivalent to write, whereas for cigarette the telic role is equivalent to smoke and the agentive role is equivalent to roll or manufacture. When finish combines with an object-denoting NP, a metonymic interpretation is constructed in which the missing information is provided by the qualia structure of the NP. More technically, semantic composition of finish with cigarette causes the semantic type of the noun to be coerced into its telic event (or its agentive event), and the semantic relation corresponding to the metonymic verb (finish) predicates over this event. This results in an interpretation of (1a) equivalent to (1b). Verbs like begin and enjoy behave in a similar way. Enjoy the book can mean enjoy reading the book, because of book's telic role, or enjoy writing the book, because of book's agentive role. In fact, the agentive reading is less typical for book than the telic one, but for other nouns the opposite is true. For instance, begin the tunnel can mean begin building the tunnel, but the interpretation that is equivalent to begin going through the tunnel is highly marked. There is also variation in the relative likelihood of interpretations among different metonymic verbs. (We will return to this issue shortly.) The adjective-noun combinations are treated along similar lines. Thus the logical polysemy of words like finish and fast is not accounted for by exhaustive listing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="24">  In contrast to the volume of theoretical work on logical metonymy, very little empirical work has tackled the topic. Briscoe et al. (1990) investigate the presence of verbal logical metonymies in naturally occurring text by looking into data extracted from the Lancaster-Oslo/Bergen corpus (LOB, one million words). Verspoor (1997) undertakes a similar study in the British National Corpus (BNC, 100 million words). Both studies investigate how widespread the use of logical metonymy is, and how far the interpretation for metonymic examples can be recovered from the head noun's qualia structure, assuming one knows what the qualia structure for any given noun is. Neither of these studies is concerned with the automatic generation of interpretations for logical metonymies and the determination of their likelihood.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="25"> Although conceptually elegant, Pustejovsky's (1995) theory of the generative lexicon does not aim to provide an exhaustive description of the telic roles that a given noun may have. However, these roles are crucial for interpreting verb-noun and adjective-noun metonymies. In contrast to Vendler (1968), who acknowledges that logical metonymies may trigger more than one interpretation (in other words, that there may be more than one possible event associated with the noun in question), Pustejovsky implicitly assumes that nouns or noun classes have one (perhaps default) telic role without, however, systematically investigating the relative degree of ambiguity of the various cases of logical metonymy (e.g., the out-of-context possible readings for fast scientist suggest that fast scientist exhibits a higher degree of semantic ambiguity than fast plane). One could conceivably represent this by the generality of the semantic type of the telic role in the various nouns (e.g., assign the telic role of scientist a relatively general type of event compared with that for plane). But this simply transfers the problem: The degree of generality in lexical representation is highly idiosyncratic and ideally should be acquired from linguistic evidence; furthermore, for nouns with 1 Other lexical accounts, such as Copestake and Briscoe (1995), differ from Pustejovsky's (1995) in that the coercion is treated as internal to the semantics of the metonymic verb or adjective rather than the noun; motivation for this comes from copredication data, such as the acceptability of fast and intelligent typist and John picked up and finished his beer.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="26">  Lapata and Lascarides Logical Metonymy a general telic role, pragmatics would have to do 'more work' to augment the general interpretation with a more specific one. Even in theories in which more than one interpretation is provided (see Vendler 1968), no information is given with respect to the relative likelihood of these interpretations.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="27"> Pustejovsky's account also doesn't predict the degree of variation of interpretations for a given noun among the different metonymic verbs: for example, the fact that begin the house is, intuitively at least, more likely to resolve to an agentive-role interpretation (i.e., begin building the house) than a telic-role interpretation (i.e., begin living in the house), whereas the reverse is true of enjoy the house. Ideally, we would like a model of logical metonymy that reflects this variation in interpretation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="28"> In this article we aim to complement the theoretical work on the interpretation of logical metonymy by addressing the following questions: (1) Can the meanings of metonymic adjective-noun and verb-noun combinations be acquired automatically from corpora? (2) Can we constrain the number of interpretations of these combinations by providing a ranking on the set of possible meanings? (3) Can we determine whether a particular adjective has a preference for a verb-subject or a verb-object interpretation? We provide a probabilistic model that uses distributional information extracted from a large corpus to interpret logical metonymies automatically without recourse to pre-existing taxonomies or manually annotated data.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="29"> The differences among the various theoretical accounts--for example, that Copestake and Briscoe (1995) treat type coercion as internal to the metonymic word, whereas Pustejovsky (1995) treats it as part of the noun--do not matter for our purposes, because we aim to provide information about metonymic interpretations that is compatible with either account. More specifically, we are concerned with using a real-language corpus to acquire automatically the semantic value of the event that is part of the interpretation. We abstract away from theoretical concepts such as semantic type coercion and instead utilize co-occurrence frequencies in the corpus to predict metonymic interpretations. Very roughly, we acquire a ranked set of interpretations enjoy V-ing the book for the construction enjoy the book by estimating the probabilities that V is enjoyed and that it is something done to books; and we estimate these probabilities on the basis of the corpus frequencies for V's appearing as a (verbal) complement to enjoy and for V's taking book as its object. Similarly, we acquire a ranked set of verb-subject interpretations of fast plane by estimating the likelihood of seeing the plane Vs and Vs quickly in the corpus. (See Sections 2 and 3 for more details and motivation of these models.) Our results show not only that we can predict meaning differences when the same adjective or verb is associated with different nouns, but also that we can derive--taking into account Vendler's (1968) observation--a cluster of meanings for a single verb- or adjective-noun combination. We can also predict meaning differences for a given noun associated with different metonymic verbs and adjectives. We evaluate our results by comparing the model's predictions to human judgments and show that the model's ranking of meanings correlates reliably with human intuitions.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="30"> However, the model is limited in its scope. It is suited for the interpretation of well-formed metonymic constructions. But it does not distinguish odd metonymies (see (4)) from acceptable ones: in both cases, paraphrases will be generated, at least in principle (see Section 2.1 for explanation and motivation). In particular, the model does not learn conventional constraints, such as that enjoy must take an event of duration as its argument (Godard and Jayez 1993). However, such constraints are potentially captured indirectly: If the above conventional constraint is right, enjoy referring to should not be attested in the corpus, and hence according to our model it won't be part of a possible paraphrase for enjoy the dictionary (see Sections 2.4.2 and 2.5.3 for further discussion). Further, since the model abstracts away from semantic type coercion, it  Computational Linguistics Volume 29, Number 2 does not distinguish between uses of a verb or adjective that are claimed in the lexical semantics literature to be metonymic uses (e.g., enjoy the book, fast programmer) and those that are claimed to be nonmetonymic uses (e.g., enjoy the marriage, fast run-time). Again, the model of interpretation presented here will generate paraphrases for all these cases (e.g., it will paraphrase enjoy the marriage as enjoy going to or participating in the marriage and fast run-time as run-time that goes by or passes quickly). The model also does not take discourse context into account; for example, it will not predict the intuitive interpretation of (5e). Rather, it determines the most dominant meanings for a given metonymic construction overall, across all of the instances of it in the corpus. The remainder of this article is organized as follows: in the first part (Section 2) we present our probabilistic model of verbal logical metonymy and describe the model parameters. In Experiment 1 we use the model to derive the meaning paraphrases for verb-noun combinations randomly selected from the BNC (see Section 2.3) and formally evaluate our results against human intuitions. Experiment 2 demonstrates that when compared against human judgments, our model outperforms a naive baseline in deriving a preference ordering for the meanings of verb-noun combinations, and Experiment 3 evaluates an extension of the basic model. In the second part (Section 3), we focus on adjectival logical metonymy. Section 3.1 introduces our probabilistic formalization for polysemous metonymic adjectives and Sections 3.3-3.6 present our experiments and evaluate our results. Overall, the automatically acquired model of logical metonymy reliably correlates with human intuitions and also predicts the relative degree of ambiguity and acceptability of the various metonymic constructions. In Section 4 we discuss our results, we review related work in Section 5, and we conclude in Section 6.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

