<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W03-1801">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 N. Aussenac-Gilles, B. Biebow, and S. Szulman. 2003. D'une mthode a un guide pratique de modlisation de connaissances a partir de textes. In Proc. of the 5th Conference on Terminologie et Intelligence Artificielle, Strasbourg, March 31 -April 1.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 2 Ken Barker , Stan Szpakowicz, Semi-automatic recognition of noun modifier relationships, Proceedings of the 17th international conference on Computational linguistics, August 10-14, 1998, Montreal, Quebec, Canada 3 D. Bourigault, C. Jacquemin, and M-C. L'Homme, editors. 2001. Recent Advances in Computational Terminology, volume 2. John Benjamins.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 4 J. Dowdall, M. Hess, N. Kahusk, K. Kaljurand, M. Koit, F. Rinaldi, and K. Vider. 2002. Technical Terminology as a Critical Resource. In Proc. of LREC-02, Las Palmas, 29--31 May.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 5 P. Downing. 1977. On the creation and use of english compound nouns. Language, (53):810--842.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 6 D. A Evans, R. G. Lefferts, G. Grefenstette, S. K. Handerson, W. R. Hersh, and A. A. Archbold. 1992. CLARIT TREC design, experiments and results. Technical report, Carnegie Mellon University.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 7 T. Finin. 1980. The semantic interpretation of nominal compounds. In Proceedings &amp;quot;Artificial Intelligence, pages 310 - 312. Stanford.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 8 L. Gay , W. Croft, Interpreting nominal compounds for information retrieval, Information Processing and Management: an International Journal, v.26 n.1, p.21-38, 1990 9 F. Ibekwe-SanJuan and E. SanJuan. 2003. From term variants to research topics. Journal of Knowledge Organization (ISKO), special issue on Human Language Technology, 29(3/4).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 10 Fidelia Ibekwe-Sanjuan, Terminological variation, a means of identifying research topics from texts, Proceedings of the 17th international conference on Computational linguistics, August 10-14, 1998, Montreal, Quebec, Canada 11 F. Ibekwe-SanJuan. 2001. Extraction terminologique avec intex. In Proc. of the 4th Annual INTEX Workshop, Bordeaux, 10--11 June.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> 12 Pierre Isabelle, Another look at nominal compounds, Proceedings of the 22nd annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.509-516, July 02-06, 1984, Stanford, California 13 C. Jacquemin. 1995. A symbolic and surgical acquisition of terms through variation. In Proc. of IJCAI95, Montral.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> 14 C. Jacquemin. 2001. Spotting and discovering terms through Natural Language Processing. MIT Press.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> 15 K. Kageura. 2002. The dynamics of Terminology: A descriptive theory of term formation and terminological growth. John Benjamins, Amsterdam.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> 16 J. N. Levi. 1979. The syntax and semantics of complex nominals. Academic press, New York.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> 17 J. Pearson. 1998. Terms in Context. John Benjamins, Amsterdam.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

