<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J79-1067">
<Title>HELPING-GAME Paramctcrs: Thc parameters are two roles (HELPER and HELPEE) and a topic (TASK/HG). A Modcl of Dialogue Parameter specifications:</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
SUMMARY
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Within a view of ianguagc users as problem solvers, speakers arc seen as creating uttcrsnccs in pursuit of thcir own goals. Dialogue &amp;quot;works&amp;quot; because this activity tends to scrvc goals of both participants. ,k Hcncc, for the model of dialogue cornprchcnsion prcscnted here, rccognifion of these goals of the speaker is central to the comprehension  of dialo~uc, Wc have found that dialogues arc conrposud of structured interactions rcpresanted by collections of knowledge which dcscri be the intcrrelatcd goals of the participants. We call thcsc knawlcd~c structures &amp;quot;Dialogue-games&amp;quot; (DGg). This paper describes DGs in gcncral, a particular one (the Hclping-DG) in some detail, how OGs are used by our Dialog~c-game Model (DGM), and the benefits of this model.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> A DG consists of three parts: the Parameters (the two roles fillcd by thc participants, and the topic), the Pnramcter Spccifications (a set of predicates on the Pararndcrs), and the Components (a sequcncc of goals hgld by the participants in the course of the dialogue).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> For cxample, in the Helping-DG, the Parameters are HELPER, HELPEE (the rolcs) and TASK (the topic). The Spccifications are: 1) The HELPEE wants to pertorm the TASK: 2) thc HELPEE wants to bc a6/e to do it but 3) the HELPEE is not able to. 4) The ILELPER wants to enable the HELPEE to do the TASK and 5) the HELPER is ab/e to provide this help. The Componcntr specify that 1) the HELPEE wants to establish a context by describing a collection of unexceptional events (a parlial performance of the TASK): 2) he also wants to dcscribc some sort of unresirable surprise: then 3) the. I-IELPER wants to cxplain the violation of expectation so that the HELPEE can avoid it a'nd get on with the TASK.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The DGM makes use of DGs in fiue stages of processing: Nomination, Recognition, Instantiation, Conduct and Termination.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Thc DGM models each participant's knowlcd,ge, goal and attention states. A mcchanisrn adds to the attention state, cmcepts &amp;quot;suggested&amp;quot; by those already in attention. Whcn a hearer sees himself or his partner as potentially filling a role in a DG(by fulfilling one or more demands of the DG's Specifications) then that DG is brought into attention (Nominated), DGs can bc nominated by weak evidence: Recognition is the step of verifying that these DGs arc plausibly consistent with the currcnt state of the model. Thosa which arc not are eliminated from attention.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> A Model of Dialogue DGs which survive Lhc Recognition stagp arc Instantiated by asserting (as assumptions) all the Specifications not ye1 rcprcscnicd as holding. For example, when a person says &amp;quot;Do you have a match?&amp;quot;, instantiation, by the hcarer (of the-~ction-sck DG) dcrivcs asscrtionr; that thc speaker does not have a match and wants the hcarer to give him one, The Conduct of ihc DG is rnodclcd by tracking the pursuit and fulfillment of the participants' goals as rcprescntcd in the Components.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Whcn tho DGM dctcpls that onc parlicipant no longer regards a Specification as holding, this crcatcs an cxpcctation of the Termination of this phase of the dialogue--there is no longer a possibility that it will serve both participants' goals, Thc appendix contains a detailed hand-simulation of the DGM assimilating a scgrncnt of a dialogue.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> A Modcl of Dialogue</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

