<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J79-1054">
<Title>Association for Computational Linguist ~CS</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="4" end_page="4" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
3 *
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> the lcnowledge environment of the ,;yntcm, 1; I. L :.hc ti::ol s a credously accepting everything v~lirlt io said. It ir evidently quite easy both for humans and computers; in practice hunan.1 apply this strategy mainly when they are forced to devote rnor3.tof their computational power to other tasks of a higher priority.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Between these two extrenes there exist many mixed strategies, where the system for every person of the aiscourse makes an independent decision, whether or not to create a new environment, based both on the reliability of the person and the avallabilits of resources, r T-opic environments, The usual way of handling the reference problem is to compute for every noun phrase or pronoun a separate list of possible referents afid to use some heuristics to choose one element from the list. Another approach, advocated here, consists in storing all possible referents permanently available into a special topic environments. The items stored in the topic environments may be the symbols of physical object as we21 as some relations and other semantic data structures, put there during the evaluation of respective,linguiotic constructs. In particular, thr indefi-nite dttscriptioi1~ of the type (3ellcrt 197':: 32)  (37) It is a foreigner who is delivering espeech now.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> (38) One young boy has flunked his mtriculetion exem,  are interpreted as declarations, used to create appropriate data structure3 to be put into the topic; therefore do r.ct need the Ref operator of Bellcrt (1372:3 ) introduced to ksndlr such examples.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> In every topic environment the items are rdered in ooxe way; the access routine 1 cn re quest the mbseqirent elements uf the topic in the very order; if the environment is exhausted and some new candidate for a referent is nee6ed, tae ac em routine switches to the respective super-envirorment.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> hkery succesful access to the topic cauees it-s pe~mutation,~vhich results 5-11 making the accessed item thc first element of tile environment.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The essential difference bet~~*ec:: the traditional approach and that presented he17e lies in the possibility o&amp;quot; st^. ct~rine, a topic enviror~?.ent.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> For example (~sard 1974a), in the text:  (~9.1) ;'!hat did John say about; Dick? (39.2) He said that (39.3) he looked like a druaken giraffe cn ibe skates.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7">  there is co doubt that hhe&amp;quot; of i.39 '3) refers to Dick.-ile account ioz* it in the following way: every first use of a vero of the '\verbLm diccndi'' f-yp.l,e c3uaea a 1 topic environment to be created; tile environment is ntali, in our case to Dick and tlle~~ itcelf bec~mes an item of the current topic. Tr~e next mention of that act of communicatio~ cQU:ie:; the se~rch in tire current topi0 for the environment previously stored ; vhen it ic found, the reported clause is interpreted within it. Tn our ceoe the first word oi: the reported clause is -\;he pronoun &amp;quot;he\' which calls the access routine for a posoiblc referent. 4s tho first and only possible relerent of the current toplc is 1)i.c~ the pronoun is properly bound.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> In the caze of the text (40.1 ) '#Rat bid John sag about nicp? (40.2) iie sald that (40.3) te doubted whethlr irick would like it.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> tile pronoun will be also at first bound to Dick from the topic \\ But when the proper name ~ick&amp;quot; will be evaluated, an attempt will be made to shift ilick to the first positiou in the topic where it already is located. This is a violation of the elfi~ ciency rde, and this interpretation will e rejected. Rext possible refrent will then be obtaln from the super-environment yielding the correct result.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> There are some exceptions to the efficiency rule; in particular redundancy is desirable immediately after topic switching:  (4 1.1) Ylhat did John say about Dick? (4 t .r) He naid that (41l.3) Dick Tooked like b drunken gird~fc or. i~e l:ates. Another al-gur~ellt for topic : t:*uctullint; is ti:c exist P:.~c iYT xi': (42) Jnnet, M.11 and 1 sis t ex1 tir.lc:l :.:ere cut ::l&lt;e, it Janet Baid: 1' calibt keep this kitten. 'Jould you like to 'I\ \\ \\ \ .,* hdve itr liclen? . Yes , mid Helen. Rill said A don't /&lt;now, Remembpr ! t ~k Jcc ted to tphn t robin. &gt;he &amp;quot; \\ would not ict us keep it . But L.other &amp;aid it is cct \' \ i good to keep s robin indoors, sa~d flelen, It is ~ot</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> fair to the robin , Look, sald Janet, D, you want it or not ?\'.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> At this stage the topic problem is the least elaborated part of my multiple ewironments approach;therefore I am not a~le to go into debails here, Fome additional argument in favour of the topic environment ideas will be fcund in the paragraph 4.2. 4, Runninrg an utterance .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> By desimators I understand the linguistic means used to refer to particular objects. Designators may be classified roughly into three classes: proper names; common names and description9. All three kinds of designators have been discussed for centuries by philosophers and logicians; our pragmatic approaah to the designators is based mainly on the works of ICripke (1 972) and Donnellan (1971).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> The characteristic festure of proper names is that their use must be preceded by the act of fixing thdreference. Contrary to popular opinion, in practice proper names we much more ambiguous than common names , because pr ORT names re f er to individuals and common namels to classes of individual^, For example, there are many men called John and if weare to understand e. g.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> (43) John has come.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> we need to have the referent of John already fixed. Different types of object have proper names of different stability. Countries, towns, mountains et c. have of ten unique names which are rarely changed.Most human full names are also rather stable from the practical poiat of view.Forenames are so ambiguous that their referents have to be reset again and again in every discourse, e.g. by quoting the full hame of the person in question. Such proper names as first and second pereon pronouns may alternate their meaning even during one discourse. To sumarize, proper names in fact name some recognition routine supplied in the act of fixing the reference.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="18"> Common names do not refer directly to individuals, but they are names of characteristic functions of the respective sets of individua1s;their mealling is so stable that they can be assumed to belong to the knowledge of the world; and therefore, fixing the reference, except in some peculiar cases, need not be performed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="19"> Descriptions are compound names constructed nd iloc by npccial linguintic means, like qualifyirlg 3 common noun by an ad jcctive etc. They name 31no respective compound chnmctcri~tlc functions, All the desic;n;nators are usually used in tne referential way. That means that tile respctive procedure is cvnlunttJ in a proper environment to yield the intended referent. Such treotmeat agrees in particular with Donnellan's intuition that a definite description does not in itself refer to anything but only its use points to a referent. Therefore, c.e nay explain easily why the sentence (~onnelltln 1971:llO): (44) Her husband is kind to her.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="20"> can be sometimes properly understood even if the man refered to is not the husband of the woman; such a sentence is just to be evaluated in the environment of false belie of the sender.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="21"> Quite often the sender uses undersp'ecified descriptions, i. e. the descriptions which refer to a much larger set of individudls than it is intended, e. g. in Gnarniak ( 1972:72) :  (45.1) Mother made some cookies and left one on a plate.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="22"> (45.2) She put the plate on the kitchen table and went. into living room.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="23">  &amp;quot;the pla~e'' of (45.2) by itself refers to every plate of the world.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="24"> The addressee has in such situations to restrict the respective characteristic function to the object on his current topic; if it does not suffice, he need to eliminat8 the remaining ambiguities in the usual way, i. e. by meano of the coherency, consistency and efficiency rules.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="25"> All designators except pronouns can also be use tn an attributive way. In this case  they mean just their characterintic functions. For example (46) hiount Everst is Chomolungna.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="26"> means that in the sender'a beliefs the characteristic function of fv'lowlt Everest has as well all relevant seatures of Chomolungma. In some other usage the respective characteristic function is to be adapted by the addreL,;ac to he JLL:*-X 11-5  nonspecific setting , e. g. (Charniak 1972:178) a kitten&amp;quot; in (50. 1: (50. I) Jack wanted a kitten.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="27"> (50.2) Bill had a kitten and Jack offered to trade his ball for the kitten.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="28"> (50.3) Bill wanted to keep his kitten, so Jack went to look for George who also had a kitten.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="29"> (50.4) George was willing to trade so Jack got his kitten. It is intereating that the SI1RDLU program (Y/iinograd~l~7 2) treat indefinite descriptions,which are used only at t x~ibutivel~,  '3. g* (51) piclc up a big block (52) find a block which is taller than the one you are  holding and put it into the box just along the lines given above, i. e. as programs with a free variable (Xinograd 1972 : 1 30 1 , a1 though Pinograd himself describes it, probably influenced by the logical tradition, by means of the variable bound by the existential nuantif~er (1972: 126).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="30"> The characteristic feature of proper and cormon nouns lo thet they ore always to be run in a single environment. It is not the case with descriptions which mag require suitable ~plitting between several environments. It has been noted by Winograd (1972: 147) with respct to the tine reference, e. g. : (53) Idany rich men made their fortunes during the depression, (54) Idany rich men lost their fortunes during the depression, (55) Many rich men worked in restaurants during the depression, null \ In these sentences the rich men&amp;quot; phrase is to be evaluated in the present time environment for (53), in the past tine environment for (54), and the sentence (55) is ambiguou:: when taken out of a larger context.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="31"> There are other ainilar case:q, e, g. the acctendc  (56) Smith Knows thdt the friend of i~owal-hic s brother i:: is subject to several interpretation:;; acme of then art3 (57) Smith kncwu Kov~al ski, ICowaZcki s bx*otL-:c~ r'In i,i~ .Criend of ~owalski's brother and Llnimlth lanows that the friend of I(owa1ski ' s brother is a vrrite13.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="32"> (50) Smith does not know Kowalski, but he knows ~owalnki's  brother and the friend of icowalski's brothel. md Smith knows that the friend of ~owalski's brother is a ivriter. Obviously, ' the interpretations (57) and (58) differ in the way \\ the phrase &amp;quot;the friend of Powalskf's brother is split be tween the environments of the knowledge of the sender and the ih?owledge of Smith.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="33"> Mnce we allow designators to switA environm~nts, we have no problem with so called nouns vvi tll erlpty denotdtion ; they are to be evaluated in the respective fictitious worlds, e. g. (59) I met him in the park by the sculpturt. of a faun. 4f2. Pointers.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="34"> In this paragraph we shall dizcuss the reference problem for the third person pronouns,the most important class of pomters. \\ We shall f'ormulatc a rule intendcd to substit~te the connand \\ rule xi' the tmnsf ox?i!ational grammar. The arguaento in J avour of our rule are oinplicity, bcttt~~ odequ~cy and ufiage of t21c demo11 facility whicn should be prerent in the sgstel:: for other reanons ( ~harniak 1972).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="35"> First, we ahall remind that every accesr to the tcpic pe-nutc:: it by advnncicg the ac3crseed element to the very beg inn in^; of the topic; succesful evtlluation of e designator introducing ~1 new aob ject puts the rcpre::ent~tL~:: 3f the obj ect also at the very beginning of the topic. Our rule stdtes that the main L c lause pronouns imrnediat ely execute access .o the !o;Lc, while the evaluation of subordinate clause pronouns rcay be suspnded if tllere io l~c suitable value for them ln the I? topic; all the pronouns s'noYbxld be resolved be t.Tbr ri:t. il!c c~f the main clause processing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="36"> Let us see how the rule works for examples from (:.lcCawiey 1~/1:226).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="37"> (60) 4fter John left his apartment, he we~t to the pool hall. The proper name &amp;quot; ~ohn&amp;quot; advances the J'orm's representation at \\ the beginni~g of the topic. The pronoun his&amp;quot; is evaluated because there is at least one suitable value in Xie topic, i.e. John ; if bounding of\'his&amp;quot; to John is rejected by some r\ \\ pragmatic rule, another possible referent is found, ne is set to it and the referent is advanced at the beginning of the t @pic, getting ahead of John , Vhen &amp;quot;her is evaluated, '\ it is us~elly bound to the same referent as his&amp;quot;, which may be John or some other person.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="38"> (bl) After he left his apartment, John went to the pool hall, &amp;quot; ~fter&amp;quot; introduces a subordinate clause, whii.h may be auo\\ null pended if there iz no quitablc value for '\he\' or &amp;quot;i7is in the topic; if the clause io suspended, it can be roomed :.dlen \\ \\ evaluation of Joh~ puts its valuc to the topic.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="39"> (62) Joha -:ient to the pool room uf ter he left :.;is cpartnent. \\ \\ There is no problem with the sentence ; John sets the topic \i supplying a possible value for &amp;quot;he\\ and his&amp;quot;. (63) He went to the pool hall after John left his apartment. The &amp;quot;he&amp;quot; is evaluated immediately; therefore the evaluation of &amp;quot; ~ohn&amp;quot; cannot influeace its value. The strong feeling that the value of &amp;quot;he&amp;quot; should be different from John is explained as the violation of the efficiency rule: if you can refer to an object by a pointer and there is no possibility of misunderstqnding, do not refer to it by a designator. (64) A boy who saw her kissed a girl who knew him.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="40"> I am anxious to see a sentence of this type in an authentic English text, not as an example of areference problem, because I do not see any circumstances under which such a sentence can be uttered. Bone the less, we can handle thehexample easily. First, a boy&amp;quot; is evaluated, yielding a per son environment v~hich I L is put into the topic. Next, who saw her&amp;quot; is evaluated except for the \her\' because of the lack of a suitable value for ;t In the topic ; therefore , the clause is xuopendod, '!!hen the rest of the main clause 1s evaluated and the peraon environm~nt for \\ H is created, resulting in an updating of the topic.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="41"> Now the suspended clause can be reoumed and evaluated in paral\\ null lel with ti12 clause who knew hid' ; all the pronoun:: will be properly bound.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="42"> Althougll it should be obvious, it is better to state explicitg that the value of his in (60)-(s3) is finally fixed by tile coherency rule.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="43"> Analogically as with subordinate clauses, we can treat parenthethical clauses and phrases, e. g.: (b5) In ~ohn's apartment, he smskes pot.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="44"> (66) In his apartment, John smolces pot, and obtain the desired results, It is hoped that the above discussion together with works of Isard, Davies and Longuet-Higgins has shown the advantage of treaking discourses and utterances as programs. Below we give an additional argument in favour of this approach, based on an article by Karttunen (1974). He presented difficulties related to finding the presupposition for a compound sentence and suggested they b'e avoided by adopting the more dynamic approach of a recursive verification of the satisfaction of presupposit ion&amp;quot; condition. This idea can be ea~ily integrnted in our model, as it is test illuatratcd from examples  (67) If Dean told the tru-tih, Nixon ia guilty too.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="45"> (bR) if Haldeman is guilty, Nixon is guilty too.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="46"> (69) If Miss Woods destroyed the missing tapes, Nixon is  guilty too.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="47"> The consequent clause in 911 of these prenupposca the guilt of someone else, but the presupposition of the irholc sentences J&amp;quot;.? -?; 1 - ; , , $1,1,)differ: (b8) definitely do-:: not prc;;~1i);)3.. .IL c,LLLolio i- Ise vfkila (67) and (69) may presuppose it or not, depending upon the circumstances of their use. In our model the antecedent clauses are run before the consequent clause; therefore in (68) the presupposition of the consequent clause is satisfied by the antecedent and in (6'1) and (b9) it can also be the case, depending upon the other knowledge available. in the environment of the evaluation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="48"> , Conclusions.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="49"> &amp;en if some of the presented ideas may becoae obsolete throught further research, the usefulnew of the soph~ s*~ated environment B trmctures for natural language descriptions se ems evident. The notion of environment deserves a place as a crucial notion in a fully adequate theory of natural language. It is important that the environment structures postulated here involve quite complicated embedding of environments without any static restrictions on the depth of the embedding. At the preoent state of art, it is convenient to deocribe such struct6reo in . .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="50"> terms of computer science, because e. g, t'o1~1e.l 1ot;i.c LA i.~ - rk only u 1 -~213. ': 1~1,s bc tneen di fi'erent po~ciblr coslds . This fact, together with some other advantages shorvn in the papey, makes a strong argument in favour of treating discourses and ut t erances as pr ograrns .</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

