<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C92-4194">
<Title>Institute of History and Philology Academia Sinica</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
2) The Classical Corpns
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Roughly three million characters of Chinese written prose have smvived frmn the years before Christ was born (i.e. from all tile periods up to the Western Hart Dynasty). A corpus of roughly 1.5 million characters of the text is now available in machine readable forms from a previous prolect in Academia Sinica, the remaining 1.5 million characters arc now being keyed in and will be on-line by mid-1992.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 111. Functions and Applications It is out&amp;quot; hmg term goals for the Corpus to have the automatic dictionary compiling abilities, fashioned aftcr COBUILI) (Sinclair 1987, iN)l), adapted for both parsing and hard- copy publishing. In the flirt stage, however, we concentrate on developing tools for linguistic research. We will describe the search functions that we have developed so far. Most of the functions are character-based now and call be upgraded to word-based once we incorporate our tagger and word segmentation naKlule.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The search utility in our corpus is basically a KWIC (key wtlrd-in~m-- text) search based on Chinese characters. Our search progranl allows the linguists to specify both the size of right-and left-hallO side cxmtext sh(lwn as the search resnlt. There is also a randomizer to chm)se a more manageable size of data if the search result is too big (more than a thou- sand citations). The ordering of data is done in the traditional way in terms of nu tubers of strokes in tile character in the immediate context. This is not the ideal methtxl but may be the best available before we can deveh)p a system which is ln)ttt linguistically and hem-istically more ~phisticated. A romanizatiml based articling s~ystem would be even less desirable fl)r the lack of unifl~rm (and familiar) romanization system ill 'lliiwan and h~r the failure to disamhiguiate homonyms.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> In addition to the basic s(~irell procedures, the following customized search commands are added to serve tile need of linguistic research.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  is 'left- disassociatcd' fronl another key word (kwl), i.e. where the sccnnd key word does not (recur in the left-context of the first key word.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 6) &lt; kwl &gt;/r &lt; kw2 &gt; : context where a key word (kw2) is 'right-disassociated' from another key word (kwl), i.e. where tile secured key word does not occur in the right-context of the first key word.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> t ;ommands 1)-3) are helpful tools in studying morphological rules and identifying morphological constmctions for Chinese. Since Chinese writing systems do not include word-breaks, and since no lexicon can ever offer a complete list of words, word segmentatkm is non-trivial in Chinese Language Processing (Chert and Liu 1992). Identifying and util~ing morphological information is therefore essential Ix)th in lexical computing and in natural language processing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> ACnT.S Dr. COLING-92, NANTES, 23-28 Ao(rr 1992 1 2 1 5 PROC. OF COLING-92, NAN-rES, AUG. 23-28, 1992 Command 4) is a handy tool to discover cooccurrence restrictions and their semantic consequences. Commands 5) and 6) are used to eliminate ambiguity and to cut down the size of search results.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> It can be noted that since our tagger is not running yet and since the Chinese running text seldom defines a sentence by a period (a whole paragraph often contains only one period and many commas), the above commands use number of characters rather than sentence markers to delimit search domains.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> Concordance programs are also being developed for our project. The current version runs with our classical corpus. It is able to show both the text source of each concordance item as well as page numbers from the printed version for easy reference. This is originally developed on the HP workstation, the machine we now use, but a version that runs on IBM PC 486 with either SUN Unix or CCL Unix is also available now.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> Another research tool that we developed deal with frequency counts of characters and words and statistical packages to compare linguistics and other textual features of the corpora. Like many other modules of our project, this module has been developed and completed mdependently. It has been tested on the untagged on-line classical Chinese database of the &amp;quot;l~,enty-five Dynastic Histories (Hsieh 1991). This module is ready to be incorporated into the system.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> IV. Accomplishments and Future Developments In this first stage of the development of a Chinese corpus for NLP and for linguistic research, we have achieved the primary goals of acquiring the core text data, and establishing a mutual-supporting environment between the lexical computing research on the corpus and the computational linguistics research on NLE Our systems are developed on HP workstations under Unix. The system should be portable to any Unix machine with compatible Chinese solution. For instance, we are porting each of our modules to a IBM PC 486 running Unix for the use of our collaborator in London. null In this preliminary stage, the most encouraging sign is that our human linguists have established productive interaction with the corpus. Human expertise helped to design search utilities pertinent to linguistic research and corpora provided both a convenient source of linguistic facts and a solid basis for deducing useful generalizations. With the basic KWIC search utilities, the CKIP project has finished several linguistic studies with the help of the corpus. Take Mo et al. (1991) for exampie, the quantifier-measure rule that our analyzer-generator uses is based on generalizations extracted from the corpus, and the program itsetf is tested on texts randomly selected from the corpus. Other linguistic works based on the corpus include Hong, Huang and Chen (1991) on morphological rules fl)r Chinese, and Mo, Huang and Chen on serial verb construction in Chinese (1991). This corpus is currently used by the CKIP project in their ac- counts of A-not-A questions, of resultative compounding, of nominalization, and of various reduplications.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> Incorporation of an automatic tagger and extraction of grammatical information from the tagged corpora is the most important immediate future goals of this project. This, of course, depends crucially on a tagging system with theoretically well-structured attributes. A database for attributes is being developed with the 1N-FORMIX software. And we will folh)w the TEl guidelines (Sperber-McQueen and Burnard 1990) whenever possible. Our word segmentation program now doubles as a category-tagger. But this can only be viewed as a research aid for the linguists to detect categorical ambiguities and unlisted words. We also expect the on-goo ing linguistic research to identify more search functions and refine the existing utilities. Direct extraction of dictionaries and grammars should I)c feasible in five years.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> Aeknowlegements: Research of this project was partially funded by the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchanges. The first author wants to express his gratitude to the Center for the Study of Language and Information, Stanford University for thc surport he received when he visited there, during which a draft of this note was completed. Responsibility of any errors remain ours alone.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

