<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C92-2114">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper shows how lexical choice during text generation depemls on linguistic context. We argue that muking c(Irrect lexieal choice in rite textual context requires distinguishing properties of concepts, which are ntme or less independent of file language, from language-specific representations of text where lexemes and their semantic and symantic relations are represented. In particular, l.exical Fnnctions are well-suited to tormalizing anaphoric lexical links in text, including the introduction of superordinates. This sheds new light on the notion of &amp;quot;basic level&amp;quot;, which has recently been applied to lexieM selection in genaration. Some consh'aints governing rite generation of lexical nnd grammatical anaphora are proposed for procedural text, using examples front tim sublanguage of recipes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> O. Introduction Lexical choice cannot be made dining text generation wifltottt taking into account the linguistic context, both the lexical context of inmmdiately surrounding words and rite larger textual context.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> a) Lexical context consists of the words (or lather, the lexicnl specifications of nascent words) that enter into syntactic relations with the lexical item being generated.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> This intrn-clausal context is crncial lor lk)rmnlating collocational constraints, which restrict ways of expressing a preci~ meaning to certain lexical items, lot example as in expressions like pay attention, receive attention or narrow escape. The importance of eollocational constraiuts hlts IR3en emphasized in the literature on text generation aud inachine translation (Bateman &amp; Wanner 1990, lordanskaja et al. 1991, Nirenbnrg &amp; Nirenbnrg 1988, Held &amp; Raab 1989).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> b) Textual conlext consists of the linguistic content of previous and subsequent clauses. This context is tile scope for cohesive links (ttalliday &amp; Hasan 1976) with the lexical items m be generated in the current clause.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The gn'eat majority of cohesivc links are anaphoric in nature 2. A textnal element T is an attaphor with reslmct to an antecexlent A (previtmsly introdacexl in the text) if the semantic or referential interpretation of T ~ depends on the interpretation of A. When genmating auallhttrs, it is Iberefot~ the previotts context that ntust bc taken inlo acconn\[, ItS ill: I) Now in Centre National d'Etudes des T61dcommunications,  LAA/SLC\]AIA, Route de Trdgnstel BP 40 22301 l..unifion Cddex, Frmice.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 2) In the case of ca!alphorn, as in rite following sentence, If you want to, peel and chop the lualatoes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> tile subsequent context mr,st be taken into account.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> 3) Reference of a textual elemeut is file association betwean n textual eleme, nt and extra-linguistic reality.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> (1) ihel)am tile carrots, the celery mid the asparagus.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10">  Cook tile vegetables in I~iling wat,~&amp;quot; for ten minutes. Two textual clement are coreferential if they t-eli:r to the same exlralinguistic reality. Coreierential elentenls in our examples are often written ill italics, or indicated by identical snbsctipts.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> Faihue Rt ch~.R)se all appropriate anaphoric expression daring generation typically lcads to awkward or nnacceptable text such as (2): (2) a. l:'repme the t:aTmts, the celery and the asparagus. b. Cook tile caners, the celcly and tile aslmragos in N)iling wateL c. Take tile carrots, tile celery and the asparagus otlt at'tel tell ninltltes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> Ill this paper, we examine the mechanisms required fox' making natural lexical choice as a lunetion of preceding text tlud its reference to extralingttistic objtx:ls or concepts. In particular, we are interested ill lexical anal)hera, wllere open-class lexical items or exl)ressions provide a coroference link to one or nlore snch items ill preceding clanses. For example, ill (1) vegetables is a lexicat corefercntial anaphor of the carrots, the celery and the asparagus..</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> ht what fallows, we ainl to show that correct lexicalization in context reqnires access to both the ctntcepnml relmence and the linguistic prolmrties of preceding text. For it pipelined generation architcctmc which \[naps froln abstract representation levels towards text, this implies distinguishing at conceptual level, more or less independent of the language, ti'oln language-specific representation levels which encode lexemes and the grammatical relation between thenl. In particular, we illustrate the paradignlatic Lexical l'unctkms (hereafter  1. Varieties of lexical anapbora  Beft)re reviewing conshaints on tile introduction of lexical anal)hera during generation, we give examples of inlportant tYlmS of cm'eferential anaphoric links 4.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> We consider an anallher 10 13(3 lexical only if we can  the coreferential link between the two phrases is based on world knowledge, and not on linguistic semantics.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> One type of coreferential lexical anaphora is called &amp;quot;reiteration&amp;quot; by Halliday &amp; Hasan (1976) with three subtypes: exact repetition, illusWated by (4b), synonym substitution (4b'), and superordinate substitution (4b&amp;quot;). We can add to this group partial repetition (4b&amp;quot;'):  (4) a. 1 bottle of light red bordeaux.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> b. Pour the light red bordeaux on the meat.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> b'. Pour the lieht red bordeaux wine on the meat.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="18"> b&amp;quot;. Pour the ~ oct the meat.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="19"> b'&amp;quot;. Pour the ~ on the meat.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="20"> Nominalization provides another way of introducing a coreferential link to a previous verb: (5) Cook the rabbit for two hours.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="21"> Ten minutes before the end of cooking, add the spices. Coreferential lexical links can also be established between an action and its result.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="22"> (6) Meanwhile. mix the egg yolki with the sugarj.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="23">  Pour the milk on the mixturei+ j.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="24"> In this example, mixture has no direct semantic link with its antecedents egg yolk and sugar. The link appears indirectly through the verb mix.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="25"> Another type of lexical anaphora occurs with nouns denoting typical actants of an antecedent verb: (7) Marga i was lecturing to third year students k. The lecturer i was very interesting and the audience k quite attentive. In this case, lecturer is linked coreferentially with Marga because it is the &amp;quot;agent noun&amp;quot; of lecture, while audience is the corresponding &amp;quot;patient noun&amp;quot;, and is coreferential with third year students.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="26"> These examples illustrate some of the diversity of lexico-semantic resources needed to build coreferential links in text. Text generation therefore requires a lexicon which gives access to the full range of such resources from the &amp;quot;viewpoint&amp;quot; of the antecedent lexeme. As seen in the next section, LFs provide an appropriate access mechanism for choosing the correct anaphor.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

