<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J95-2005">
<Title>Squibs and Discussions Efficient Parsing for Korean and English: A Parameterized Message-Passing Approach</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This article presents an efficient, implemented approach to cross-linguistic parsing based on Government Binding (GB) Theory (Chomsky 1986) and followers. One of the drawbacks to alternative GB-based parsing approaches is that they generally adopt a filter-based paradigm. These approaches typically generate all possible candidate structures of the sentence that satisfy X theory, and then subsequently apply filters in order to eliminate those structures that violate GB principles. (See, for example, Abney 1989; Correa 1991; Dorr 1993; Fong 1991.) The current approach provides an alternative to filter-based designs that avoids these difficulties by applying principles to descriptions of structures without actually building the structures themselves. Our approach is similar to that of Lin (1993) in that structure-building is deferred until the descriptions satisfy all principles; however, the current approach differs in that it provides a parameterization mechanism along the lines of Dorr (1994) that allows the system to be ported to languages other than English. We focus particularly on the problem of processing head-final languages such as Korean.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> We are currently incorporating the parser into a machine translation (MT) system called PRINCITRAN. l In general, parsers of existing principle-based interlingual MT systems are exceedingly inefficient, since they tend to adopt the filter-based paradigm.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> We combine the benefits of the message-passing paradigm with the benefits of the parameterized approach to build a more efficient, but easily extensible system, that will ultimately be used for MT. The algorithm has been implemented in C++ and successfully tested on well-known, translationally divergent sentences.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> We present a general framework for parsing by message passing and describe our implementation of GB principles as attribute-value constraints. We then present the parameterization framework, demonstrating the feasibility of handling cross-linguistic variation within the message-passing framework. A technique for automatic precompilation of parameter settings is described. Finally, we compare the efficiency of the  ,,', ,, Cbar .........</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> / ', ', C . &amp;quot;., At&amp;quot; ~. 1~1 &amp;quot; , &amp;quot;-..N INI ~ : Vk' .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> /i. ............... . \ ............................. UY-&amp;quot; English Grammar Network Korean Grammar Network n ............... ~ :~ head domina e adjunct dominance complement dominance 7 ......... :~&amp;quot; m specializati specifier dominance barrier  Figure 1 Network representation of English and Korean grammar.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> parser to that of the original CFG algorithm as well as Tomita's algorithm (Tomita 1986) on a test suite of representative sentences. We argue that the efficiency of the system is not simply a side effect of using an efficient programming language (i.e., C++), but that the algorithm is inherently efficient, independent of the programming language used for the implementation.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

