<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J98-1001">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The automatic disambiguation of word senses hasbeen an interest and concern since the earliest days of computer treatment of language in the 1950s. Sense disambiguation is an &amp;quot;intermediate task&amp;quot; (Wilks and Stevenson 1996), which is not an end in itself, but rather is necessary at one level or another to accomplish most natural language processing tasks. It is obviously essential for language understanding applications, such as message understanding and man-machine communication; it is at least helpful, and in some instances required, for applications whose aim is not language understanding: * machine translation: sense disambiguation is essential for the proper translation of words such as the French grille, which, depending on the context, can be translated as railings, gate, bar, grid, scale, schedule, etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> (see, for instance Weaver \[1955\], Yngve \[1955\]).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> * information retrieval and hypertext navigation: when searching for specific keywords, it is desirable to eliminate occurrences in documents where the word or words are used in an inappropriate sense; for example, when searching for judicial references, it is desirable to eliminate documents containing the word court as associated with royalty, rather than with law (see, for instance, Salton \[1968\], Salton and McGill \[1983\], Krovetz and Croft \[1992\], Voorhees \[1993\], Schfitze and Pedersen \[1995\]).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> * content and thematic analysis: a common approach to content and thematic analysis is to analyze the distribution of predefined categories of words--i.e., words indicative of a given concept, idea, theme, etc.--across a text. The need for sense disambiguation in such analysis, in order to include only those instances of a word in its proper sense, has long been recognized (see, for instance, Stone et al. \[1966\], Stone \[1969\], Kelly and Stone \[1975\]; for a more recent discussion see Litowski \[1997\]).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> * grammatical analysis: sense disambiguation is useful for part-of-speech tagging for example, in the French sentence L'~tag~re plie sous les livres ('The shelf is bending under \[the weight of\] the books'), it is necessary to disambiguate the sense of livres (which can mean 'books' or 'pounds' * Department of Computer Science, Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York 12604-0520. E-mail: ide@cs.vassar.edu ~ Laboratoire Parole et Langage, ESA 6057 CNRS, Universit~ de Provence, 29 Avenue Robert Schuman, 13621 Aix-en-Provence Cedex 1, France. E-mail: Jean.Veronis@lpl.univ-aix.fr (~) 1998 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 24, Number 1 and is masculine in the former sense, feminine in the latter) to properly tag it as a masculine noun. Sense disambiguation is also necessary for certain syntactic analyses, such as prepositional phrase attachment (Jensen and Binot 1987; Whittemore, Ferrara, and Brunner 1990; Hindle and Rooth 1993), and, in general, restricts the space of competing parses (Alshawi and Carter 1994).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> speech processing: sense disambiguation is required for correct phonetization of words in speech synthesis, for example, the word conjure in He conjured up an image or in I conjure you to help me (Sproat, Hirschberg, and Yarowsky 1992; Yarowsky 1997), and also for word segmentation and homophone discrimination in speech recognition (Connine 1990; Seneff 1992).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> text processing: sense disambiguation is necessary for spelling correction (for example, to determine when diacritics should be inserted, such as in French, changing comte to comte \[Yarowsky 1994a, 1994b\]); for case changes (HE READ THE TIMES ~ He read the Times); for lexical access of Semitic languages (in which vowels are not written), etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> The problem of word sense disambiguation (WSD) has been described as &amp;quot;AI-complete,&amp;quot; that is, a problem which can be solved only by first resolving all the difficult problems in artificial intelligence (AI), such as the representation of common sense and encyclopedic knowledge. The inherent difficulty of sense disambiguation was a central point in Bar-Hillel's well-known treatise on machine translation (Bar-Hillel 1960), where he asserted that he saw no means by which the sense of the word pen in the sentence The box is in the pen could be determined automatically. Bar-Hillel's argument laid the groundwork for the ALPAC report (ALPAC 1966), which is generally regarded as the direct cause for the abandonment of most research on machine translation in the early 1960s.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> At about the same time, considerable progress was being made in the area of knowledge representation, especially the emergence of semantic networks, which were immediately applied to sense disambiguation. Work on word sense disambiguation continued throughout the next two decades in the framework of AI-based natural language understanding research, as well as in the fields of content analysis, stylistic * and literary analysis, and information retrieval. In the past ten years, attempts to automatically disambiguate word senses have multiplied, due, like much other similar activity in the field of computational linguistics, to the availability of large amounts of machine-readable text and the corresponding development of statistical methods to identify and apply information about regularities in this data. Now that other problems amenable to these methods, such as part-of-speech disambiguation and alignment of parallel translations, have been fairly thoroughly addressed, the problem of word sense disambiguation has taken center stage, and it is frequently cited as one of the most important problems in natural language processing research today.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> Given the progress that has been recently made in WSD research and the rapid development of methods for solving the problem, it is appropriate at this time to stand back and assess the state of the field and to consider the next steps that need to be taken. To this end, this paper surveys the major, well-known approaches to word sense disambiguation and considers the open problems and directions of future research.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> Ide and V4ronis Introduction</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

