<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J98-3001">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> There are two sides to natural language processing. On the one hand, work in natural language understanding is concerned with the mapping from some surface representation of linguistic material expressed as speech or text--to an underlying representation of the meaning carried by that surface representation. But there is also the question of how one maps from some underlying representation of meaning into text or speech: this is the domain of natural language generation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Whether our end-goal is the construction of artifacts that use natural languages intelligently, the formal characterization of phenomena in human languages, or the computational modeling of the human language processing mechanism, we cannot ignore the fact that language is both spoken (or written) and heard (or read). Both are equally large and important problems, but the literature contains much less work on natural language generation (NLG) than it does on natural language understanding (NLU). There are many reasons why this might be so, although clearly an important one is that researchers in natural language understanding in some sense start out with a more well-defined task: the input is known, and there is a lot of it around. This is not the case in natural language generation: there, it is the desired output that is known, but the input is an unknown; and while the world is awash with text waiting to be processed, there are fewer instances of what we might consider appropriate inputs for the process of natural language generation. For researchers in the field, this highlights the fundamental question that always has to be asked: What do we generate from? Despite this problem, the natural language generation community is a thriving one, with a research base that has been developing steadily--although perhaps at a slower pace because of the smaller size of the community--for just as long as work in natural language understanding. It should not be forgotten that much of NLP has its origins in the early work on machine translation in the 1950s; and that to carry out machine translation, one has to not only analyze existing texts but also to generate new ones. The early machine translation experiments, however, did not recognize the problems that give modern work in NLG its particular character. The first significant pieces of work in the field appeared during the 1970s; in particular, Goldman's work on the problem of lexicalizing underlying conceptual material (Goldman 1974) and  * School of Mathematics, Physics, Computing and Electronics, Sydney NSW 2109, Australia t Learning Research and Development Center, 3939 O'Hara Street, Pittsburgh, PA 15260, U.S.A. :~ Information Technology Research Institute, Lewes Road, Brighton BN2 4GJ, UK (~) 1998 Association for Computational Linguistics  Computational Linguistics Volume 24, Number 3 Davey's work on the generation of paragraph-long descriptions of tic-tac-toe games (Davey 1979) were among the first to focus on issues unique to NLG. The field really took off, however, in the 1980s; for those working in NLG, the decade began with a bang, and the Ph.D. theses of McDonald (1980), Appelt (1981), and McKeown (1982) have had a lasting impact on the shape of the field) But what has happened in the last fifteen years since those major pieces of work first appeared? Although one does find articles on NLG in the pages of Computational Linguistics and other journals in the field, and papers on generation do appear at the major NLP conferences, the quantity and range of work being carried out in NLG tends to be underrepresented in these forums. Instead, the community has tended to present its results at the two biennial series of workshops--one European and one international--that have sprung up in the last ten years. Many of these workshops have led to books: see Kempen (1987); McDonald and Bolc (1988); Zock and Sabah (1988); Dale, Mellish, and Zock (1990); Paris, Swartout, and Mann (1991); Dale et al. (1992); Horacek and Zock (1993); and Adorni and Zock (1996). This special issue of Computational Linguistics was inspired by discussions at the International Workshop on Natural Language Generation held in Herstmonceux in 1996; the aim of the volume you are reading is to show the wider computational linguistics community something of the range of activities in NLG.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

