<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P98-2175">
<Title>An Intelligent Multi-Dictionary Environment Gdbor Pr6sz6ky MorphoLogic</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="1067" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> An open, extendible multi-dictionary system is introduced in the paper. It supports the translator in accessing adequate entries of various bi- and monolingual dictionaries and translation examples from parallel corpora. Simultaneously an unlimited number of dictionaries can be held open, thus by a single interrogation step, all the dictionaries (translations, explanations, synonyms, etc.) can be surveyed. The implemented system (called MoBiDic) knows morphological rules of the dictionaries' languages. Thus, never the actual (inflected) words, but always their lemmas - that is, the right dictionary entries - are looked up. MoBiDic has an open, multimedial architecture, thus it is suitable for handling not only textual, but speaking or picture dictionaries, as well.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> The same system is also able to find words and expressions in corpora, dynamically providing the translators with examples from their earlier translations or other translators' works. MoBiDic has been designed for translator workgroups, where the translators' own glossaries (built also with the help of the system) may also be disseminated among the members of the group, with different access rights, if needed. The system has a TCP/IP-based client-server implementation for various platforms and available with a gradually increasing number of dictionaries for numerous language pairs.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Introduction &amp;quot;The whole world of translation is opening up, to new possibilities, and to technological and methodological change&amp;quot; (Kingscott 1993). Some years after the above claim, we see that software tools for translators, even the most recent ones, do not yet guarantee perfect solutions to automatic translation. More and more systems introduce, however, new facilities to the translator working in a computational environment. As Hutchins says, &amp;quot;the best use must be made of those systems that are available, and the producers and developers must be encouraged to improve and introduce new facilities to meet user needs.&amp;quot; (Hutchins 1996) It is almost a commonplace that texts - books, newspapers, letters, official memos, brochures, any type of publications, reports, etc. - in the nineties are written, sent, read and translated with the help of the electronic media. Consequently, traditional information sources, like paper-based dictionaries, and lexicons, are no longer as much a part of the translation environment.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Electronic dictionaries for most developers just mean, however, to make the well-known paper dictionary image appear on the computer screen.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> It is easy to understand why we say that dictionary computerization does not mean producing machine-readable versions of traditional printed dictionaries, but the combination of the existing lexical resources with up-to-date language technology. null On the other hand, there is a question whether we have to continue in the traditional way of developing new - and different - lexicons for any new application/system, starting from scratch every time and therefore consuming time, money and manpower, or is it new lexicons.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> In what follows, timely to think of the possibility of making the effort to converge, trying to avoid unnecessary duplications and - where possible - building on what already exists (Calzolari 1994). Consequently, in the near future we have to combine the two above needs: making existing  lexical resources computationally accessible and showing the strategy how to develop we try to argue for changes in development strategies of electronic translation dictionaries. Today's lingware technology can - and must - use dynamic actions, like morpho-syntactic analysis, lemmatization, spell checking, and so on. On the other hand, dictionaries can never be full in any sense, therefore we have to make parallel multi-dictionary access possible. It means that a single dictionary look-up should use an unlimited number of lexical resources that are available for the translator.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

