<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P98-1001">
<Title>A Quasi-Dependency Model for Structural Analysis of Chinese BaseNPs*</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="1" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The concept of baseNP is initially put forward by Church. In English, baseNP is defined as 'simple non-recursive noun phrases', which means that there is no sub-noun-phrases contained in a baseNP\[1\]. B~t the definition can not meet the needs in Chinese information retrieval. The noun phrases such as &amp;quot;1~ ~(natural) ~-~(language) ~(process)&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;~-IF~b~l(Asian) ~;-'~!\]~(finance) ~f~ ~(crisis)&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;i~(political) /C/~k$1J(system) ~(reformation) ~.~(process)&amp;quot; are critical for information retrieval, but they are not non-recursive noun phrases.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Type In Chinese, the attribute of noun phrases can be classified into three types, that is restrictive attributes, distinctive attributes and descriptive attributes, among which the restrictive attributes have agglutinative relation with the heads. The using the paper defines the Chinese baseNP restrictive attributes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  \[ Definition 1 \] Chinese baseNP (hereafter abbreviated as baseNP)baseNP -- baseNP + baseNP baseNP --- baseNP + N I VN baseNP -- restrictive-attribute + baseNP baseNP --- restrictive-attribute + N I VN restrictive-attribute --- A I B I V IN \] S I X I (M+Q)  Where, the terminal symbols A, B, V, N, VN, S, X, M, Q stand for respectively adjective, distinctives, verbs, nouns, norminalized verbs, locatives, non-Chinese string, numerals and quantifiers. According to the definition, noun phrases falls into baseNPs and non-baseNPs (abbreviated as ~baseNP). Table-1 gives some examples.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Table- 1 : Examples of baseNP and -baseNP  Both baseNP recognition and baseNP structural analysis are basic tasks in Chinese information retrieval. The paper mainly discusses the problems in structural analysis of baseNPs, which is essential for generating the compositional indexing units from a baseNP. The task of baseNP * The research is supported by the key project of the National Natural Science Foundation  structural analysis is to determine the syntactic structure of a baseNP. In this paper, we use dichotomy for baseNP analysis. For example, the structure of &amp;quot;I~1 ~/natural ~/ianguage ~J~ /process&amp;quot; is &amp;quot;( ~ ~/natural i,~'/language) ~ /process&amp;quot;. Obviously, a baseNP composed of three or more than three words has syntactic ambiguities. For example, baseNP &amp;quot;x y z&amp;quot; has two possible structures, that is &amp;quot;(x y) z&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;x (y z)&amp;quot;. The task of baseNP structural analysis is to select the correct structure from the possible structures. The paper mainly discusses the problems related to Chinese baseNP structural analysis.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Section 2 puts forward a quasi-dependency model for structure analysis of Chinese baseNPs. Section 3 gives an unsupervised quasi-dependency-strength estimation algorithm based on the minimum description length (MDL) principle.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Section 4 analyzes the performance of the proposed model and the algorithm. Section 5 discusses some issues in the implementation of baseNP structure analysis and quasi-dependency-strength estimation. Section 6 is the conclusion.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

