<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P98-2142">
<Title>Integrated Control of Chart Items for Error Repair</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="862" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper describes a system that performs hierarchical error repair for ill-formed sentences, with heterarchical control of chart items produced at the lexical, syntactic, and semantic levels. The system uses an augmented context-free grammar and employs a bidirectional chart parsing algorithm. The system is composed of four subsystems: for lexical, syntactic, surface case, and semantic processing. The subsystems are controlled by an integrated-agenda system. The system employs a parser for well-formed sentences and a second parser for repairing single error sentences. The system ranks possible repairs by penalty scores which are based on both grammar-dependent factors (e.g. the significance of the repaired constituent in a local tree) and grammar-independent factors (e.g. error types). This paper focuses on the heterarchical processing of integrated-agenda items (i.e. chart items) at three levels, in the context of single error recovery.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Introduction Weischedel and Sondheimer (1983) described two types of ill-formedness: relative (i.e. limitations of the computer system) and absolute (e.g. misspellings, mistyping, agreement violation etc). These two types of problem cause ill-formedness of a sentence at various levels, including typographical, orthographical, morphological, phonological, syntactic, semantic, and pragmatic levels.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Typographical spelling errors have been studied by many people (Damerau, 1964; Peterson, 1980; Pollock and Zamora, 1983).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Mitton (1987) found a large proportion of real-word errors were orthographical: to--&gt; too, were ---&gt; where. At the sentential level, types of syntactic errors such as co-occurrence violations, ellipsis, conjunction errors, and extraneous terms have been studied (Young, Eastman, and Oakman, 1991). In addition, Min (1996) found 0.6% of words misspelt (447/68966) in 300 email messages, leading to about 12.0% of the 3728 sentences havingerrors. null Various systems have focused on the recovery of ill-formed text at the morpho-syntactic level (Vosse, 1992), the syntactic level (Irons, 1963; Lyon, 1974), and the semantic level (Fass and Wilks, 1983; Carbonell and Hayes, 1983). Those systems identified and repaired errors in various ways, including using grammar-specific rules (metarules) (Weischedel and Sondheimer, 1983), least-cost error recovery based on chart parsing (Lyon, 1974; Anderson and Backhouse, 1981), semantic preferences (Fass and Wilks, 1983), and heuristic approaches based on a shift-reduce parser (Vosse, 1992). Systems that focus on a particular level miss errors that can only be detected using higher level knowledge. For example, at the lexical level, in I saw a man if the park, the misspelt word if is undetected. At the syntactic level, in I saw a man in the pork, the misspelling of pork can only be detected using semantic information.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> This paper describes the automatic correction of ill-formed sentences by using integrated information from three levels (lexical, syntactic, and semantic). The CHAPTER system (CHArt Parser for Two-stage Error Recovery), performs two-stage error recovery using generalised top-down chart parsing for the syntax phase (cf. Mellish, 1989; Kato, 1994). It uses an augmented context-free grammar, which covers verb subcategorisations, passives, yes/no and WHquestions, finite relative clauses, and EQUI/SOR phenomena.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The semantic processing uses a conceptual hierarchy and act templates (Fass and Wilks, 1983), that express semantic restrictions.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Surface case processing is used to help extract meaning (Grishman and Peng, 1988) by mapping surface cases to their corresponding conceptual cases. Unlike other systems that  have focused on error recovery at a particular level (Damerau, 1964; Mellish, 1989; Fass and Wilks, 1983), CHAPTER uses an integrated agenda system, which integrates lexical, syntactic, surface case, and semantic processing. CHAPTER uses syntactic and semantic information to correct spelling errors detected, including real-word errors.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> Section 1 treats methodology. Section 2 gives test results for CHAPTER. Section 3 describes problems with CHAPTER and section 4 contains conclusions.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

