<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P98-1050">
<Title>Multext-East: Parallel and Comparable Corpora and Lexicons for Six Central and Eastern European Languages</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The EU Copernicus project Multext-East has created a multi-lingual corpus of text and speech data, covering the six languages of the project: Bulgarian, Czech, Estonian, Hungarian, Romanian, and Slovene. In addition, wordform lexicons for each of the languages were developed. The corpus includes a parallel component consisting of Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four, with versions in all six languages tagged for part-of-speech and aligned to English (also tagged for POS). We describe the encoding format and data architecture designed especially for this corpus, which is generally usable for encoding linguistic corpora. We also describe the methodology for the development of a harmonized set of morphosyntactic descriptions (MSDs), which builds upon the scheme for western European languages developed within the EAGLES project. We discuss the special concerns for handling the six project languages, which cover three distinct language families.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Introduction In order to provide resources to enable the efficient extraction of quantitative and qualitative information from corpora, several corpus development and distribution efforts have been recently established. However, few corpora exist for Central and Eastern European (CEE) languages, and corpus-processing tools that take into account the specific characteristics of these languages are virtually non-existent.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The Multext-East Copernicus projec0 (Erjavec, et al., 1997) was a spin-off of the LRE project Multext 2 (Ide and Vtronis, 1994) intended to fill these gaps by developing significant resources for six CEE languages (Bulgarian, Czech, Estonian, Hungarian, Romanian, Slovene) that follow a consistent and principled encoding format and are maximally suited to easy processing by corpus-handling tools. To this end, Multext-East developed a corpus of parallel and comparable texts for the six CEE project languages, together with wordform lexicons and other language-specific resources. In the following sections we briefly describe the Multext-East corpora (text, speech) and the Multext-East lexicons and language-specific resources.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

