<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P98-1002">
<Title>The production of code-mixed discourse</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> We propose a comprehensive theory of code-mixed discourse, encompassing equivalence-point and insertional code-switching, palindromic constructions and lexical borrowing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> The starting point is a production model of code-switching accounting for empirical observations about switch-point distribution (the equivalence constraint), well-formedness of monolingual fragments, conservation of constituent structure and lack of constraint between successive switch points, without invoking any &amp;quot;code-switching grammar&amp;quot;. Codeswitched sentence production makes alternate reference to two virtual monolingual sentences, one in each language, and is based on conservative conditions on language labeling of constituents, together with a constraint against real-time &amp;quot;look-ahead&amp;quot; from one code-switch to the next. Selective weakening of model conditions can produce (i) the type of palindromic (or portmanteau) construction occasionally occurring e.g., in switches between prepositional and postpositional languages, (ii) the switching by &amp;quot;insertion&amp;quot; of very specific kinds of constituent reported e.g., for French noun phrases in switching with Arabic and, most important, (iii) lexical borrowing. Borrowing can create ambiguity as to language membership of sentence items, but the model predicts where this can be resolved, and the confirmation of these predictions, based on empirical studies of inflectional morphology, validates key aspects of the model.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Introduction Communities of bilinguals tend to evolve a conversational mode where elements of both languages appear in the same interaction and even in the same sentence despite the fact that all participants may be competent in either of the two languages. Whether this mode is used in preference to monolingual discourse depends on the type of interaction, the participants, the subject of conversation and many other factors. The grammatical nature of code-mixed discourse, however, tends to be very specific to the community and varies widely among bilingual communities, even among communities which share the same pair of languages. Empirical research has isolated four clearly distinct processes which may be responsible for mixing to different extents in different communities -- code-switching, nonce borrowing, specialized incorporation and interference. None of these processes requires the deformation, alteration or convergence of either of the two constituent languages at the syntactic, lexical, morphological, phonological, or semantic levels at the moment the mixing occurs. Except for codeswitching, however, they may all lead in the long term to lexical expansion in one or both of the languages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> This paper is a contribution to a coherent formal account of code-mixing which integrates all of these processes 1, though only code-switching and borrowing will be considered here. This is based on a series of empirical studies which now allows us to distinguish between them structurally and quantitatively. Our starting point will be a recent formal characterization of a equivalence-point code-switching (Sankoff, 1The analysis of code-mixing is a controversial sub-ject with respect to several aspects: Is all code-mixing -- borrowing, switching, interference -- really the same process? Do languages involved in code-mixing tend to converge syntactically? Are patterns of code-mixing predictable or explicable by theories of (monolingual) grammar? We assume a negative response to all these questions and refer to the literature for more detailed discussion. null 1998). We will then extend this to two rarer code-switching mechanisms, and finally to lexical borrowing, the most frequent type of codemixing. null</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

