<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P05-3005">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1 Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> With the use of computers in storing the explosive amount of biological information, natural language processing (NLP) approaches have been explored to make the task of managing information recorded in free text more feasible [1, 2]. One requirement for NLP is the ability to accurately recognize terms that represent biological entities in free text. Another requirement is the ability to associate these terms with corresponding biological entities (i.e., records in biological databases) in order to be used by other automated systems for literature mining. Such task is called biological entity tagging. Biological entity tagging is not a trivial task because of several characteristics associated with biological entity names, namely: synonymy (i.e., different terms refer to the same entity), ambiguity (i.e., one term is associated with different entities), and coverage (i.e., entity terms or entities are not present in databases or knowledge bases).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Methods for biological entity tagging can be categorized into two types: one is to use a dictionary and a mapping method [3-5], and the other is to markup terms in the text according to contextual cues, specific verbs, or machine learning [6-10]. The performance of biological entity tagging systems using dictionaries depends on the coverage of the dictionary as well as mapping methods that can handle synonymous or ambiguous terms. Strictly speaking, tagging systems that do not use dictionaries are not biological entity tagging but biological term tagging, since tagged terms in text are not associated with specific biological entities stored in databases. It requires an additional step to map terms mentioned in the text to records in biological databases in order to be automatically integrated with other system or databases. Due to the dynamic nature associated with the molecular biology domain, it is critical to have a comprehensive biological entity dictionary that is always up-to-date.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> In this paper, we present a system that constructs a large protein entity dictionary, BioThesaurus, using online resources. Terms in the dictionary are then curated based on high ambiguous terms to flag nonsensical terms (e.g., Novel protein) and are also curated based on the semantic categories acquired from the UMLS to flag descriptive terms that associate with other semantic types other than gene or proteins (e.g., terms that refer to species, cells or other small molecules). In the following, we first provide background and related work on dictionary construction using online resources. We then present our method on constructing the dictionary.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

