<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P05-1001">
<Title>A High-Performance Semi-Supervised Learning Method for Text Chunking</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> In machine learning, whether one can build a more accurate classifier by using unlabeled data (semi-supervised learning) is an important issue. Although a number of semi-supervised methods have been proposed, their effectiveness on NLP tasks is not always clear. This paper presents a novel semi-supervised method that employs a learning paradigm which we call structural learning. The idea is to find &amp;quot;what good classifiers are like&amp;quot; by learning from thousands of automatically generated auxiliary classification problems on unlabeled data. By doing so, the common predictive structure shared by the multiple classification problems can be discovered, which can then be used to improve performance on the target problem. The method produces performance higher than the previous best results on CoNLL'00 syntactic chunking and CoNLL'03 named entity chunking (English and German).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> (Blum and Mitchell, 1998) automatically bootstraps labels, and such labels are not necessarily reliable (Pierce and Cardie, 2001). A related idea is to use Expectation Maximization (EM) to impute labels. Although useful under some circumstances, when a relatively large amount of labeled data is available, the procedure often degrades performance (e.g. Merialdo (1994)). A number of bootstrapping methods have been proposed for NLP tasks (e.g. Yarowsky (1995), Collins and Singer (1999), Riloff and Jones (1999)). But these typically assume a very small amount of labeled data and have not been shown to improve state-of-the-art performance when a large amount of labeled data is available.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Our goal has been to develop a general learning framework for reliably using unlabeled data to improve performance irrespective of the amount of labeled data available. It is exactly this important and difficult problem that we tackle here. This paper presents a novel semi-supervised method that employs a learning framework called structural learning (Ando and Zhang, 2004), which seeks to discover shared predictive structures (i.e. what good classifiers for the task are like) through jointly learning multiple classification problems on unlabeled data. That is, we systematically create thousands of problems (called auxiliary problems) relevant to the target task using unlabeled data, and train classifiers from the automatically generated `training data'. We learn the commonality (or structure) of such many classifiers relevant to the task, and use it to improve performance on the target task. One example of such auxiliary problems for chunking tasks is to `mask' a word and predict whether it is &amp;quot;people&amp;quot; or not from the context, like language modeling. Another example is to predict the pre-</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

