<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W05-0301">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="1" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1 Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The Frontiers in Corpus Annotation workshops are opportunities to discuss the state of the art of corpus annotation in computational linguistics. Corpus annotation has pushed the enitre eld in new directions by providing new task de nitions and new standards of analysis. At the rst Frontiers in Corpus Annotation workshop at HLT-NAACL 2004 we compared assumptions underlying different annotation projects in light of both multilingual applications and the pursuit of merged representations that incorporate the result of various annotation projects.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Beginning September, 2004, several researchers have been collaborating to produce detailed semantic annotation of two dif cult sentences. The effort aimed to produce a single uni ed representation that goes beyond what may currently be feasible to annotate consistently or to generate automatically. Rather this pie in the sky annotation effort was an attempt at de ning a future goal for semantic analysis. We decided to use the Pie in the Sky annotation effort (http://nlp.cs.nyu.edu/meyers/piein-the-sky.html) as a theme for this year's workshop. Consequently this theme has been brought out in many of the papers contained in this volume.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The rst 4 papers (Pustejovsky et al., 2005; E. W.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Hinrichs and S. Kcurrency1ubler and K. Naumann, 2005; Bies et al., 2005; Dinesh et al., 2005) all discuss some aspect of merging annotation. (Pustejovsky et al., 2005) describes issues that arise for merging argument structures for verbs, nouns and discourse connectives, as well as time and anaphora representations. (E. W. Hinrichs and S. Kcurrency1ubler and K. Naumann, 2005) focuses on the merging of syntactic, morphological, semantic and referential annotation. (E. W. Hinrichs and S. Kcurrency1ubler and K. Naumann, 2005) also points out that the Pie in the Sky representation lacks syntactic features. This brings to light an important point of discussion: should linguistic analyses be divided out into separate levels corresponding to syntax, morphology, discourse, etc. or should/can a single representation represent all such levels ? As currently conceived, Pie in the Sky is intended to be as language neutral as possible this may make adding a real syntactic level dif cult. However, arguably, surface relations can be added on as features to Pie in the Sky, even if we delete or ignore those features for some (e.g., language neutral) purposes. Still, other papers present further dif culties for maintaining a single representation that covers multiple modes of analysis.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> (Bies et al., 2005) discusses possible con icts between named entity analyses and syntactic structure and (Dinesh et al., 2005) discusses a con ict between discourse structure and syntactic structure. I think it is reasonable to assume that some such con icts will be resolvable, e.g., I believe that the named entity con icts point to shortcomings of the original Penn Treebank analysis. However, the discourse structure/syntactic structure con icts may be harder to solve. In fact, some annotation projects, e.g., the Prague Dependency Treebank (Haji cov*a and Ceplov*a, 2000), assume that multiple analyses or levels are necessary to describe the full range of phenomena.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The 5th through 7th papers (Inui and Okumura, 2005; Calhoun et al., 2005; Wilson and Wiebe, 2005) investigate some additional types of annotation that were not part of the distributed version of Pie in the Sky, but which could be added in principle. In fact, with help from the authors of (Calhoun et al., 2005), I did incorporate their analysis into the latest version (number 6) of the Pie in the Sky annotation. Furthermore, it turns out that some units of Information Structure cross the boundaries of the syntactic/semantic constituents, thus raising the sort of dif culties discussed in the previous paragraph.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Speci cally, information structure divides sentences into themes and rhemes. For the sample two sentences, the rheme boundaries do correspond to syntactic units, but the theme boundaries cross syntactic boundaries, forming units made up of parts of multiple syntactic constituents.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> (Palmer et al., 2005; Xue, 2005) (the eighth and  eleventh papers) make comparisons of annotated phenomena across English and Chinese. It should be pointed out that seven of the papers at this workshop are predominantly about the annotation of English, one is about German annotation and one is about Japanese annotation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> These two are the only papers at the workshop that explicitly discuss attempts to apply the same annotation scheme across two languages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> (McShane et al., 2005; Poesio and Artstein, 2005) (the ninth and tenth papers) both pertain to issues about improving the annotation process. (Poesio and Artstein, 2005) discusses some better ways of assessing inter-annotator agreement, particularly when there is a gray area between correct and incorrect annotation. (McShane et al., 2005) discusses the issue of human-aided annotation (human correction of a machine-generated analysis) as it pertains to a single-integrated annotation scheme, similar in many ways to Pie in the Sky , although it has been in existence for a lot longer.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

