<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="E87-1005">
<Title>A MORPHOLOGICAL PROCESSOR FOR MODERN GREEK</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
ABSTRACT
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> In this paper, we present a morphological processor for Modern Greek.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> From the linguistic point of view, we tr 5, to elucidate the complexity of the inflectional system using a lexical model which follows the mecent work by Lieber, 1980, Selkirk 1982, Kiparsky 1982, and others.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The implementation is based on the concept of &amp;quot;validation grammars&amp;quot; (Coumtin 1977). The morphological processing is controlled by a finite automaton and it combines a. a dictionary containing the stems for a representative fragment of Modern Greek and all the inflectional affixes with b. a grammar which camries out the transmission of the linguistic information needed for the processing. The words are structured by concatenating a stem with an inflectional part. In certain cases, phonological rules are added to the grammar in order to capture lexical phonological phenomena.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> i. Intu'oduction-Ovemview Our processor is intended to provide an analysis as well as a generation for every derived item of the greek lexicon. It covers both inflectional and derivational morphology but for the time being only inflection has been treated.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Greek is the only language tested so far.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Nevertheless, we hope that our system is general enough to be of use to other languages since the formal and computational aspect of &amp;quot;validation grammars&amp;quot; and finite automata has already been used for French (c.f. Courtin et al. 1976, Galiotou 1983).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> The system is built around the following data files: I.A &amp;quot;dictionary&amp;quot; holding morphemes associated to morpho-syntactic information.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 2.A &amp;quot;model&amp;quot; file containing items which act as reference to every morphematic entry in order to determine what kind of process the entry undergoes. null 3.A word grammar which governs permissible word structures. The rules that can apply to an entry are divided in a. a &amp;quot;basic initial rule&amp;quot; acting as a recognition process.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> b. The validation Pules that determine all possible combinations of the entry with other morphemes.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

