<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-1028">
<Title>TRANSLITERATION MAPPINGS I PHONOLOGICAL RULES at 'Xi:ro'vo, n de 'hsraf,storem I. SENTENCE ACCENT ASSIGNMENT J INTONATION CONTOUR COMPUTATION at 'X i~r a'v&amp;n do 'h~ref,storam</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstvact
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> We (k;~,.c,ibe a set of rt,o(lttle.,i that together tuake up a grapheme-to phoneme conversion system for Dutch. Modules include a syflabificatiou program, a fast morphological parser, a lexical database, a phonological knowledg*: base, transliteration rules, and phonological rnles. Knowledge and procedures were intlflenmnted object-orientedly. We contrast GRAFON to recent p.tern recognitkm and rule. compiler approaches mid tit to show that the first fails for languages with concatenative comlmtmding (like Dutch, Get,nan, and Scandinavian languages) while the second lack.,; the flexibility to model different phonological theories. It is claimed that sylhtbles (and not graphemes/phonemes or ulorphemes) should be central units in a rtde-based phonemisatkm algorithm. Furthermore, the architectnre of GRA!:&amp;quot;ON and its nser interface make it ideally suited as a rule testing tool fol phonologists.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 1. INTROI)~CI'I(1lkl Speech :;ynthesis systems cousist of a linguistic and an acoustic part The linguistic part converts an orthographic representation of a text into a phonetic representation flexible and detailed enough to serve as input to the acoustic part.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The acoustic t)art is a speech synthesiser which may be based on the production of allophones or diphones. This paper is concerned with file linguistic part of speech synthesis for Dutch (a process we will call phonamisation). The problem of phonemi~;ation has beett approached in different ways.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Recently, covnectionist approaches (NETtalk: Sejnowski and Rosenberg, 1987) mid memory-based reasoning approaches (MBRtalk: Slanfill and Waltz, 1986) have been proposed as alternatives tt) the traditional symbol-manipttlation approach.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Within the latter (rule-based) approach, several systems have bexm built for English (the rnost comprehensive of which is probably Ml\]'alk; Allen, Hunnicutt and Klatt, 1987), and systems for othm&amp;quot; European hmguages are beginning to appear. Text-to-,;peech systems tbr Dutch are still in an experimental stage, and two different designs can be distinguished. Some researchers adopt an 'expert system' pattern matching approach /Boot, 1984/, others a 'rule compiler' approach /Kerkhoff, Wester and Bores, 1984; Berendsen, Langeweg attd van Leer,wen, 1986/ in which the rules are mostly in an SPE-inspired format. Both approaches take the grapheme/phoneme as a central nnit. We will argue that within the symbol manipulation approach, a modular architecture with rite syllable as a central tmit is to be preferred. The research described in this paper was supported partly by the European Community under ESPRIT project OS 82. The paper is based on an hiternal memo (Daelemans, 1985) and on part of a dissertation (l)aelemans, 1987b). The system described here is not to be eonfilsed with the GRAPHON system developed at the Techaisehe Oniversitiit Wien (Pounder and Kommcnda, 1986) which is a text-to-speech syatenl for German. I am grateful to my forraer and present c(lleagtms in Nijmegen and Brtmsels for providing a sthnulating wo,'kiag environment. Erik Wybouw developed C-code for constructing an indexed-sequential version of the lexical database. null The architecture of GRAFON as it is currently implemented is shown in Figure l.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

