<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-1047">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="232" end_page="232" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
3 Dynamic Account
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> However, the above static approach cannot by itself explain some UBD phenomena, especially so-called the Complex NP Constraint (originally termed by Ross /Ross 1967/) observed in the examples that follow.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1">  (9) *Whoi do you believe \[NPl\[mp2the claim\] \[gsthat \[ssshe loves q\]\]\]? (10) *What/ did you propose a plan \[vP to buy el\]?  In (9), Sa is the complement of 'claim'. Hence the dislocated element, bound by 'Who/' should be permitted to be passed into Sa without violating (6). Similarly, VP (or CP, in the trausformational account) in (10) is regarded as the eomplelnent of 'plan', so that the dislocated element bound by 'What/' should be able to pass through, (6) aud (7) being respected. Hence the static account in the previous section provides no reason why these examples should be ungrammatical. It is considered because of essentially the same sort of difficulty that Chomsky /Chomsky 1986/ leaves unexplained this type of island effect. 3ol A Model of Language Processing Now then let us turn to dymunic aspects of language processing, and consider what kind of syntactic structures a human bearer should have tmilt and tentatiwdy maintains when 'that' in (9) is encountered. As a basis for this investigatiou, we adopt the following postulates about ha,nan language processing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> (\[1) t*. When ;~ word is encountered, it is attached to stcuc.. tures previously built, giving rise to new structures.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> ii;ven when several possible waY=~ of attachment are acknowledged, the processing is sot postponed, but a~ many new structures corresponding to those ways o:{! attachment are made in parallel.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> b. 'lJ'here is a limitation on the size of the memory for .~toring these structures, and thus it is impossible to retain all the structures potentially sanctioned. Only strtn;tures activated strongly enough can survive the competition lbr seats in the limited memory.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> From (ll) plus some minor hypotheses, a general processing model %11o'C/% which describes both sentence comprehension and generation. This model postulates that. just after any word a is encounLered, every maximal structure of the sentence cur, rently hypothesized in mind should look at)t)roximately like the part enclosed within the curve in (:12).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6">  (12) j;2 itere ew;ry branching local tree is assumed to be binary, without los~ of generality. AI and ,5' may be identical, and the short-term memory contains the information about Ai, Bi (1 _&lt; i &lt; d), and A, pins the inEormatin about the configura..  lion of these categories relative to each other. Note that, as a whole, enough information is thus retained to control the gram-. maticality ot the way the foregoing context fits the rest of the sentmme; Those categories are the points on which the currently hypothesized structure has contacts with the still unknown part of the sente0ce.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> Strictly speaking~ the picture shown in (12) should he looked upon merely as a first order approximation of the reality. That ia, the part of the sentence structnre enclosed in tlte curve might contain some variable parts, rather than being totally definite. Suppose, \[o;r instance, that a sentence begins wit, h a *~oun phrase say &amp;quot;this man'. Tit(; entire tree structure of this NP should he completed as sool~ as 'm~,on' is encountered, but its grammatical case would not be uniquely determined yet, hecause the senteuce as a whole might turn out to be soinething like &amp;quot;l'his n-tP, n, I don't know', rather than &amp;quot;Fhis man is crazy'; The initiM NPis accusative in the former sentence, and nonfinative in the latter. In the following discussion, however, we shall merely exploit very rough properties of the model, so that such an inaccuracy is considered irrelevant. Readers are referred to llasida/liasida 1985/for how this model is ohtained and what it predicts, wtfich the limited space of the current article fails to accommodate.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

