<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-2100">
<Title>A ~,&amp;quot;e'aa~)lework ~bv Lexkat Setecth~n h~ Natmdega~ ge~;vei Nire~tburg Ca, r~egie,.Mel#m Unive~'i~y</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
3A Collocations
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Lcxical choices am, however, tylfically made in centext. Conlextual rclations anloug lcxical units reflect lueauiflg.-iudilced consiraillts ori eamccarfence (selectional ~estrictions: admire utkes a human subject).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Sometimes, however, it is difficult to formulate a cot~:cnrrencc C()llstraint ill terms of selectional rcslriclions alone. Ttnls, 10r cxanqfie, tile causative construction wilh the English inJhzence requires eae, t; ils Russian equivalent vlijanie requires okazyvat', aed the \]alter is not a Rnssian correlate of exert other Itmn ill the above and very R'.w similar syntagmatic conslructions. Why do wc use, in Euglish, shed with iea,'s or leaves but don't usuaUy say shed water out era bucket or they drop tear,*&amp;quot; every time when &lt;...&gt;? Snch properties of the lexical sleek of a natural language ate called eolloeational. We will now ilhlsi~tte, Ihe c~meept of collouation through several examples, Cousidcr thc conceptual Old,rater of a large quantity of, a (relative) value liar measuring quantities (of materMs, lknccs, qualities, properties, etc.). It is realized in Euglish in sorer&amp;race with collocational propm'ties of the lexical units that arc ascxl its its ope.lands. Not every quantity goes with every realization of the above opeaattm Members of ~hc set &lt;big, enormous, great, high, large, strong, wide&gt; of potential realb,~ltions of a large quantity of call reoccur with every of file members of the set &lt;amount, difficulty, expanse, selection, voltage&gt; of quantities. We say high voltage but a large amount. It wouhl lx~ inapprollriate liar a generation system to produce someflfing like high selection or large dif3eulty. (Note that in parsing the problem of assigning a similar senatntk: marker to all file various expressions from tile e.x~allpl(,; C~tU~ in priuciple, be. tackled through a mechanism of metaplt(w pnmcssing (e.g., Cat'boneR, 1987), whereby a geueral heuristic rule is dcw;luped for processing metaphorical input belouging a single class, such as, for instance, a large quantity of... - see Lakoff and Johnson, 1980, 10r an extensive listing of potential metaphor classes; in generalion, however, the task is the opposite - to produce llucnt nmtaphorical lauguuge.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Since this depends not on regularities of meaning, but mthcJ on the idiosyncrasies of nteaniug realization in the varlons natural langtmges, the general rules will be more difficalt to come by and furumlate,) An additional class of collocations are the paradigmalic collocao lions. &amp;quot;these am best exemplified by the 'set-complement' collocaliuns such as the English left and right or parents and chiMren. 'l~le knowi.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> edge of these collocations, for instauee, simplifies the proccss of lcxical selection of conjoined constructions, such as ladies and gemlemen.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Colloeatioual relatious are defined on lexical ualls, not meaning ~'epresentadons. The study of collocations asceuds to Firdi (195 It; it i:,  a central part of the Meaning - Text school of linguistics --- cf. Mel'~uk, 19'14; 1981. 'll,e importance of collocational propelzies in generations has been recognized (cf. Cummiug, 1986), bat relatively few systems actually include collocational information in their decision processes.</Paragraph>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
3.2 ElLipsis and Anaphora
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Certain contexts completely alleviate the problem of open-class lexical selection. Consider the following (gloss of an) input segment: (2) Clause1:BuyOohn3 book7), time|, focus: book7 Clause2:Bring(John3 book7 office~), belong-to(office~ John3), time2: time~ &gt; timeh focus: office| Clause3:Read(John3 hook7), aspect: inchoative, time: after(timez) One of the adequate ways of realizing it is: (3) John bought a book. He brought this book to his office and started to read it.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Ttiefe are seven instances of the three object-type concepts in the case-role slots of the input propositions above. Each of the three concepts is realized lexically only once. In two cases these meanings were realized through prononlinalization and in one each through definite description and ar |elliptic'/ construction. This example shows that non-lexical realization is an integral part of the process of lexical selection m generation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> In what fellows we briefly describe the system architecture,, the knowledge structures and the algorithm we use for selecting open-class lexical items in generation.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Section>
</Paper>

