<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-1064">
<Title>t exicon Component I I LEXiCAL ~EPRESENTATI ON I I TwoAevel Rules I I SI.IRIFACE IiEPRESENTATION</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="313" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
SI.IRIFACE IiEPRESENTATION
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Fig. 1 _nL~ paper desc~ibes a fairly comprehensive two-level ~le 3ysh~a~ ~br phonological and morphophonological alter~atio~ in Akkadian word inflection and regular ve~obal derivation. The rule component proves to be similar i~ two-level rule systems ~br other la~guages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Interdigitation entails more requirements for the lexicon which defines feasible lexical representations and relates them to underlying morphemes..The task for the lexicon component is more or less universal, even if some languages can do with simpler lexicons while others require more sophisticated structures.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> This paper discusses a solution which involves using two separate lexicons, one for word roots, and the other for prefixes, flexional elements and suffixes. Entries for roots leave flexlonal elements unspecified and vice versa. The intersection of these two lexicons effectively defines lexical representations of word-forms.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 2. Morphotactic structure of word-forms.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Akkadian verbs have the following overall pattern: \[pers.\] \[root &amp; flection\] \[gender &amp; numb.\] \[opt. subjunctive etc.\] \[opt. obj.\] An example of a full fledged verbal form would be '(that) they caught him': lexicalrepresentation: I X t a B A T - u \ - n I - sh u surface representation: i x x a b t u u n i sh u A dash '-' denotes morpheme boundary, and backslash 'V a morphophoneme for vowel lengthening. The above word-form is divided into its parts according to the pattern as follows: person 1  root X ... B ... A T flection ... t a ......</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> gender &amp; number u \ subjunctive n 1 object sh u  Capital letters are used in order to distinguish radical consonants and vowels fi'om segments in other morphs. Thus, the root &amp; flection part is XtaBAT where capital letters are components of the root, with lower case letters representing flectional elements.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Nouns, in turn, have an overall structure : \[stem\] \[case &amp; number\[ \[opt. possessive\] An example of a maximal nominal word-form is their kings ~.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> lexicalrepresentation: Sh a R \ - a \ n t - sh u n U surface representation: sh a r r a a n i sh u n u  This can be readily decomposed into its parts as follows:  stem Sh a It \ case&amp;number a \ n i possessive sit u n u 3. Overall structure of morphs  Verbal roots have an overall pattern of three radical consonants and one vowel c ... C ... v c where flectional elements may occur in the two intervening slots marked with &amp;quot;...&amp;quot; Flectional elements have a pattern consisting of two parts to fill the corresponding two gaps in the verbal root. The overall pattern is roughly ...(((c)C)v)...(v or \)... There is at most one verbal prefix and it indicates person (and partly modus). Its overalll pattern is (C)y. There are at most three verbal suffixes attached to the stem. The first suffix indicates gender and number (and partly person). They have the form v\ or they are empty. The second suffix indicates either the subjunctive (u, empty, or n-l) or the ventive (am or aim). The third suffix denotes the object or the dative case and conforms to a pattern c v( c u(\ c v)) Nominal stems are given as derived complete stems containing three radical consonants which can be identified, but no attempt has been made to generate them from plain radical consonants and flectional elements because stems are idiosyncratic and better described as lexicalized whole units.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> Nominal suffixes indicate gender, number and case. Gender is part of the stem for nouns whereas adjectives have an explicit feminine suffix (a)t (the masculine has no marking). Number and case are represented by portmanteau morphs. After these endings there may be a possessive ending according to one of two patterns: v k or c v (c v).</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

