<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-1025">
<Title>Aknowledgement: We would like to thank Hang Xiong,</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="117" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> IM'I/EC is an English-Chinese machine translation system ~,hich integrates some outstanding features of the case grammar end semantic grammar lnto a uniform frame, LISeS various kuowledgo In the disamblguation, and tries to modify the object language by itself. In this poF,er,we first introduce IMT/EC's design motivetiorl and overall architecture, then describe the deslgn philosophy of its translation mechanisms and thelr procesging algorithms.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> J,The design nlotivation \]'he design of the IMT/EC system are motivated to develop new approaches to the Engllsh-Chinese machine translation, such as, to provide the system with powerful analysis meohanisnls end MT knowledge base menagonlerit system , as well as some exceptional processing and learning meohanlsms, that is, to make the system ba intelligent. In addition, it also tries to inregret9 as many advantages of conventional machine translation systems into a single system as possible, such as, to provide the system with powerful mechon-.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Isms for the processing of various ambiguities and contextu,~l relations. The design of the IMT's translation mechanisms are based on the following consl-</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> In the development of machine translation system, in order to disambiguato the source language, we have to {molyze the input deeply to get the internal meonlng representation of the source language.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> However, the deeper we aaalyze the input, the more we lose the clues about how to express the translation, also, th(it it results in extremely poor or no translations ef sentences for which complete analyses can not be (h~rlved\[Slocum 85\]. To find a suitable analysis depth so as to get both clues about how to express the trorl~;lation of the input and to disombiguate the input conlpletely Is almost impossible. In the IMT/EC, we try t(, design a simple grammar analysis mechanism -- SC-gr'(~mmar auulysls mechanism to inherit both the outstanding features of case grammar analysis and semantic grammar analysis so as to produce a high quality translation, (2) Multl-language translations oriented In present technical conditions, it is impossible to design a general internal meaning representation for all natural languages. Thus, the knowledge based multl-language oriented machine translation system is difficult to be marketed in the near future. A feaslble way ~or designing multl--longuage oriented machine translatJorl systems might be to separate the processing mechanisms from the language specific rules |as King et oI. ~5\], thet ie, t O apply the same processing meotlonlsm with different language specific rules for d~ffErent natural language pair translations. In the 1NI'/EC, we develop a general rule representation form for the representation of various knowledges used in the translotlon. Knowledges for different language palr translations are stored in the differant packages of the knowledge base IMT-KB. The knowledge base are organized In multi-package end multi-level way so as to store rules for the translation of different language pairs and different phases of the  processing. Thus, the system can be easily extended for' multi-language trarlslatlon purposes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> (3) Diversity processing  As the dlsemblguation rules are rather words specific, +-% is difficult to manage them in the same way. To deal wlth this problem, we store these rules in their respected word entries end classify them es several categories in the IMT/EC, Each category corresponds tO 0 general subroutine epplleatlon mechanism, which apply the word specific rules and subroutines in the processing of translation. The subroutines are stored in a natural language specific sub-routine package. Some word specific subroutines are directly stored in the respected word entry.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> (~) Powerful exceptional processing Since the natural language phenomena ore so abundant that any existed machine translation system can not process all the phenomena, it is essential to provide an exceptional processing mechanism in the system to deal wlth exceptional phenomena. As IMT/EC incorporates some learning mechanisms, thus, it is more powerful in dealing with the exceptions than others.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> (5) Automatic modification of the translation Generally speaking, machine translation system can only produce rigid translatlons, it is a desire that MT systems be able to modify the output by itself so as to produce more fluent translations. IMT/EC tries to apply same common sense knowledge and linguistic knowledge of object language to disamblguate the input end modify the translations, thus, to improve the translatlon quality.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> In the following paragraph, we focus on the translation procedure of the system end the algorithms related to it ignoring the knowledge base organization and management mechanisms.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> 2. The overall architecture of the system The architecture of the IMT/EC system is as follow,</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> Fig. The architecture of the IMT/EC  As the rule bose and dlctlonarv in a machine trenslatlon system is so vast that it ls impossible for human beings to find the confllotion end implication among the rules. To modify a rule in the knowledge base often results In many side effects on other rules. Thus, it Is necessary to provide a self reorganization and refinement mechanisms in the knowledge bose.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> In the IMT/EC, we design a special knowledge base management system IMT-KB to manage ell the knowledge used In varlous processing phases of the translation. In addition, IMT/EC also provides o knowledge bose augmentation and knowledge acquisition environment for the system to augment system performance by itself and for the users to improve the knowledge base.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> The col1 relations connected by dotted llnes in the figure above ore executed only when the user sets the learning mechanisms in working status. These mechanisms can acquire new knowledge in the dynamic interactive, static interactive,or disconnected ways. They ore primarily used to resolve the exaeDtlenel phenomena in the translation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> Dynamic Interactive Learning (DIL): Whenever the system encounters c sentence out of its processing range, it produces various possible translations for each segment of the sentence and interacts with human beings when necessary to select on appropriate translation of the segment and combine them to get o correct translation of the sentence. At the some time, it also creates'some new rules to reflect the selections. That is, it learns some new knowledge.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> Static Interactive Learning (SIL): Whenever the system encounters a sentence out of its processing range,it records down the sentence and its appearance context in e file. After the text has been translated, it begins to analyze the sentence in detail to get various possible translations for each segment of the sentence and interacts with human beings when necessary to get appropriate translations of the segments and combines them to get a correct translation of the sentence. At the same time, it also creates some new rules to reflect the selections, thus, to learn new knowledge.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> Disconnected Learning (DL): Whenever the system encounters o sentence out of its processing range, it analyzes the sentence in detail to get all the possible translations, and then evaluates these translations according to the preference rules stored in.the IMT-KB to select on appropriate translation and modify the related rules used in the analysis to reflect the selections. It skips over sentences which the translation con not be determined by the preference rules Instead of interacting with human beings.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

