<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C88-2098">
<Title>A Animal B Female Animal C Concrete D Male Animal E 'S' + 'L' F Female tluman G Gas It ltuma~ I Inanimate J Movable K Male ('D' + 'M') L Liquid M Male Human N Not Movable O 'A' + 'II' P Plant Q Animate R Female ('B' + 'P)</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="460" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
DF
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> to leave completely and fQr ever desert to leave (a relation o~ I~iend) in a though~ less or cruel way to give up, esp. without finishing to give (oneself) up completely to a feelo lag, desire, etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> the state when one's feelings and acgions axe uncontxoned freedom from control given up to a life that is though~ ~(~ be immoral see also ABANDON (2,4)  * beat: to hit many times, esp. with a stick (r) kick: to hit with the foot (r) knee: to hi~ with the knee  From this pattern of definitions, we can draw figm'e 1 which shows the semantic hierarchy around to kit: to beat, ~o kick and lo knee are specialized verbs of to kit ~Ib expand this hierarchy, a program to extract the key verbs from a definition is developed. Table 3 (LDBV.D2) shows some examples of this extraction. In table 4, the frequency of key verbs is listed. Most frequently used key verb is l0 make. Note that ~o make and to cause are used to define causative and transitive verbs respectively.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  HW KV PS_ DN DF abase make v 0 to make (someone, esp. oneself) have less self-respect abase make V 0 make humble abash cause v 0 to cause to feel uncomioxtable o~  ashamed in the presence of others abate become v 1 (of winds, storms, disease, pain, etc.) to ~eeome less strong abate decrease v 1 decrease abate mane v 2 &lt;lit&gt; to make less abate bring v 3 &lt;law&gt; to bring to an end (esp. i~ the pht. &lt;abate a nuisance&gt; )  'lYaveming these relations between delined verb and key verb, a thesaurus (network) of verbs has been obtained approximately. Most of the verbs in this tlu.~uurus make s tree-like structure shown in figure 1. Ilowever, several 'loops' are found. A 'loop' exprea~es a cyclic definition: ~o welcome is defined by t0 greet, and to greet is defined by lo welcome. In the network, six typical cyclic definitions are: do: do (the verb to do does not have a key verb.) cha~tge: dtange, move~ come, become ~ go: go, leave get: get, receive stop:: stop, cease o let: let, allow, permit Note that there are many other cyclic definitions in the network. However, most of them have a link to another verb; at least one of the verb in a cyclic definitions is defined by another verb. Since no reader of LDOCE cml understand the meaning of these verbs only from the dictionary, these may be a kind of bug of the dictionary. However, these cyclically defined verbs seem to correspond to semanlic primitives, which are first introduced to AI works by \[Sehank 1975\]. Semantic primitives may be defined outside of linfuislic words. Details of the result of extraction are discussed in \[Nakamura 1986\].</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3">  We cau apply a similar algorithm to definitions of nouns, although the pattern of definitions of nouns is mo~e complex than that of verbs, ln~cting definitions with LDOCE/ttDB, most of them a~e, classified into two forms:  1. {determiner} {adjective}* \]Key Noun {adjective phrase}* 2. {determiner} {adjective}* le-hnction Noun of Key Noun {adjective phrase}*  The first one is a simple form and many of them express is-a relations between a defined:noun and a key noun. For example, abandon: the w~aSe when one's feelings sad actions axe u;acontroIled shows that abandon is-a slate.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> The second form expresses more complex ~mantic relations between nouns.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> abbey: the group of people living in such a building shows that abbey is-a-group-of people.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> A function noun, therefore, explicitly expresses the semantic relation between a head word and a key noun. With terras of a semantic network, defined nouns aml key nouns are nodes in a semantic network, and function nouns (when function noun is empty, its function noun is regared ~ kind) expre~ the name of a link between nodes. The following nouns (41 nouns, in total) are considered to be function nouns, which are mannally extracted.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> is-a: kind, type, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> o part-of: part, side, top, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> member~shlp: set, member, group, class, family, ... (r) action: act, way, action, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> state: state, condition, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> amount: amount, sum, measure, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> degree: degree, quality, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> * form: form, shape, ...</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> A program to extract key nouns and function nouns from the definitions of nouns is developed, rl~ble 5 shows a part of the key noun and fmtction noun table in the LI)OCE/RI)B (LDBN.D2) generated by this program.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> As shown in table 6, the key noun of highest frequency is person (2174 times) and for function noun is type (1064 times) except null function noun (pattern 1).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> 'lYaversing is-a relation, for example, a thesaurus has been obtained \[Nakamura 1987\]. Table 7 shows a part of the autmnatically obtained thesaurus, whose 'root' word is person: actor is a-kind-of person; comedian, ezlra, ham, and mime are a-kind-of actor; comedienne is a-kind-of comedian.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

