<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P01-1021">
<Title>Grammars for Local and Long Dependencies.</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1 Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Syntactic theories based on the concept of dependency have a long tradition. Tesni`ere (Tesni`ere, 1959) was the first who systematically described the sentence structure in terms of binary relations between words (dependencies), which form a dependency tree (D-tree for short). D-tree itself does not presume a linear order on words. However, any its surface realization projects some linear order relation (called also precedence). Some properties of surface syntactic structure can be expressed only in terms of both dependency (or its transitive closure called dominance) and precedence. One of such properties, projectivity, requires that any word occurring between a word a9 and a word a10 dependent on a9 be dominated by a9a12a11 In first dependency grammars (Gaifman, 1961) and in some more recent proposals: link grammars (Sleator and Temperly, 1993), projective dependency grammars (Lombardo and Lesmo, 1996) the projectivity is implied by definition. In some other theories, e.g. in word grammar (Hudson, 1984), it is used as one of the axioms defining acceptable surface structures. In presence of this property, D-trees are in a sense equivalent to phrase structures with head selection 1. It is for this reason that D-trees determined by grammars of Robinson (Robinson, 1970), categorial grammars (Bar-Hillel et al., 1960), classical Lambek calculus (Lambek, 1958), and some other formalisms are projective. Projectivity affects the complexity of parsing : as a rule, it allows dynamic programming technics which lead to polynomial time algorithms (cf. a0a13a1a4a3 a5 a7 -time algorithm for link grammars in (Sleator and Temperly, 1993)). Meanwhile, the projectivity is not the norm in natural languages. For example, in most European languages there are such regular non-projective constructions as WH- or relative clause extraction, topicalization, comparative constructions, and some constructions specific to a language, e.g. French pronominal clitics or left dislocation. In terms of phrase structure, non-projectivity corresponds to discontinuity. In this form it is in the center of discussions till 70-ies. There are various dependency based approaches to this problem. In the framework of Meaning-Text Theory (Mel'Vcuk and Pertsov, 1987), dependencies between (some1See (Dikovsky and Modina, 2000) for more details. times non adjacent) words are determined in terms of their local neighborhood, which leads to non-tractable parsing (the NP-hardness argument of (Neuhaus and Br&amp;quot;oker, 1997) applies to them). More recent versions of dependency grammars (see e.g.(Kahane et al., 1998; Lombardo and Lesmo, 1998; Br&amp;quot;oker, 1998)) impose on non-projective D-trees some constraints weaker than projectivity (cf. meta-projectivity (Nasr, 1995) or pseudo-projectivity (Kahane et al., 1998)), sufficient for existence of a polynomial time parsing algorithm. Still another approach is developed in the context of intuitionistic resource-dependent logics, where D-trees are constructed from derivations (cf. e.g. a method in (Lecomte, 1992) for Lambek calculus). In this context, non-projective D-trees are determined with the use of hypothetical reasoning and of structural rules such as commutativity and associativity (see e.g. (Moortgat, 1990)).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> In this paper, we put forward a novel approach to handling discontinuity in terms of dependency structures. We propose a notion of a polarized dependency (PD-) grammar combining several ideas from cf-tree grammars, dependency grammars and resource-dependent logics. As most dependency grammars, the PD-grammars are analyzing. They reduce continuous groups to their types using local (context-free) reduction rules and simultaneously assign partial dependency structures to reduced groups. The valencies (positive for governors and negative for subordinates) are used to specify discontinuous (long) dependencies lacking in partial dependency structures. The mechanism of establishing long dependencies is orthogonal to reduction and is implemented by a universal and simple rule of valencies saturation. A simplified version of PD-grammars adapted for the theoretical analysis is introduced and explored in (Dikovsky, 2001). In this paper, we describe a notion of PD-grammar more adapted for practical tasks.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

