<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W01-1618">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Paolo Baggia , Giuseppe Castagneri , Morena Danieli, Field trials of the Italian ARISE train timetable system, Speech Communication, v.31 n.4, p.355-367, Aug. 2000 2 L. Lamel , S. Rosset , J. L. Gauvain , S. Bennacef , M. Garnier-Rizet , B. Prouts, The LIMSI ARISE system, Speech Communication, v.31 n.4, p.339-353, Aug. 2000 3 Lavelle, A. C., Calmes, H., Prennov, G., 1999. &amp;quot;Confirmation strategies to improve correction rates in a telephonic inquiry dialogue system&amp;quot;. EUROSPEECH, Budapest, Hungary.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 4 Macas-Guarasa, J. Ferreiros, J., San-Segundo, R., Montero, J. M., and Pardo, JM., 2000. &amp;quot;Acoustical and Lexical Based Confidence Measures for a Very Large Vocabulary Telephone Speech Hypothesis-Verification System&amp;quot;. ICSLP. Beijing, China. 5 Pellom, B., Ward, W., Pradhan, S. 2000. &amp;quot;The CU Communicator: An Architecture for Dialogue Systems&amp;quot;. ICSLP, Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 6 Rudnicky, A., Bennet, C., Black, A., Chotomongcol, A., Lenzo, K., Oh, A., Singh, R. 2000. &amp;quot;Task and domain specific modelling in the Carnegie Mellon Communicator system&amp;quot;. ICSLP, Beijing, China. 7 San-Segundo, R., Pellom, B., Hacioglu, K., Ward, W., and Pardo, JM., 2001. &amp;quot;Confidence measures for Spoken Dialogue Systems&amp;quot;. ICASSP, Salt-Lake-City, Utah, USA.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 8 San-Segundo, R., Cols, J., Ferreiros, J., Macas-Guarasa, J., Pardo, J. M., 2000. &amp;quot;Spanish Recognizer of continuously spelled names over the telephone&amp;quot;. ICSLP, Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 9 Sturm, J., den Os, E., and Boves, L., 1999 &amp;quot;Issues in Spoken Dialogue Systems: Experiences with the Dutch ARISE System&amp;quot;. Proceedings of ESCA Workshop on Interactive Dialogue in MultiModal Systems. Kloter Irsee, Germany, 1--4. 10 Veldhuijzen van Zanten, G., 1999. &amp;quot;User modelling in adaptative dialogue management&amp;quot;. EUROSPEECH, Budapest, Hungary.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

