<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W01-0717">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Chinatsu Aone , Scott Bennett, Applying machine learning to anaphora resolution, Connectionist, Statistical, and Symbolic Approaches to Learning for Natural Language Processing, p.302-314, January 1996 2 Breck Baldwin. 1997. CogNIAC: High precision coreference with limited knowledge and linguistic resources. In Proceedings of the ACL-EACL'97 workshop on operational factors in practical, robust anaphora resolution for unrestricted texts, pages 38--45, Madrid, Spain. 3 Eric T. Bell. 1934. Exponential numbers. American Mathematical Monthly, 41:411--419.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 4 Claire Cardie and Kiri Wagstaff. 1999. Noun phrase coreference as clustering. In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-99), pages 82--89, College Park, Maryland. 5 Michael Collins and James Brooks. 1995. Prepositional phrase attachment through a backed-off model. In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Very Large Corpora (WVLC-3), pages 27--38, Cambridge, Massachusetts. http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/cmp-lg/9506021. 6 Dennis Connolly, John D. Burger, and David S. Day. 1994. A machine learning approach to anaphoric reference. In Proceedings of the International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing, pages 255--261, Manchester, England.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 7 Ido Dagan , Alon Itai, Automatic processing of large corpora for the resolution of anaphora references, Proceedings of the 13th conference on Computational linguistics, p.330-332, August 20-25, 1990, Helsinki, Finland 8 Barbara J. Grosz , Scott Weinstein , Aravind K. Joshi, Centering: a framework for modeling the local coherence of discourse, Computational Linguistics, v.21 n.2, p.203-225, June 1995 9 Sanda M. Harabagiu , Steven J. Maiorano, Multilingual coreference resolution, Proceedings of the sixth conference on Applied natural language processing, p.142-149, April 29-May 04, 2000, Seattle, Washington 10 Sven Hartrumpf. 1999. Hybrid disambiguation of prepositional phrase attachment and interpretation. In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-99), pages 111--120, College Park, Maryland. 11 Hermann Helbig and Sven Hartrumpf. 1997. Word class functions for syntactic-semantic analysis. In Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing (RANLP'97), pages 312--317, Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria, September. 12 Hermann Helbig. 2001. Die semantische Struktur natrlicher Sprache: Wissensreprsentation mit MultiNet. Springer, Berlin.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 13 Lynette Hirschman and Nancy Chinchor. 1997. MUC-7 coreference task definition (version 3.0). In Proceedings of the 7th Message Understanding Conference (MUC-7). http://www.itl.nist.gov/iaui/894.02/related_projects/muc/.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 14 Nancy Ide, Greg Priest-Dorman, and Jean Vronis, 1996. Corpus Encoding Standard. http://www.cs.vassar.edu/CES/.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 15 Slava M. Katz. 1987. Estimation of probabilities from sparse data for the language model component of a speech recognizer. IEEE Transactions on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing, 35(3):400--401, March.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 16 Christopher Kennedy , Branimir Boguraev, Anaphora for everyone: pronominal anaphora resoluation without a parser, Proceedings of the 16th conference on Computational linguistics, August 05-09, 1996, Copenhagen, Denmark 17 Alois Knoll , Christian Altenschmidt , Joachim Biskup , H.-M. Blthgen , Ingo Glckner , Sven Hartrumpf , Hermann Helbig , C. Henning , Reinhard Lling , Burkhard Monien , Thomas Noll , Norbert Sensen, An Integrated Approach to Semantic Evaluation and Content-Based Retrieval of Multimedia Documents, Proceedings of the Second European Conference on Research and Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries, p.409-428, September 21-23, 1998 18 Shalom Lappin , Herbert J. Leass, An algorithm for pronominal anaphora resolution, Computational Linguistics, v.20 n.4, p.535-561, December 1994 19 Ruslan Mitkov. 1995. An uncertainty reasoning approach for anaphora resolution. In Proceedings of the Natural Language Processing Pacific Rim Symposium (NLPRS'95), pages 149--154, Seoul, Korea.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 20 Ruslan Mitkov. 1997. Two engines are better than one: Generating more power and confidence in the search for the antecedent. In Ruslan Mitkov and Nicolas Nicolov, editors, Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing: Selected Papers from RANLP'95, pages 225--234. John Benjamins, Amsterdam. 21 Ruslan Mitkov. 1998a. Evaluating anaphora resolution approaches. In Proceedings of the Second Colloquium on Discourse Anaphora and Anaphor Resolution (DAARC 2), pages 164--177, Lancaster, England.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

