<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W01-1619">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Paolo Baggia , Giuseppe Castagneri , Morena Danieli, Field trials of the Italian ARISE train timetable system, Speech Communication, v.31 n.4, p.355-367, Aug. 2000 2 Nielsole Ole Bernsen , L. Dybkjaer , Laila Dybkjaer, Designing Interactive Speech Systems: From First Ideas to User Testing, Springer-Verlag New York, Inc., Secaucus, NJ, 1997 3 L. F. Lamel , S. K. Bennacef , S. Rosset , L. Devillers , S. Foukia , J. J. Gangolf , J. L. Gauvain, The LIMSI RailTel system: field trial of a telephone service for rail travel information, Speech Communication, v.23 n.1-2, p.67-82, Oct. 1997 4 L. Lamel , S. Rosset , J. L. Gauvain , S. Bennacef , M. Garnier-Rizet , B. Prouts, The LIMSI ARISE system, Speech Communication, v.31 n.4, p.339-353, Aug. 2000 5 Lavelle, A. C., Calmes, H., Prennov, G., 1999. &amp;quot;Confirmation strategies to improve correction rates in a telephonic inquiry dialogue system&amp;quot;. Proc. of EUROSPEECH, Budapest, Hungary. Vol. 3, pp. 1399--1402. 6 Macas-Guarasa, J., Ferreiros, J. Cols, J., Gallardo, A., and Pardo. J. M., 2000a. &amp;quot;Improved Variable List Preselection List Length Estimation Using NNs in a Large Vocabulary Telephone Speech Recognition System&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP, Beijing, China. Vol. II, pp. 823--826. 7 Macas-Guarasa, J., Ferreiros, J., San-Segundo, R., Montero, J. M., and Pardo, J. M., 2000b. &amp;quot;Acoustical and Lexical Based Confidence Measures for a Very Large Vocabulary Telephone Speech Hypothesis-Verification System&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP. Beijing, China. Vol. IV, pp. 446--449. 8 Montero, J. M., Crdoba, R., Vallejo, J. A., Gutirrez-Arriola, J., Enrquez, E., Pardo, J. M., 2000. &amp;quot;Restricted-domain female-voice synthesis in Spanish: from database design to a prosodic modeling&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP. Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 9 Pellom, B., Ward, W., Pradhan, S., 2000. &amp;quot;The CU Communicator: An Architecture for Dialogue Systems&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP, Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 10 Riccardi, G., Gorin, A., 2000. &amp;quot;Stochatic Language Adaptation over time and state in natural spoken dialog systems&amp;quot;. IEEE Trans. on Speech and Audio Processing, Vol 8, pp. 3--10.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 11 Rudnicky, A., Bennet, C., Black, A., Chotomongcol, A., Lenzo, K., Oh, A., Singh, R. 2000. &amp;quot;Task and domain specific modelling in the Carnegie Mellon Communicator system&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP, Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 12 San-Segundo, R., Cols, J., Ferreiros, J., Macas-Guarasa, J., Pardo, J. M., 2000. &amp;quot;Spanish Recognizer of continuously spelled names over the telephone&amp;quot;. Proc. of ICSLP, Beijing, China.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 13 H. Schramm , B. Rueber , A. Kellner, Strategies for name recognition in automatic directory assistance systems, Speech Communication, v.31 n.4, p.329-338, Aug. 2000 14 Sturm, J., den Os, E., and Boves, L., 1999 &amp;quot;Issues in Spoken Dialogue Systems: Experiences with the Dutch ARISE System&amp;quot;. Proceedings of ESCA Workshop on Interactive Dialogue in MultiModal Systems. Kloter Irsee, Germany, 1--4. 15 Veldhuijzen van Zanten, G., &amp;quot;User modelling in adaptive dialogue management&amp;quot;. 1999. Proc. of EUROSPEECH, Budapest, Hungary. Vol. 3, pp. 1183--1186.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 16 Zue, V., Seneff, S., Glass, J., Hetherington, L., Hurley, E., Meng, H., Pao, C., Polifroni, J., Schloming, R., Schmid, P., 1997. &amp;quot;From interface to content: transclingual access and delivery of on-line information&amp;quot;. Proc. of EUROSPEECH, Athenas, Greece.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

