<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="A83-1003">
<Title>INTRODUCING ASK, A SIMPLE KNOWLEDGEABLE SYSTEM</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
ABSTRACT
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> ASK, ~ ~ i m p l e K n o w l e d g e a b l e S y s t e m , i s a t o t a l system for the structuring, manipulation and communication of information. It is a simple system in t h e sense thaC its development concentrated on c l e a n e n g i n e e r i n g solutions to w h a t c o u l d be d o n e now w i t h g o o d r e s p o n s e t i m e s . The user interface is a limited dialect of English. In contrast to expert systems, in which experts build the knowledge base and users make u s e o f t h i s e x p e r t k n o w l e d g e , ASK i s a i m e d a t t h e u s e r who w i s h e s t o c r e a t e , test, modify, extend a n d m a k e u s e o f h i s own k n o w l e d g e b a s e . It is a s y s t e m for a research team, a m a n a g e m e n t or military staff, or a business office.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> some h a v e t h e f o l l o w i n g n u m b e r a t t r i b u t e s : speed length beam &gt;List the destinations a n d home p o r t o f each ship, ship destination home p o r t Ubu New York Naples Tokyo --Morn 0slo Tokyo Kittyhawk</Paragraph>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
Naples Boston Boston -London
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper is designed to give you a feel for the general performance of t h e ASK S y s t e m a n d overview of its operational capabilities. To Chin end, the movie you see will continue throughout the talk. Indeed, the talk itself is a commentary on t h i s b a c k g r o u n d m o v i e . The m o v i e i s bona f i d e and in real time, i t i s o f t h e ASK S y s t e m i n action. (Many o f t h e i l l u s t r a t i o n s from the movie are reproduced in the written paper.) I. ASK AS A DATABASE SYSTEM A. Examples o f ASK English To i n t r o d u c e a few examples you to ASK, we w i l l s t a r t o u t w i t h of queries of a simple data base The uninitiated user may wish London London N e w York --North Scar London New York gimitz London Norfolk Saratoga unknown Norfolk &gt;What c i t i e s a r e t h e home p o r t s o f s h i p s whose d e s t i n a t i o n i s London? Boston London New York Norfolk &gt;Are t h e r e s h i p s t h a t do n o t h a v e a c a r g o ? yes &gt;What i s t h e number o f New York s h i p s ? There are 2 answers: ( 1 ) New York ( d e s t i n a t i o n ) ships 2 ( 2 ) New York (home p o r t ) s h i p s 1 &gt;How many s h i p s a r e t h e r e w i t h l n e g t h g r e a t e r t h a n 600 f e e t ? Spelling correction: &amp;quot; l n e g t h &amp;quot; to &amp;quot; l e n g t h &amp;quot; 4 &gt;What ships t h a t carry wheat go to London or Alamo Oslo? ships that carry wheat London Maru Oslo Alamo &gt;Does the Maru carry wheat and go co London? yes concerning ships. simply to ask: &gt;How many ships are there? 7 &gt;What is known about ships? some are in the following classes: Navy freighter old S. The ASK Data Structures A l t h o u g h in the t e r m i n o l o g y of data base theory, ASK can be considered as an &amp;quot;entityrelation&amp;quot; system, ASK retains its information in records w h i c h are interlinked in a s e m a n t i c net. One reason we refer to ALE as simple is because ic uses only a few kinds of nodes in its s e m a n t i c tanker a l l have t h e f o l l o w i n g a t t r i b u t e s : destination home p o r t some have t h e f o l l o w i n g a t t r i b u t e s : cargo a l l have t h e f o l l o w i n g number a t t r i b u t e s : age 17 net, namely: fio</Paragraph>
</Section>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
Attributes Relations
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> and the ctbvious c o r r e s p o n d i n g arcs. We speak of this as the COAR structure. A~tributes are single valued, e.g., &amp;quot;father&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;home port&amp;quot;, &amp;quot; t i t l e &amp;quot; ; relations may be m u l t i p l e valued, e.g., &amp;quot;child&amp;quot;~ &amp;quot;cargo&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;author&amp;quot;. The d i f f e r e n c e between attributes and relations can be seen in the following p r o t o c o l . &gt;What is the cargo and home port of the Maru? cargo home port wheat London &gt;The home port of Maru is Boston. London has been replaced by Boston as the home port of Maru. &gt;The cargo of Maru is coal. coal has been added as the cargo of Maru. &gt;What i s the cargo and home port of the Maru? cargo home port wheat BosCon coal --&gt;definition:long:paper whose number of pages e x c e e d s 49 Defined.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> &gt;definition:long:book whose number o f p a g e s e x c e e d s 800 Defined.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> &gt;What AI bibliography i t e m s a r e long? There are 2 answers: (1) long:paper whose number of pages exceeds 49 Physical Symbol Systems A General Syntactic P r o c e s s o r (2) long:book whose number of pages exceeds 800 Human Problem Solving &gt;What long books were written in 19727 long:book whose number of pages exceeds 800 Human Problem Solving Family relationships make for a g o o d illustration of definitions; we switch to a small family relationship context. &gt;What are attributes? individual/individual attributes : spouse &gt;What are relations? individua I/individual relations : parent &gt;What are classes? individual classes : male female &gt;What are definitions? definition:mother :female parent definition: father :male parent definition:child:converse of parent definition:sibling:child of parent bur not oneself definition'cousin:child of sibling of parent &gt;List the father and mother of each of Billy Smith's cousins. Billy Smith's cousins father mother Baby Boyd R o b e r t Boyd J i l l Boy C. Extendin K and Hodifyin~ I. Definitions t h e Dat~ To make such a system more knowledgeable, one needs to be able co add d e f i n i t i o n s that e m b o d y interrelationships a m o n g the basic classes, objects, a t t r i b u t e s and relations of the data. The simplest form of definition is synonym: &gt;definition:tub:old Defined. ship Although this form of definition allows one to introduce abbreviations and many forms of jargon, more extensive forms of definition are desirable. Here are three illustrations using the same &amp;quot;ship&amp;quot; file as above. In the third definition, note the use of quotes to create local '~ariables&amp;quot;.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> &gt;definition:area:length * beam Defined &gt;List the length, beam and area of each tub. tub length beam area foot foot foot**2 Ubu 231.667 48 11120.016 Alamo 564.5 84 47418. &gt;definition:meter:39.37 * (foot / 12) Defined. &gt;beam of the Alamo squared in square meters? 655.526472343 square meters &gt;definition:longest &amp;quot;ship&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;ship&amp;quot; whose length is the maximum length of &amp;quot;ship&amp;quot;s Defined. &gt;What is the length in meters of the longest ship whose home port is Naples? 121.920243840 meters T h e n o t i o n of w h a t is l o n g m a y be q u i t e different in another context, say in the context of b i b l i o g r a p h y of a r t i f i c i a l intelligence literature. 18 2. Verbs Most verbs e m b o d y k n o w l e d g e specific to the application in which they are used, the exceptions being the copula verbs. Therefore the only verbs initially known to the ASK System are &amp;quot;to be&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;to have&amp;quot;. The user c a n add n e w v e r b s by paraphrase. &gt;verb:ships &amp;quot;go&amp;quot; to New York:destination of ships is New York Defined. &gt;verb:ships &amp;quot;carry&amp;quot; coal from London to Boston:ships have coal as cargo, have L o n d o n as home port and go to Boston Defined.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> &gt;Each old ship carries what cargo to each port? old ship port cargo Ubu New York oil Tokyo oil Alamo London wheat coal fi&gt;What i s c a r r i e d by t h e Alamo? wheat coal &gt;Wheat i s c a r r i e d to London from what p o r t s ? New York &gt;What c i t i e s does t h e Alamo c a r r y wheat to? London  &gt;Create t h e a t t r i b u t e : r a t i n g The a t t r i b u t e r a t i n g h a s been a d d e d . &gt;Create i n d i v i d u a l s : s e m i n a l , e x c e l l e n t , f a i r and i m p o s s i b l e The f o l l o w i n g i n d i v i d u a l s have been added: seminal excellent fair impossible &gt;The r a t i n g o f W i n o g r a d ' s 1980 p a p e r i n Cognitive Science is excellent. e x c e l l e n t h a s been added a s t h e r a t i n g o f W i n o g r a d ' 8 1980 p a p e r in C o g n i t i v e S c i e n c e &gt;Rating o f A Framework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g In p r a c t i c a l s y s t e m s f o r e x p e r t s , a b b r e v i a t e d f o r m s of a d d r e s s i n g t h e c o m p u t e r a r e common. Thus the ability to h a n d l e p r o n o m i n a l and e l l i p t i c a l constructions are of considerable importance. A l t h o u g h t h e r e has been p r o g r e s s i n t h e l a s t few years in the linguistic understanding of these c o n s t r u c t i o n s , many d i f f i c u l t i e s r e m a i n . However, b u i l d i n g on t h e work t h a t ham been a c c o m p l i s h e d , many o f t h e s e c o n s t r u c t i o n s can be h a n d l e d by t h e ASK System. In o r d e r to a v o i d m i s l e a d i n g t h e u s e r when t h e c o m p u t a t i o n a l a l g o r i t h m does not make t h e c o r r e c t i n t e r p r e t a t  i o n , echo i s u s e d t o i n f o r m t h e u s e r of t h e i n t e r p r e t a t i o n t h a t h a s been t a k e n . &gt;Is t h e r e a s h i p whose d e s t i n a t i o n i s unknown? yes &gt;What is it? What is it [ship whose destination is ..knov.] ? Saratoga &gt;Is its cargo wheat or c o a l ? I s i t s [ s h i p whose d e s t i n a t i o n i s unknown] cargo wheat or c o a l ? wheat no coal yes &gt;Does t h e A l a m o ' s l e n g t h exceed t h a t of t h e Ubu? yes &gt;What about t h e N o r t h e r n S t a r ? [the Northern Star?] does t h e A l a m o ' s l e n g t h exceed t h a t of t h e Northern Star? no &gt;Is i t s cargo wheat? Is its [Northern Star] cargo wheat? no &gt;Is it that of the Ubu? Is i t [Norther, Star cargo] that [cargo] of the Obu? yes &gt;Wheat is carried by how many ships? 2 &gt;Coal and oil? c o a l and o i l i s c a r r i e d by how many ship*? coal I oil 2 &gt;by the Ubu? c o a l and o i l i s c a r r i e d by t h e Ubu? coal no oil yes Knowledge i s i m p o s s i b l e .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> i m p o s s i b l e h a s been added as t h e r a t i n g o f A remework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g Knowledge. &gt;Scripts, P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g ' s rating is se~.nal. s e m i n a l h a s been added a s t h e r a t i n g o f S c r i p t s , P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> &gt;The r a t i n g o f M i n s k y ' s paper i n The P s y c h o l o g y of Computer V i s i o n is seminal. i m p o s s i b l e has been r e p l a c e d by s e m i n a l as t h e r a t i n g o f M i n s k y ' s p a p e r i n The P s y c h o l o g y o f Computer V i s i o n . &gt; L i s t t h e a u t h o r of e a c h paper t h a t h a s a r a t i n g o f e i t h e r s e m i n a l or e x c e l l e n t .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> paper S c r i p t s , Plans, Goals and Understanding R. C. Schauk A Framework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g Knowledge M. Minsky What Does I t Mean to U n d e r s t a n d N a t u r a l Language To Winograd &gt; r e l a t i o n : keyword The r e l a t i o n keyword h a s been added. &gt;individuals:context, natural language, knowledge r e p r e s e n t a t i o n The f o l l o w i n g i n d i v i d u a l s have been added: c o n t e x t n a t u r a l l a n g u a g e knowledge representation &gt;Context and knowledge r e p r e s e n t a t i o n a r e k e ~ o r d a of S c r i p t s , P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g and A Framework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g Knowledge. c o n t e x t knowledge r e p r e s e n t a t i o n have been added as keywords o f S c r i p t s , P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g . c o n t e x t knowledge r e p r e s e n t a t i o n have been added as keywords o f A Framework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g Knowledge. &gt; N a t u r a l l a n g u a g e i s a keyword of S c r i p t s , P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g . n a t u r a l l a n g u a g e h a s been added a s keyword of Scripts, Plans, Goals and Understanding. &gt;definition:about &amp;quot;booka'*:converse of keyword of &amp;quot;books&amp;quot; Defined. &gt;What AI Sibliosraphy items are about knowledge r e p r e s e n t a t i o n ? S c r i p t s , P l a n s , Goals and U n d e r s t a n d i n g A Framework f o r R e p r e s e n t i n g Knowledge D. Inheritanc~ 4. E x t e n d i n 2 th_...eeVocabular 7 an...~dDa~a Bas~ New o b j e c t s , c l a s s e s , a t t r i b u t e s and r e l a t i o n s may be a d d e d a t w i l l . T h i s w i l l be i l l u s t r a t e d using the AI Bibliography. 19  Classes, as well as objects, may be t h e a r g u m e n t s or v a l u e s o f a t t r i b u t e s and r e l a t i o n s . T h i s r a i s e s t h e q u e s t i o n of i n h e r i t a n c e of properties and attributes. The a n s w e r is to be fifound in the following protocol, using attribute of color; inheritance for relations h a n d l e d i n s i m i l a r ways. &gt;class: r a c i n g sloop, sports b o a t , Norwegian The following classes have been added: racing sloop sports boat Norwegian &gt;attribute: color The a t t r i b u t e c o l o r h a s been a d d e d . &gt;individuals: white, blue, b l a c k , g r a y The following i n d i v i d u a l s have b e e n added: white blue black gray &gt;Saratoga is a racing sloop. S a r a t o g a has b e e n added to r a c i n g s l o o p .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> &gt;Racing s l o o p s a r e s p o r t s b o a t s . r a c i n g s l o o p s have b e e n added to s p o r t s boats. &gt;Alamo is industrial and Norwegian. Alamo has b e e n added to i n d u s t r i a l Norwegian. &gt;The c o l o r o f s p o r t s b o a t s i s w h i t e . w h i t e h a s b e e n added a s c o l o r o f s p o r t s boats &gt;Maru's color is gray. g r a y has b e e n added a s c o l o r o f Maru. &gt;Black i s t h e c o l o r of i n d u s t r i a l . b l a c k has b e e n added as t h e c o l o r o f industrial. &gt;Blue is the color of Norwegian. b l u e h a s b e e n added a s t h e color of Norwegian. &gt;What i s the color of each s h i p ? There are 3 answers: (t) ship color Maru gray Saratoga white (2) Alamo as industrial ship color Alamo black (3) Alamo as Norwegian ship color Alamo blue the is There are 2 answers: ( i ) T h e r e a r e no p o r t s ( 2 ) T h e r e a r e no U.S. d e s t i n a t i o n s o f Maru. &gt; I s some E u r o p e a n p o r t a p o r t o f Maru? The f o l l o w i n g word i s n o t i n t h e v o c a b u l a r y : portof Correction: Is some European port a port of Maru? There is no port.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> &gt;London is Alamo's port. London h a s b e e n added a s t h e p o r t o f Alamo. &gt; I s som E u r o p e a n p o r t a p r o t o f Maru? Spelling corrections: &amp;quot;son&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;some&amp;quot; &amp;quot;prot&amp;quot; tO &amp;quot; p o r t &amp;quot; T h e r e i s no p o r t o f Maru. &gt;New York i s M a r u ' s p o r t . New York h a s b e e n added a s p o r t o f Maru. &gt; I s some E u r o p e a n p o r t a p o r t o f Maru. I s some E u r o p e a n p o r t a p o r t o f Maru? no</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Section>
</Paper>

