<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="E83-1005">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
ABSTRACT
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> A computer program for the automatic translation of any text of Italian into naturally fluent synthetic speech is presented. The program, or Phonological Processor (hence FP) maps into prosodic structures the phonological rules of Italian.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Structural information is provided by such hierarchical prosodic constituents as Syllable (S), Metrical Foot (HF), Phonological Word (PW), Intonational Group (IG). Onto these structures, phonological rules are applied such as the &amp;quot;letter-to-sound&amp;quot; rules, automatic word stress rules,internal stress hierarchy rules indicating secondary stress,external sandhi rules, phonological focus assignment rules, logical focus assignment rules. The FP constitutes also a model to simulate the reading process aloud, and the psycholinguistics and cognitive aspects related will be discussed in the computational model of the FP.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> At present, Logical Focus assignment rules and the computational model are work in progress still to be implemented in the FP. Recorded samples of automatically produced synthetic speech will be presented at the conference to i11ustrate the functioning of the rules.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> O. Introduction The FP which we shall describe in detail in the following pages, is the terminal section of a system of speech synthesis by rule without vocabulary restrictions, implemented at the Centre of Computational Sonology of the University of Padua.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> From the linguistic point of view the FP is a model to simulate the operations carried out by an Italian speaker when reading aloud any text. To this end, the speaker shall use the rules of his internal grammar to translate graphic signs into natural speech. These rules wi11 have to be implemented in the FP, together with a computational mechanism simulating the psychological end cognitive functions of the reading process.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> I. The Phonologlcal Rules At the phonological level the FP has to account for low level or segmental phenomena, and high level or suprasegmental ones. The former are represented by three levels of structure, that is S, MF, PW and are governed by phonological rules which are meant to render the movements of the vocal tract and the coarticulatory effects which occur regularly at word level and at word boundaries. The latter are represented by one level of structure, the IG, and are governed by rules which account for long range phenomena like pitch contour formation, intonation centre assignment, pauses. In brief, the rules that the FP shall have to apply are the following: i. transcription from grapheme to nphoneme&amp;quot;, including the most regular coarticulatory and allophonic phenomena of the It~dian language; ii. automatic word stress assignment, including all the most frequent exceptions to the rules as well as individuation of homographs, which are very common in Italian; iii. internal word stress hierarchy, with secondary stres/es assignment, individuation of unstressed dipththongs, triphthongs, hiatuses; iv. external sandhi rules, operating at word boundaries and resulting in stress retraction, destressing, stress hierarchy modification, elision by assimilation and other phenomena; v. destressing of functional words listed in a table lookup; vi. pauses marked off by punctuation; pauses deriving from a count of PWs; pauses deriving from syntactic structural phenomena; comma intonation marking of parentheticals and similar structures; vii. rules to restructure the IG when too long - more than ? PWs, or too short - less than 5 PWs; viii. Focus Assignment Rules or FAR, which at first mark Phonological Focus, or intonation centre dependent on lexical and phonologically determined phenomena; ix. FAR which mark Logical Focus or intonation centre dependent on structurally determined phenomena.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> From a general computational point of view,the FP operates bottom-up to apply low level rules, analysing each word at a time until the PW structure is reached; it operates top-down to apply high level rules and to build the higher structure, the IG.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

