<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J04-4004">
<Title>c(c) 2004 Association for Computational Linguistics Intricacies of Collins' Parsing Model</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="480" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Michael Collins' (1996, 1997, 1999) parsing models have been quite influential in the field of natural language processing. Not only did they achieve new performance benchmarks on parsing the Penn Treebank (Marcus, Santorini, and Marcinkiewicz 1993), and not only did they serve as the basis of Collins' own future work (Collins 2000; Collins and Duffy 2002), but they also served as the basis of important work on parser selection (Henderson and Brill 1999), an investigation of corpus variation and the effectiveness of bilexical dependencies (Gildea 2001), sample selection (Hwa 2001), bootstrapping non-English parsers (Hwa, Resnik, and Weinberg 2002), and the automatic labeling of semantic roles and predicate-argument extraction (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000; Gildea and Palmer 2002), as well as that of other research efforts.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Recently, in order to continue our work combining word sense with parsing (Bikel 2000) and the study of language-dependent and -independent parsing features (Bikel and Chiang 2000), we built a multilingual parsing engine that is capable of instantiating a wide variety of generative statistical parsing models (Bikel 2002).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  As an appropriate baseline model, we chose to instantiate the parameters of Collins' Model 2. This task proved more difficult than it initially appeared. Starting with Collins' (1999) thesis, we reproduced all the parameters described but did not achieve nearly the same high performance on the well-established development test set of Section 00 of [?] Department of Computer and Information Science, 3330 Walnut Street, Philadelphia, PA 19104. E-mail:  Submission received: 18 January 2003; Revised submission received: 20 March 2004; Accepted for publication: 10 June 2004  Computational Linguistics Volume 30, Number 4 the Penn Treebank. Together with Collins' thesis, this article contains all the information necessary to replicate Collins' parsing results.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3">  Specifically, this article describes all the as-yet-unpublished details and features of Collins' model and some analysis of the effect of these features with respect to parsing performance, as well as some comparative analysis of the effects of published features.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  In particular, implementing Collins' model using only the published details causes an 11% increase in relative error over Collins' own published results. That is, taken together, all the unpublished details have a significant effect on overall parsing performance. In addition to the effects of the unpublished details, we also have new evidence to show that the discriminative power of Collins' model does not lie where once thought: Bilexical dependencies play an extremely small role in Collins' models (Gildea 2001), and head choice is not nearly as critical as once thought. This article also discusses the rationale for various parameter choices. In general, we will limit our discussion to Collins' Model 2, but we make occasional reference to Model 3, as well.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

