<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W04-1803">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> L. Ahrenberg et al. 1998. A simple hybrid aligner for generating lexical correspondences in parallel texts. COLING ACL.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> J. Breen. EDICT. online.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> N. Collier et al. 1997. Acquisition of English-Japanese proper nouns from noisy-parallel newswire articles using KATAKANA matching. Proc. of the Natural Language Processing Pacific Rim Symposium 1997. A. Fujii and T. Ishikawa. 2001. Japanese English cross-language information retrieval: exploration of query translation and transliteration. Computers and the Humanities. W. A. Gale and K. W. Church. 1991. Identifying word correspondances in parallel texts. DARPA Speech and Natural Language Workshop.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> D. Himestra. 1997. Deriving a bilingual lexicon for cross-language information retrieval. Proc. 4th Groningen International Information Technology Conference for Students. K. S. Jeong et al. 1999. Automatic identification and back-transliteration of foreign words for information retrieval. Information processing and management. M. Kitamura and Y. Matsumoto. 1996. Automatic extraction of word sequence correspondences in parallel corpora. VLC workshop.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> K. Knight and J. Graehl. 1997. Machine transliteration. ACL.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> J. Kupiec. 1993. An algorithm for finding noun phrase correspondances in bilingual corpora. EACL.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> I. D. Melamed. 2000. Models of translational equivalence among words. Computational Linguistics.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> H. Omae et al. 2003. Extraction of compound word translation from non-parallel japanese-french text in world wide web. Proc. of workshop PAPILLON 2003 on multilingual lexical databases. F. Samdja et al. 1996. Translating collocations for bilingual lexicons: a statistical approach. Computational Linguistics.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> K. Tsuji. 2002. Automatic extraction of translational japanese-KATAKANA and english word pairs from bilingual corpora. International Journal of Computer Processing of Oriental Languages.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

