<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W04-1312">
<Title>Normal Compressed + Visual Digits Noise + Visual Digits Low Pass + Compression</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="85" end_page="86" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> We evaluate the inferences that can be drawn from dissociations in syntax processing identified in developmental disorders and acquired language deficits. We use an SRN to simulate empirical data from Dick et al. (2001) on the relative difficulty of comprehending different syntactic constructions under normal conditions and conditions of damage. We conclude that task constraints and internal computational constraints interact to predict patterns of difficulty. Difficulty is predicted by frequency of constructions, by the requirement of the task to focus on local vs. global sequence information, and by the ability of the system to maintain sequence information. We generate a testable prediction on the empirical pattern that should be observed under conditions of developmental damage.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 1 Dissociations in language function Behavioural dissociations in language, identified both in cases of acquired brain damage in adults and in developmental disorders, have often been used to infer the functional components of the underlying language system. Generally these attempted fractionations appeal to broad distinctions within language. However, fine-scaled dissociations have also been proposed, such as the loss of individual semantic categories or of particular linguistic features in inflecting verbs. Here, we consider the implications of developmental and acquired deficits for the nature of syntax processing.</Paragraph>
<Section position="1" start_page="85" end_page="85" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
1.1 Developmental deficits
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> A comparison of developmental disorders such as autism, Downs syndrome, Williams syndrome, Fragile-X syndrome, and Specific Language Impairment reveals that dissociations can occur between phonology, lexical semantics, morphosyntax, and pragmatics. The implications of such fractionations remain controversial but will be contingent on understanding the developmental origins of language structures (Karmiloff-Smith, 1998). These processes remain to be clarified even for the normal course of development.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> In the area of syntax, Fowler (1998) concluded that a consistent picture emerges. Individuals with learning disabilities are systematic in their grammatical knowledge, follow the normal course of development, and show similar orders of difficulty in acquiring constructions. However, such individuals can often handle only limited levels of syntactic complexity and therefore development seems to terminate at a lower level.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> While there is great variability in linguistic function both across different disorders and within single disorders, this cannot be attributed solely to differences in general cognitive functioning (e.g., as assessed by problem solving ability). Syntax acquisition is therefore to some extent independent of IQ. However, adults with developmental disorders who have successfully acquired syntax typically have mental ages of at least 6 or 7, an age at which typically developing children also have well-structured language. The variability in outcome has been attributed to various factors specific to language, including verbal working memory and the quality of phonological representations (Fowler, 1998; McDonald, 1997).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Most notably, disorders with different cognitive abilities show similarity in syntactic acquisition.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> The apparent lack of deviance across heterogeneous disorders has been used to argue for a model of language acquisition that is heavily constrained by the brain that is acquiring the language (Newport, 1990).</Paragraph>
</Section>
<Section position="2" start_page="85" end_page="86" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
1.2 Acquired deficits in adulthood
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> One of the broadest distinctions in acquired language deficits is between Brocas and Wernickes aphasia. Brocas aphasics are sometimes described as having greater deficits in grammar processing, and Wernickes aphasics as having greater deficits in lexical processing. The dissociation is taken to support the idea that the division between grammar and the lexicon is one of the constraints that the brain brings to language acquisition.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Dick et al. (2001) recently argued that four types of evidence undermine this claim: (1) all aphasics  have naming deficits to some extent; (2) apparently agrammatic patients retain knowledge of grammar that can be exhibited in grammaticality judgements; (3) grammar deficits are found in many populations both with and without damage to Brocas area, the reputed seat of syntax in the brain; and (4) aphasic symptoms of language comprehension can be simulated in normal adults by placing them in stressed conditions (e.g., via manipulating the speech input or giving the subject a distracter task). Dick et al. pointed out that in syntax comprehension, the constructions most resilient in both aphasic patients and normal adults with simulated aphasia are those that are most regular or most frequent, and conversely those liable to errors are non-canonical and/or low frequency. Dick et al. (2001) illustrated these arguments in an experiment that compared comprehension of four complex syntactic structures:  x Actives (e.g., The dog [subject] is biting the cow [object]) x Subject Clefts (e.g., It is the dog [subject] that is biting the cow [object]) x Passives (e.g., The cow [object] is bitten by the dog [subject]) x Object Clefts (e.g., It is the cow [object] that  the dog [subject] is biting) The latter two constructions are lower frequency, and have non-canonical word orders in which the object precedes the subject. Dick et al. tested 56 adults with different types of aphasia on a task that involved identifying the agent of spoken sentences. Patients with all types of aphasia demonstrated lower performance on Passives and Object Clefts than Actives and Subject Clefts. Moreover, normal adults given the same task but with a degraded speech signal (either speeded up, low-pass filtered, or with noise added) or in combination with a distracter task (such as remembering a set of digits) produced a similar profile of performance to the aphasics (see Figure 1).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Dick et al. (2001) argued that the common pattern of deficits could be explained by the Competition Model (MacWhinney &amp; Bates, 1989), which proposes that the difficulty of acquiring certain aspects of language and their retention after brain damage could be explained by considering cue validity (the reliability of a source of information in predicting the structure of a target language) and cue cost (the difficulty of processing each cue). Cues high in validity and low in cost, such as Subject-Verb-Object word order in English, should be acquired more easily and be relatively spared in adult breakdown. The proposal is that for a given language, any domain-general processing system placed under sub-optimal  data from Dick et al. (2001) conditions should exhibit a similar pattern of developmental or acquired deficits. Thus Dick et al. predicted that a connectionist model trained on an appropriate frequency-weighted corpus would show equivalent vulnerability of non-canonical word orders and low frequency constructions under conditions of damage. In contrast to the inferences drawn from developmental deficits, the focus here is on attributing similarities in patterns of acquired deficits to features of the problem domain rather than constraints of the language system.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Section>
</Paper>

