<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="H90-1008">
<Title>Picking Reference Events from Tense A Formal, Implement able Theory of English Tense-Aspect Semantics Trees:</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="37" end_page="40" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
\[~OT ** eT\]),
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> tree transformation: (pres 9)&amp;quot; r = 9. (or) Here e T is assumed to be a new episode variable name uniquely defined for any given T (e.g., the letter e with subscript i where i is the least integer such that ei does not yet occur in T). &amp;quot;OT&amp;quot; means &amp;quot;store e T at the focal node of T.&amp;quot; Emb T denotes the last-added episode at the node which directly embeds the tree containing the focal node of T. (This is usually an episode corresponding to a performative or attitude verb.) If there is no embedding node, Emb T is the Now-point of the current context.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Last T is the last-stored episode variable at the focus of T.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Thus the de-indexicalization rule &amp;quot;creates&amp;quot; a new episode token, which it predicates to be at about the time of embedding event (e.g., the assertion of the sentence being processed), designates the last-stored episode at the current focus as the point of orientation for the new episode, and states that the formula 9 on which pres operates, after recursive de-indexicalization (with e T now stored at the focus), characterizes the new episode.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The tree transformation which is induced by this de-indexicalization (in the implementation, as a side effect) is separately stated above. The dot symbolizes the tree-structure transformation function,</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Thus, the effect of (pres 9) on T is just storage of e T at the focus of T, followed by whatever additional transformations 9 induces. (Note that the function composition in &amp;quot;9 * (OT)&amp;quot; is read &amp;quot;from the inside to the outside,&amp;quot; as usual.) Next, the de-indexicalization of past is given by Past: (past 9)T ~ (JET: \[\[e T before EaUbT\] A \[Last/, T orients eT\] \]</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> tree transformation: (past if)&amp;quot; T = T(9&amp;quot; (O~,/T)) Here &amp;quot;l T&amp;quot; signifies T with the focus displaced to the left (i.e., past) daughter, with creation of a new daughter if necessary. Thus the orienting episode for the new past episode e T is the last-stored episode at the past daughter of the focal node. (So for a succession of simple past-tensed sentences, each episode generated will orient the next one. As well, all of them will be before their embedding episode, i.e., the appropriate sentence utterance.) Again, the recursively de-indexicalized 9 (with the T-focus shifted left and e T stored there) is taken to characterize the new episode. In the tree transformation equation, the upward arrow signals upward displacement of the focus to the mother. This restores the focus to its original position, assuming that recursive processing of q~ has no net effect on the focus (which it doesn't, thanks to the way the remaining rules work).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> Actually, the above Past-rule is a slight simplification. It applies as stated only when the focal node is not &amp;quot;past-dominated,&amp;quot; i.e., if there are no past-branches in its ancestry (with embedding links counting as ancestry links). If the focus is past-dominated, \[e T before ErabT\] is replaced by \[e T at-or-before EmbT\]. Here at-or-before is regarded as a context-charged relation, with different probable consequences depending on the aspectual class of its first argument. In particular, for stative eT, \[e T at-or-before EmbT\] strongly suggests \[e T at ErabT\]. This is  aimed at &amp;quot;sequence of tense&amp;quot; phenomena, observable in sentences like (11) John knew that Mary left.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> (12) John knew Mary had a cold.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10">  For (11), our rules predict that the &amp;quot;leaving&amp;quot; is strongly preferred to be prior to the &amp;quot;knowing&amp;quot; (though a variant like &amp;quot;John noticed that Mary winked at him&amp;quot; forces a concurrent-event reading); while for (12), they predict that the &amp;quot;cold&amp;quot; episode is strongly preferred to be at the same time as the &amp;quot;knowing&amp;quot; episode (though a variant like &amp;quot;John remembered that Mary had a cold when they got married&amp;quot; forces an earlier-episode reading).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> To understand the next rule, recall that we take will and would (in their future and future-in-the-past readings) to consist logically of tense plus the futr operator. Thus the futr operator is encountered only after its implicit tense operator has been processed, so that a characterizing (&amp;quot;**&amp;quot;) relation will already embed the (futr if) expression.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> Futr: \[(futr 9)T ** ~\] ~-~ \[(JET: \[\[e T after r/\] A</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> tree transformation: (futr 9)&amp;quot; r = T (~&amp;quot; (O\ r)) This is quite analogous to pres and past, except that the temporal location of the new episode e T is specified relative to the episode 7/(usually a present or past episode) characterized by &amp;quot;having 9 true in its future,&amp;quot; rather than relative to an &amp;quot;embedding episode.&amp;quot; Also, (F r/) in the rule denotes &amp;quot;the facts about r/.&amp;quot; Roughly speaking, this is needed because the formula preceding &amp;quot;** (F r/)&amp;quot; is an atemporal characterization of the propositional content of r/ (one that is simply true or false, rather than true of some episodes and false of others); whereas (futr 9)W is a temporal characterization of r/(&amp;quot;being followed at some future time by a 9-episode&amp;quot; can be true of some episodes - namely, those that do precede a 9-episode and false of others). The &amp;quot;** (F ~)&amp;quot; could be dropped without falsifying the forward direction of the equivalence. null For the perfect, we need to assume an ambiguity: the present perfect auxiliary (has or have) is always translated as APAz&lt;pres (pert1 \[z P\])&gt; (so that apart from the tense, the perfect is logically pert1); but when occurring untensed or in combination with past, the perfect is  Here recent-subep is another context-charged relation, which for a state-change e of type C/ as first argument suggests the truth of \[~ * (fin r\])\], whenever \[C/ ** eli entails \[~ * (fin el)\] for all el (where fin means &amp;quot;final moment of'). For instance, consider  (13) John has been sleeping.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> (14) John has woken up.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16">  For (13), we will get a subformula \[(prog \[John sleep\]) @ e~\], for some i. Since progressives are stative, this is equivalent to \[(prog \[John sleep\]) * ei\], meaning that John is sleeping over the entire episode ei. This episode lasts until &amp;quot;rf' in the complete formula, which is nothing else but the reference episode for the perfect (corresponding to Reichenbach's reference time). For (13), this 7/is a &amp;quot;present&amp;quot; episode (by the Pres-rule), so (13) means, in effect, that John has been sleeping until now. We take this to be the desired inference.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> For (14), we will get a subformula \[\[John wake-up\] @ ei\], and since this is nonstative, (Je: \[e recent-subep ei\] \[\[John wake-up\] * e\]).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="18"> Since further \[\[John wake-up\] ** el\] entails \[\[John awake\] * (fin el)\] for all el (via suitable meaning postulates), this suggests \[\[John awake\] * (fin ei)\], where as in (13), ei lasts until r\], the (present) reference episode. In other words, John is still awake. Note that this is only an implication, since we can perfectly well say, without contradiction, &amp;quot;John has woken up and fallen asleep again.&amp;quot; The second variant of perfect is simpler, amounting to a &amp;quot;relative past&amp;quot;:  Note that in the Perf(1)-rule, episode e T was taken to last until the reference episode, and to be only indirectly characterized by * (via &amp;quot;@&amp;quot;); here e T is before the reference episode, and is directly characterized by C/ (after de-indexicalization). The two main consequences are, first, that there is no longer an implication that a stative episode persists to the reference time; and second, the episode stored in the tense tree is now the actual if-event, not an episode which by inference contains a C-event. The differences between perfl and perf2 help to account for the following contrasts:  (15) a. *John has left yesterday.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="19"> b. John had left the day before.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="20"> c. John will have left the day before.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="21"> (16) a. John has woken up and *has immediately dressed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="22"> b. John had woken up and had immediately dressed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="23"> c. John will have woken up and will immediately  have dressed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="24"> On our account, only perfl is available in the asentences; so in (15)a, we do not get &amp;quot;John's leaving&amp;quot; stored in the tense tree, but only an episode containing John's leaving and lasting till now - but that cannot possibly be contained in yesterday. Similarly in (16)a, John's waking up is not directly stored in the tense tree, and so is not directly available in the interpretation of immediately. (We think that there may be a recovery mechanism in the interpretation of adverbials, which looks for suitable points of orientation in the history list (where we assume that all indefinites and definites are recorded, whether explicitly mentioned or inferred) after failing to find them in the tense tree.) In the b and c sentences in (15) and (16), no difficulties are encountered because of the availability of the perf2 reading.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="25"> Perhaps the most important point about our treatment of the perfect, alluded to earlier, is that the reference episode is introduced simply by the normal effect of operators (usually past, pres or futr) &amp;quot;exterior&amp;quot; to it. Briefly reconsidering (9)b, for example, we see that the (wide-scope) past will generate an episode in the past relative to the time of speech, and oriented by the &amp;quot;entering&amp;quot; episode in (9)a. It is this past episode which becomes the reference episode for the perfect. Now the key to the seemingly anaphoric character of this reference episode is this: if \[el orients e2\], and e2 is stative, then there is a strong suggestion that e2 is either concurrent with el (namely, when ex is stative as well) or contiguous with its end point (when el is nonstative).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="26"> This is apparent, for instance, in the following variant of  (9): (177) a. John entered the room.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="27"> b. His paintings were gone.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="28"> c. In their place were Schwarzenegger posters.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="29">  In b, the episode of the paintings being gone covers (at least) a short time-span immediately following John's entering. In c, the episode of the posters being in place is concurrent with the paintings being gone, since both episodes are stative. Now, recognizing that perfect reference episodes are stative (because the state of being after some given type of event can persist indefinitely, and holds of the subintervals of any intervals of which it holds), the same analysis places the past episode in (9) b (serving as reference episode for the perfect) right after John's entering, contiguous with it. This is tantamount to making the end of John's entering the &amp;quot;reference time&amp;quot; for the perfect. So we get the desired &amp;quot;anaphoric&amp;quot; effect, without treating past as anaphoric, and without singling out the past in past perfect for special treatment.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="30"> Next we mention the de-indexicalization rules for That- and that-nominalizations: That(l): (That ~)T =(That ~T), tree transformation:</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="32"> The rules cause focus shifts to the root of an embedded tree, indicated by the ~ and ~ operations. The  first of t:hese always adds a new embedding link whose destination is a new root node, whereas the second only does so if no embedding link exists at the current focus; otherwise, it causes re-traversal of the last embedding link added at the current focus. The leftward arrows in the two rules indicate focus restoration much like the upward arrows in the preceding rules. Intuitively, the distinction between a sentence nominalization derived explicitly from the text and one introduced through an implicit performative is motivated by the following sort  of contrast: (18) a. John knows that Mary got home before midnight* null b. He also knows that she watched a movie* (19) a. Mary got home before midnight.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="33"> b. She watched a movie.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="34">  In (18) the sentences about Mary in a and b are objects of attitudes, and it is much less clear than in (19) whether they refer to successive episodes. Now, the LFs for (19)a,b will contain performative predicates and that-nominalization operators; since the rule for that causes re-traversal of embedding links, the a and b episodes will end up at the same node. But in (18) only the &amp;quot;knowing&amp;quot; episodes map to the same node, while the episodes involving Mary map to different embedded nodes. Thus it will be harder to establish a connection between them (i.e., tense structure alone Will not establish a connection though inference based on other information still might).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="35"> Before proceeding to further rules we illustrate some of the ones so far with a &amp;quot;trace&amp;quot; of an LF deindexicalization, namely, that of sentence (21), uttered right after (20): (20) Mary looked pale.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="36"> (21) John realized that Mary was tired.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="37"> The tree structure after processing of (20) will be T= (r)'e~p deg - e 1 where e0 corresponds to the added performative - i.e., the speaker's utterance of (20), and el corresponds to Mary's looking pale at a point in the past. The logical form of (121) is initially (without performative) \[John &lt;past realize&gt; (That \[Mary &lt;past tired&gt;\])\]. and after scoping and addition of the implicit performative, null  where T' = (~)....-po el / Next, a simple rule we have not mentioned moves the T ~ inward to the that-clause. The That(2)-rule causes retraversal of the embedding link, and the Past-rule then gives the following altered form of the outer that-clause: (That (3e3:\[\[e3 before e2\] A \[el orients e3\]\] \[\[John realize (That (past \[Mary tired\]))\]T,, ** e3\])) eoe2 where T&amp;quot; = * .........</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="38"> Again T&amp;quot; is moved inward to the embedded That-clause, and the That (1)-rule generates a new embedding link and tree root at the focal node. It then remains to process the innermost tensed clause (past \[Mary tired\])T,,</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="40"> One more application of the Past-rule, but keeping in mind that we are now at a past-dominated node, converts the tensed clause to (3e4:\[e4 at-or-before ea\] \[\[Mary tired\] ** e4\]) assuming the orienting predication is omitted when there is no orienting episode. The final tree structure will be Since e4 is stative (given its characterization \[Mary tired\]), the inference from the context-charged predication is that e4 is concurrent with e3 (i.e., John's realization), in the absence of contrary information. Also the earlier context-charged relation \[el orients e3\] will lead to the inference that John's realization was during Mary's looking pale, in view of the fact that el is stative and e3 nonstative. (As well, a causal relation can be tentatively inferred.) The results of de-indexicalization thus seem to be in complete accord with intuition.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="41"> Besides the above rules, our current theory includes rules for conjunction, negation, quantification, and some adverbials and nominalizations. However, space limitations prevent inclusion of any details. Untensed conjunctions, negation and quantification introduce episodes for * the clauses they operate on, explaining phenomenon like illustrated in (3) and (4). Adverbs and PP-adverbials of temporal location, duration, and manner are treated in a uniform way that de-indexicalizes them into predications about episodes. However, we make no attempt as yet to  interpret anaphoric NPs in those PPs (such as the NP in before C/he war). Also, relative clauses and clausal adverbials remain largely beyond the scope of our present work.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="42"> V. Conclusions and Further Work We have described a new, principled approach to tense and aspect interpretation within a compositional framework for language understanding. The central concept is that of a tense tree structure as part of a more general context structure. This provides a straightforward and easily visualized way of converting originally indexical LFs to representations of the meaning of an utterance which are context-independent at least as far as the episodic relations implicit in the tense-aspect structure are concerned. This includes the most common &amp;quot;orienting&amp;quot; relations between episodes, and some of the more subtle relations conveyed by perfective aspect.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="43"> Our Common Lisp implementation of the de-indexicalization process allows rules to be straightforwardly represented and easily edited; example sentences of the type in this paper (modulo simplification of some of the adverbials) run in roughly a tenth of a second on a Sun SPARCstation 1.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="44"> Future work will focus on extension of the rules so as to cover more types of adverbials (especially clausal ones), tenseless VPs and clauses (some of which we already handle, such as action nominalizations like &amp;quot;To have loved and lost is not unusual&amp;quot;), and relative clause. A preliminary look at some of these phenomena, especially clausal adverbials and relative clauses, suggests that an operation on pairs of trees may be required, something one might call a &amp;quot;two-point overlay&amp;quot; Ti:T2, where the root node of T1 and another node of T1 are aligned with two nodes of T2, creating orienting relationships between certain episodes stored at the aligned nodes. In any case, the potential of our approach has certainly not been exhausted. null</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

