<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="E85-1009">
<Title>An Evaluation of METAL: the LRC Machine Translation System</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="63" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
AbstraCt
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The Linguistics Research Center (LRC) at the University of Texas at Austin is currently developing METAL, a fully-automatlc high quality machine translation system, for market introduction in 1985. This paper will describe the current stat~s of METAL, e~phasizing the results of the most recent post-edltors' evaluation, and will briefly indicate some future directions for the system. A 6-page German original tex~ and a raw (unedIt~3d, but automatically reformatted) METAL translation of that text into English are included as appendices.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Introductlon The Linguistics Research Center (LRC) at the University of Texas at Austin is currently developing METAL, a fully-automatic high quality machine translation system, for market introduction in 1985. This paper wlll describe the curren~ statn/s o f METAL, including the results of the most recent evaluation, and will briefly indicate some fur%Ire directions for the system. Exhibits A and B (attached) are, respectively, a German original text and a raw (unedlted, but automatically reformatted) METAL translation of that into English.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> History and Status Machine translation research at the University of Texas began in 1956: the LRC was founded in 1961. Eor much o f the hi~cory of. this project, funding was provided by the U.S. Air Force's Rome Air Development Center and other U.S. gove~,m~nt agencies. In 1979, Siemens AG began funding the development phase of the METAL machine translation sy~cez, at which point i~lementatlon of the current system was initiated. A prototype has recently been delivered to the sponsor for market testing. The current system is a unidirectional German-English system, although work to add ot/%er target languages, as well as creating an English-German MT system, is now underway. The present staff for the METAL project consists of seven full-ti~e and five half-tlme personnel.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Application Environment Software has been developed to handle the formatting problems associated with technical manuals. This software, written in SNOBOL, automatically marks and prepares texts for the METAL translation system \[Slocum and Bennett, 1982; Slocum eu al. 0 1984\]. The only human intervention prior to translation is checking and correcting the results o f t_he automatic formatting routines. Postediting is expected for the output t~. The system does not expect (or provide for) human intervention during the actual translation phase.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Pre-processing and post-edlting are presantly done on a DEC-2060; the actual translation, on a Symbolics Lisp machine.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The &amp;quot;proch/ction ~&amp;quot; design envisions a Lisp Machine as the translation unit co, necked to 4-6 ~ranslator workstations, from which t,he prepared ~ will be sent to the translation unit and on which the output texts will be postedlted.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> METAL uses a transfer approach for translation. The entire process consists of four phases : analysis, integration, transfer, and generation (synthesis). The integration phase works with whole parse tree st-ruc~ures, following analysis and preceding transfer. Until recently, transfer and generation were essentially a single phase, but work is currently underway to separate this single phase into ~wo, with a much more powerful generation phase.</Paragraph>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="62" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
LlngulsKic Component
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The curren~ METAL lexicon consists of over 20,000 German and English monolingual entTies, cor~i~clng of morphological, syntactic, and s~ntlc features and values, and an appropriately large number of transfer entries. The featnlres and values in monollngual lexlcal entries supply necessary information for the analysis and/or synthesis of these it~m~ during the mach/x~ translation process. Most entries are reasonably s4~le, but entries for verb st~m~ are significantly more complex.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Inflected adjectives, nouns, and verbs are parsed by word-level gr~m-~r rules, with the stems and e~dlngs assigned to appropriate lexical categories.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  Each t-Fans fer lexical entry is a structure equating the source language canonical form with an appropriate target language canonical form. Certain significant information (i. e., lexical category, subject area, and preference) is coded in the entry to guide the system in selecting the appropriate translation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Furthermore, tests and operations (including transformations) may be included within transfer en~rles.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> The gr~r for METAL consists of over 600 augmented phrase s~ructure rules, each of which is used in both analysis and trans fer/generatlon. METAL' s gr~-~-r rules are used in the parsing of all levels of structure from the word level to the sentence level, including phrases and clauses. A METAL grammar rule consists of five analysis sections, plus an additional section for each target language: a top llne describing the phrase structure (with an optional enumeration of each constituent); a series of restrictions, which test the appropriateness of individual constituents on the right-hand side of the rule; TESTs, which enforce agreement among the right-hand constituents; a CONSTR section, which constructs the analysis of the phrase; an INTEC~ section, which is executed (once a complete analysis of the sentence is achieved) in order to, e.g., resolve anaphoric references; and one or more target-language-dependent Transfer sections, which control lexlcal and structn/ral translation into the target language.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Homograph resolution and dis~mhiguatlon are handled uniformly (i.e., without special passes) , in various ways : by orthographic tests, such as t_he test to ensure that a word that looks llke a German noun is not ali lower case; by positional constraints, which disallow co-occurrence of -mhlguous strings in the same clause location; and, most especial ly, by the case frame mechanism.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> The case (valency) frame mechanism is vital in METAL's analysis of German source language sentences. This mechanism is invoked in clause-level rules and uses features on the verb stem to define the functions of the various central ar~Jments to the predicate. In additlon, the case frame mechanism is used to test for such t/llngs as subject-verb agreement.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> The METAL gramm=ar makes extensive use of transformations to modify structure or perform certain tests. Transformations may be used in the TEST, CONSTR, INTEr, and Transfer phases of the rules, transformations may also be used in transfer lexlcal entries. A transformation may be written as part of a rule or called by name.</Paragraph>
</Section>
<Section position="2" start_page="62" end_page="63" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
Computational Component
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> The lexicon for METAL is maintained via a DBMS written in LISP. Input of lexical entries is facilitated by an INTERCODER, a menu-drlven system whlch asks the user for information in English and encodes the answers into the internal form used by the system. An integral part of the INTERCODER is the &amp;quot;lexical default&amp;quot; program which accepts&amp;quot; minlm~l information about the * particular entry (root form and lexical category) and encodes most of the remaining necessary features and values. Entries may also be created using any text editor, without the aid of the INTERC0DER or lexical defaulter.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Interfacing with the lexical database is done by means of a number of menu-driven functions which permlt the user to access, edit, copy, and/or delete entries individually, in groups (using specific features), or entirely. In order to assure a high degree of lexicon integrity the METAL system includes validation progr~m~ which identify errors in format and/or syntax.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> The validatlon process is automatically used to check lexlcal it~m~ which have been edited, to ensure that no errors have been introduced during editing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The grammar is also in a database and may be-accessed and/or edited in much the same way as the lexicon. System software and named trans formations are stored in individual source files.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> METAL's parser is a &amp;quot;some-paths, parallel, bottom-upparser&amp;quot; \[Slocum et al., 1984\] . It may be considered to be &amp;quot;some-paths&amp;quot; because the grammar rules are grouped into numerically indexed &amp;quot;levels&amp;quot; and the parser always applies rules at a lower level before applying rules at a higher level. Once the parser has successfully built one or more Ss at a given level, it will halt; until it discovers one or more S readings, the parser will continue to apply rules in each successive level.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Extensive experimentation with the system has found that the present parser configuration is the most efficient one for</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> In June, 1984, the METAL system was used to translate 82.6 pages of text into English; the material varied from a sales prospectus (for a speech recognition system) through various general hardware and software syste~ descriptions to highly technical documentation. The output was then edited by ~wo Siemens revisors (one a m~mher of the METAL project, one not) . This section describes the revisors ' obJective performance and subjective reactions (including comparison with earlier versions of METAL) during this experience.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> (N.B. The number of pages of text was computed automatically on the basis of &amp;quot;Siemens standard pages&amp;quot;: 26 lines x 55 characters = 1430 characters/pg.) The table above summarizes the editors' revision times. They employed rather dlfferent editing techniques (editor #i working in three passes, #2 in Just two), but their times are relatively close.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> Comments by Editor #i : ~he 3rd Pass\] tends to be concerned with sTylistic i~provements, formatting changes and t~2plng errors. The last part of this stage involves running the spelling checker on the file to eliminate remaining typing errors.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> The ~mpression of post-editing was that there have been many improvements over previous test runs. This was evidenced by the fact that on t/lls post-edlting run less than 57 o of sentences were re-translated from scratch. The major task in post-editing is now changing word order, changing verb agreement and re-translatlng the more idiomatic usages. Considerable l~rovemen~s in format made post-edlting easier, although there is still room for further enhancement.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> and 3rd phases of post-edltlng continued as normal. The previous problems wir/~ post-edlting a highly formatted text meant that whenever a textual change was made in the the te2Cc then the format had to be re-modi fled. The method o f post-editing u~ed in T-hls test proved to be considerably faster and easier to handle .... ~he results\] demonstrate that the time saving lles in the initial post-edlt phase which is when the most changes are made and which is most time intensive with regard to re- formatting text.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> Comments by Editor #2: As compared to the last run in February 1984, the June 84 output showed considerable i mprovement. A greater number o f sentences was useable and m~ny required a change in word order only. Placement o f the determiners has been improved. \[Certain\] points should be considered to Improve future translations.</Paragraph>
</Section>
<Section position="3" start_page="63" end_page="63" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
Future Directions
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> One of the greatest changes affecting post-edlting was the fact that since the initial output \[co~pared to earlier versions\] of METAL was deemed to have i &amp;quot;~r oved, the dl f fermi stages 0 f post-edlting were more clearly defined.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> That is to say, it was easier to produce an adequate translation during the first run through the tex~ ~- using the reformatted output on the screen and a hardcopy of the source text for reference -- than in previous tests. In the second run through a tex~c -- using a hardcopy of the METAL output upon which preliminary post-edlting has been performed -- it was easier to concentrate on polishing the translatlon. In the third and final post-edlt stage, one was able to make a final check for stylistic weaknesses, spelling mistakes and typing errors. This was the same method as used in previous tests but one was better able to distinguish beUween the stages (initial teckulical and stylistic post-edlting; polishing output; final stylistic check) and the entire process was less tiring than in the past.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Although the overall format of the output has i~3roved...there are still \[some\] problem areas \[with the automatic reformatting program\] .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> As an experlment, the unformatted, interlinear \[German-English\] version was used for the initial post-edlting phase.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> The text was then reformatted...and the 2nd The METAL German-Engllsh configuration was released for market testing in January 1985.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Current plans are to continue Imp~ rovement on the present system and to branch off into other target languages, specifically Spanish and Chinese. We estimate that a German-Spanish system should be ready for testing sometime in 1986, with a German-Chlnese system sometime thereafter.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> We have also begun working on an Engllsh-German system. If the planned work is success ful, work wll I begin on English-Spanish and English-Chinese MT syst~m~.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Section>
</Paper>

