<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="E85-1029">
<Title>Head Selection Feature Inheritance Conceptual Relation Prediction Triggering Thesaurus/PTABLE ._g~mn-tio Dependency Construction</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="200" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Kawasaki-city,213 JAPAN
ABSTRACT
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper describes some operational aspects of a language comprehension model which unifies the linguistic theory and the semantic theory in respect to operations. The computational model, called Augmented Dependency Grammar (ADG), formulates not only the linguistic dependency structure of sentences but also the semantic dependency structure using the extended deep case grammar and fleld-oriented fact-knowledge based inferences. Fact knowledge base and ADG model clarify the qualitative difference between what we call semantics and logical meaning. From a practrical view point, it provides clear image of syntactic/semantic computation for language processing in analysis and synthesis. It also explains the gap in semantics and logical meaning, and gives a clear computaional image of what we call conceptual analysis.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> This grammar is used for analysis of Japanese and synthesis of English, in the  constructs semantic dependency structure of Japanese input sentences by feature-oriented dependency grammar rules as main control information for syntactic analysis, and by semantic inference mechanism on a object fields' fact knowledge base. Legato maps syntactic dependency directly to meaningful logical dependency if possible, or maps it to language-particular semantic dependency if two kinds of dependencies do not coincide. The second component, Crescendo, extracts a conceptual structure about facts from the semantic dependency structure through logical interpretation on the language-particular semantic dependency using knowledge based inferences.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2">  A computational comprehension model for the ADG is given in Fig. 2. Three different kinds of information sources other than the lexicon support language comprehension, and two inference functions defined on them extract the interpretation of input sentences. The top level information is a language structure model. The bottom is a logical(factual/conceptual) interpretation model which determine the possible logical relations between &amp;quot;OBJECTs and THINGS&amp;quot;.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> The semantics located between the above two models, which has not been clarified in any paper. Suppose interpretalon is a process of determining the relation between &amp;quot; OBJECTs and THINGs &amp;quot;, the ordinary notion of semantics allows us to determine words' semantics in particular syntagmatic relations, but not relational interpretation between concepts.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  The semantics here is defined as information concerning the denotation of OBJECTs and THINGs. It interprets the (semantic) relations between them, and must be inducible from the raw syntagmatic information. That is to say, it may sometimes inherits such language particular features as syntactic structure, wording, culture. The structure representing semantics may not be interpretable in terms of pure logic, but may be represented linguistically.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> I) The ADG defines syntactic dependency structure, semantic dependency structure, and descriminates the semantic dependency from the logical structure.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 2) It functions as the interface between syntactic dependency and semantic dependency.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> The notion of basically binary &amp;quot;dependency&amp;quot; has a primary role to simplify the above interface, just in the sense that either syntactic or semantic inference recognizes interpretable binary relation. The semantics in the sense used here may not necessarily be shared among languages, while facts are shared among languages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> Legato built on the model is syntactic and semantic analysis module which construct directly semantic dependency structure from surface structure. Crescendo is an engine to eliminate non-logical part in semantic structure and induces logical structure with pragmatic information deduced from semantics.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> ~mantlo/Logical Interpretation Each word has its own meaning, sometimes plural meanings. In this paper word meaning is represented by a logical symbol called CONCEPT SYMBOL. The symbol is a representation primitive for fact knowledge base and internal conceptual representation of sentences.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> Semantic structure representation is also defined on them, but it borrows syntagmatic function called dummy symbols which never appear in conceptual representation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> The above examples ~I, SEN2 share the same meaning as shown in FACT1, except pragmatic and temporal information. Ordinary analysis of SENI produces subject-predicate-object syntagmatic information, and further case interpretaion of subject-predicate,object-predicate relations. However this kind of case interpretation brings into difficulties to select case marking ambiguities such as GOAl or RESult for the above object-predicate. SEN2 analysis produces instantly REAson interpretation between two nominals in terms of &amp;quot;REAson&amp;quot;-marking preposition &amp;quot;because-of&amp;quot;. This comparison supports the case even a verb must be interpreted in some case as a logical relation and clarifies the standpoint to specify the ADG. I. Factual(conceptual) information must be independent of syntagmatic meaning as well as independent of syntax.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> 2. Ordinary case marking strategy produces anomaly because it dare to interpret syntagmatic relations logically even if those are purely syntagmatic existence.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> 3. Fillmore's case is not suitable for conceptual representaion primitive for a variety of syntactic and syntagmatic structures.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> On the other hand, syntax is a clue to understanding of sentences. Syntagmatic relations, in most cases, can be interpretable as in FACTI for SEN2, and linguistic information is a sole trigger for human to recognize new notion or new word meaning in a sentence.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15">  SENt War resulted in disaster.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16">  information is defined by two different levels understanding; I LEGATO semantic analysis (as shown in S~I, FACTI for SENI,2 respectively) with direct correspondence to syntagmatic relation, and 2. CRESCENDO factual (logical) understanding as in a extraction process of FACTI from SENt via S~I.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="17"> The symbols; RF.J~onl,2 as in S\]~1, are called dummy relations in the sense that REAson1(2) has no logical significance because REAson1(2) holds in any combination of REAson and other concept, while REAson in FACTI holds in the special combination of concepts like WAR with DISASTAR. They play a role to match syntagmatic relation with semantics in terms of syntax. These two processes analize the pragmatic, modal, and temporal information which is added into the factual structure to produce the conceptual structure.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="18"> &amp;quot;Dependency&amp;quot; is 2nd idea, to figure out that semantic (dependency) analysis of sentences is executable at the same time of syntactic (dependency) analysis. ADG employs dependency framework in a different way from the ordinary one. It deals with prepositions, postpositions, case inflections, grsmmstical functions, copula etc., as the functional features for relational interpretation. For example, preposition in English may not be a syntactic governor ('head' in this paper) of its object phrase, copula &amp;quot;be&amp;quot; in front of adjective modifies the syntactic feature of the adjective as a syntagmatic head predicate which allows it to have a dependent marked as a subject, while adjective in itself has a function of pre-nominal modifier. Namely, most of the functional words are dealt like case inflections. They add functional features to words or modify their features.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="19"> The functional features map word-to-word dependency to concept-to-concept semantic dependency. The figure 3 explains the simple interface mechanism. Functional features such as SUBject, OBJect, BECAUSE-OF corresponds to REAsonl, RF_~son2, REAson respectively. The ADG syntactic dependency rules(see *s below) predict those semantic relations using the functional features and word syntax, and at the same time they trigger fact knowledge base inference to interpret Concept-to-Concept relations. A fact(concept) knowledge base is composed of such binary pieces as Ss or Cs. In this figure S and C mean semantic knowledge dependent on languages, and conceptual knowledge respectively.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="20">  definition DI. FEATURE describes morphological, syntactic, semantic, and conceptual information , and is used for describing the lexicon, semantic structure, conceptual structure and ADG rules. Feature is formalized as : Feature ~ . ~Feature Value} .{ Context} Dependency function, one of the syntactic features for a particle , is described as follows.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="21"> LD.LNULL ) .~A~ LH. {NULL1. tA I no word on the left depends on a particle, it depends on no word on the left RD. INOM I. A RH. INULLI. A it depends on NOMinal on the right etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="22"> D2. CONCEPTUAL SYMBOL(C3) is a large set of intensional symbols standing for meanings conveyed by words. CONCEPTUAL SYMBOL includes those symbols such as NOTION, COMPUTER, GIVE, COLOR, BEAUTIFUL, SUP-SUB, PARTOF, AGT and so on. CS is one of the features included in FEATURE.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="23"> D3. THESAURUS is a system defined as a  relation, and dummy relations such as REAsonl, REAson2, LOCI, etc. CONCEPTUAL RELATION is a subset of CONCEPTUAL SYMBOL: AGT relation , OBJ relation . POSSess relation, LOC relation and the other 41 relations.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="24"> Relations are directed binary relations including logical ones such as REAson, CAUSAL, PARTOF, SUP-SUB, etc. and deep case relations such as AGT, OBJ, LOC, etc., and several language dependent dummy relations such as LOCI, LOC2 ,CNTI, REAsonl etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="25"> The THESAURUS and the FTABLE, which is described interms of semantic dependency and conceptual information, compose the fact knowledge base. The former forms directed network called an abstraction hierarchy for concept generalization.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

