<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="P85-1003">
<Title>EIR.S E,R.S S,R.E S, RoE S~R.E S~RoE PAST PERFECT E~SoR SIMPLE PAST E.SoR PRESENT PERFECT EoS,R SIMPLE PRESENT E.S,R SIMPLE PRESENT SIEoR SIMPLE FUTURE SoE. R S, EmR S.E.R RoSoE Ro$.E R~E~S R~E,S</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
545 Technology Square
CamOridge, MA 02139.
ABSTRACT
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper explores the relationshiDs between a computational meory of temporal representation (as developed by James Alien) and a Iormal linguiStiC theory Of tense (as developed by NorOert Hornstem) and aspect. It aims tO prowde exphcit answers to four lundamental Questions: (1) what ts the computational lustd~cat=on for me or=mmves of a hngu=stIc theory; (2) what ~s the computational explanation of the formal grammatical constraints; (3) what are the processing constraints ~ml3osed on the learnabdity and marKedness of these theoretical construCtS: and (4) what are the constramnts that a hnguist=c theory imposes or. representatC/ons. We show that one can effectively exploit (n~ ,nterface between the language faculty and the cognmve faculties by using hngu=stic constra,nts tO determine restrtcuons on tile cognitive representations and wce versa.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Three mare results are cbtalned: (1) We derive an explanation of an oOserved grammabcal constrmnt on tense .. the Linear Order Constraint -- from the reformation monotonicity property of the constraint propagation algorithm of Allen's temPoral system: (2) We formulate a principle of mart~edness for the 13as=c tense structures Ioased on the computational efficiency of the temporal representations: and (3) We snow Allen's interval-Oased temporal System =s not arbitrary, bul it can be used to exolair, ;nctependently motwated lingulst~c constraints on tense and aspect interpretatmns.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> We also claim that the methodology of research developed in tins study -- &amp;quot;cross-lever' investigation of independently motivated formal grammatical theory and computational moclets -. is a C/owerful paradigm with which to attack representational problems =n oaslc cognitive domains, e.g.. space, t~me, c~u:~ality, etc.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

