<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W02-1705">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Ampornaramveth V., Aizawa A. &amp; Oyama K. (2000) An Internet-based Collaborative Dictionary Development Project: SAIKAM. Proc. of 7th Intl. Workshop on Academic Information Networks and Systems (WAINS'7), Bangkok, 7--8 December 2000, Kasetsart University.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 2 Blanc ., Srasset G. &amp; Tchou F. (1994) Designing an Acception-Based Multilingual Lexical Data Base under HyperCard: PARAX Research Report, GETA, IMAG (UJF &amp; CNRS), Aug. 1994, 10 p.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 3 Connolly, Dan (1997) XML Principles, Tools and Techniques World Wide Web Journal, Volume 2, Issue 4, Fall 1997, O'REILLY &amp; Associates, 250 p.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 4 Nancy M. Ide , Jean Veronis, Text Encoding Initiative: Background and Contexts, Kluwer Academic Publishers, Norwell, MA, 1995 5 Mangeot-Lerebours M. (2000) Papillon Lexical Database Project: Monolingual Dictionaries &amp; Interlingual Links. Proc. of 7th Workshop on Advanced Information Network and System Pacific Association for Computational Linguistics 1997 Conference (WAINS'7), Bangkok, Thailande, 7--8 dcembre 2000, Kasetsart University, 6 p. 6 Mangeot-Lerebours M. (2001) Environnements centraliss et distribus pour lexicographes et lexicologues en contexte multilingue. Nouvelle thse, Universit Joseph Fourier (Grenoble I), 27 September 2001, 280 p.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 7 Mel'tchuk I., Clas A. &amp; Polgure A. (1995) Introduction la lexicologie explicative et combinatoire. AUPELF-UREF/Duculot, Louvain-la-Neuve, 256 p.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 8 Polgure, A. (2000) Towards a theoretically-motivated general public dictionary of semantic derivations and collocations for French. Proc. EURALEX'2000, Stuttgart, pp 517--527.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 9 Gilles Srasset, Interlingual lexical organisation for multilingual lexical databases in NADIA, Proceedings of the 15th conference on Computational linguistics, August 05-09, 1994, Kyoto, Japan 10 Srasset G. (1994b) SUBLIM, un systme universel de bases lexicales multilingues; et NADIA, sa spcialisation aux bases lexicales interlingues par acceptions. Nouvelle thse, UJF (Grenoble 1), dc. 1994.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 11 Srasset G. (1997) Le projet NADIA-DEC: vers un dictionnaire explicatif et combinatoire informatis? Proc. of La mmoire des mots, 5me journes scientifiques du rseau LTT, Tunis, 25--27 septembre 1997, AUPELFUREF, 7 p.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> 12 Sasset G. &amp; Mangeot-Lerebours M. (2001) Papillon Lexical Database Project: Monolingual Dictionaries &amp; Interlingual Links. Proc. NLPRS'2001, Hitotsubashi Memorial Hall, National Center of Sciences, Tokyo, Japan, 27--30 November 2001, vol 1/1, pp. 119--125. 13 Tomokiyo M., Mangeot-Lerebours M. &amp; Planas E. (2000) Papillon: a Project of Lexical Database for English, French and Japanese, using Interlingual Links. Proc. of Journes des Sciences et Techniques de l'Ambassade de France au Japon, Tokyo, Japon, 13--14 novembre 2000, Ambassade de France au Japon, 3 p.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

