<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W02-0222">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Petra Barg , Markus Walther, Processing unknown words in HPSG, Proceedings of the 36th annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, August 10-14, 1998, Montreal, Quebec, Canada 2 Lou Burnard. 2000. Reference Guide for the British National Corpus (World Edition). Oxford University Computing Services.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 3 David Carter. 1992. Lexical acquisition. In H. Alshawi, editor, The Core Language Engine, pages 217--234. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 4 Ann Copestake, Dan Flickinger, Ivan Sag, and Carl Pollard. 1999. Minimal recursion semantics: An introduction. Draft.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 5 Gregor Erbach. 1990. Syntactic processing of unknown words. In P. Jorrand and V. Sgurev, editors, Artificial Intelligence IV - methodology, systems, applications. North-Holland, Amsterdam. 6 Simon Garrod and Martin Pickering. 2001. Toward a mechanistic psychology of dialogue: The interactive alignment model. In P. Khnlein, H. Rieser, and H. Zeevat, editors, Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on Formal Semantics and Pragmatics of Dialogue. BI-DIALOG. 7 Jonathan Ginzburg , Robin Cooper, Resolving ellipsis in clarification, Proceedings of the 39th Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.236-243, July 06-11, 2001, Toulouse, France 8 Jonathan Ginzburg and Robin Cooper. forthcoming. Clarification, ellipsis and utterance representation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 9 Jonathan Ginzburg, Howard Gregory, and Shalom Lappin. 2001a. SHARDS: Fragment resolution in dialogue. In H. Bunt, I. van der Sluis, and E. Thijsse, editors, Proceedings of the Fourth International Workshop on Computational Semantics (IWCS-4), pages 156--172. ITK, Tilburg University, Tilburg. 10 Jonathan Ginzburg, Ivan A. Sag, and Matthew Purver. 2001b. Integrating conversational move types in the grammar of conversation. In P. Khnlein, H. Rieser, and H. Zeevat, editors, Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on Formal Semantics and Pragmatics of Dialogue (BI-DIALOG 2001), pages 45--56. 11 Richard H. Granger. 1977. FOUL-UP: A program that figures out meanings of words from context. In Proceedings of the 5th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-77), volume 1, pages 172--178, August. 12 Howard Gregory. 2001. A ProFIT grammar and resolution procedure for fragments in dialogue. Technical Report TR-01-03, Department of Computer Science, King's College London, May.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 13 Peter Mark Hastings, Automatic acquisition of word meaning from context, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, 1994 14 Kevin Knight. 1996. Learning word meanings by instruction. In Proceedings of the Thirteenth National Conference on Artifical Intelligence, pages 447--454. AAAI/IAAI.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 15 Ted Pedersen. 1995. Automatic acquisition of noun and verb meanings. Technical Report 95-CSE-10, Southern Methodist University, June.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 16 Matthew Purver. 2001. SCoRE: A tool for searching the BNC. Technical Report TR-01-07, Department of Computer Science, King's College London, October.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> 17 James Pustejovsky. 1998. The semantics of lexical underspecification. Folia Linguistica, 32(3--4):323--347.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> 18 Adwait Ratnaparkhi. 1996. A maximum entropy part-of-speech tagger. In Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing Conference. University of Pennsylvania, May.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> 19 Dale W. Russell, Language acquisition in a unification-based grammar processing system using a real-world knowledge base, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Champaign, IL, 1993 20 Cynthia Ann Thompson , Raymond Joseph Mooney, Semantic lexicon acquisition for learning natural language interfaces, 1998 21 David Traum, Johan Bos, Robin Cooper, Staffan Larsson, Ian Lewin, Colin Matheson, and Massimo Poesio. 1999. A model of dialogue moves and information state revision. In Task Oriented Instructional Dialogue (TRINDI): Deliverable 2.1. University of Gothenburg. 22 Kees van Deemter. 1996. Towards a logic of ambiguous expressions. In K. van Deemter and S. Peters, editors, Semantic Ambiguity and Underspecification, number 55 in CSLI Lecture Notes. CSLI Publications. 23 Uri Zernik. 1987. Language acquisition: Learning a hierarchy of phrases. In Proceedings of the 10th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-87), volume 1, pages 125--132, August.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

