<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W02-1406">
<Title>Probabilistic named entity verification</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Named entity (NE) recognition is an important task for many natural language applications, such as Internet search engines, document indexing, information extraction and machine translation. Moreover, in oriental languages (such as Chinese, Japanese and Korean), NE recognition is even more important because it significantly affects the performance of word segmentation, the most fundamental task for understanding the texts in oriental languages. In this paper, a probabilistic verification model is designed for verifying the correctness of a named entity candidate. This model assesses the confidence level of a candidate not only according to the candidate's structure but also according to its context. In our design, the clues for confidence measurement are collected from both positive and negative examples in the training data in a statistical manner. Experimental results show that the proposed method significantly improves the F-measure of Chinese personal name recognition from 86.5% to 94.4%.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Introduction Named entity (NE) recognition (or proper name recognition) is a task to find the entities of person, location, organization, date, time, percentage and monetary value in text documents. It is an important task for many natural language applications, such as Internet search engines, document indexing, information extraction and machine translation. Moreover, in oriental languages (such as Chinese, Japanese and Korean), NE recognition is even more important because it significantly affects the performance of word segmentation, the most fundamental task for understanding the texts in oriental languages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Therefore, a high-accuracy NE recognition method is highly demanded for most natural language applications in various languages.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> There are two major approaches to NE recognition: the handcrafted approach (Grishman, 1995) and the statistical approach (Bikel, 1997; Chen, 1998; Yu, 1998). In the first approach, a system usually relies on a large number of handcrafted rules. This kind of systems can be rapid prototyped but are hard to scale up. In fact, there will be numerous exceptions for most handcrafted rules. It is generally expensive and impossible to code for every exception we can imagine, not to mention those exceptions we are not able to think of. Another serious problem with the handcrafted approach is that systems are hard to be ported across different domains and different languages. Porting a handcrafted system usually means rewriting all its rules.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Therefore, the statistical approach is becoming more and more popular because of its cost-effectiveness in scaling up and porting systems. In general, the statistical approach to NE recognition can be viewed as a two-stage process. First, according to dictionaries and/or pattern matching rules, the input text is tokenized into tokens. Each token may be a word or an NE candidate which can consist of more than one word. Then, the most likely token sequence is selected according to a statistical model, such as Markov model (Bikel, 1997; Yu, 1998) or maximum entropy model (Borthwick, 1999).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Although, the statistical NE recognition is much more scalable and portable, its performance is still not satisfactory. The insufficient coverage/precision of pattern matching rules and unknown words are the major sources of errors.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Furthermore, the role of the statistical model is to assess the relative possibilities of all possible token sequences and select the most probable one. The scores obtained from the statistical model can be used for a comparison of competing token sequences, but not for an assessment of the probability that a spotted named entity is correct.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> To reduce the recognition errors, we propose a probabilistic verification model to verify the correctness of a named entity. This model assesses the confidence level of a named entity candidate not only according to the candidate's structure but also according to its contexts. In our design, the clues for confidence measurement are collected from both positive and negative examples in the training data. Therefore, the confidence measure has strong discriminant power for judging the correctness of a named entity. In the experiments of Chinese personal name recognition, the proposed verification model increases the F-measure from 86.5% to 94.4%, which corresponds to 58.5% error reduction rate, where &amp;quot;error rate&amp;quot; is defined as &amp;quot;100% F-measure[?] &amp;quot;.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

