<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W02-1027">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 1 Ted Briscoe , Ann Copestake, Lexical rules in constraint-based grammars, Computational Linguistics, v.25 n.4, p.487-526, December 1999 2 Jean Carletta, Assessing agreement on classification tasks: the kappa statistic, Computational Linguistics, v.22 n.2, June 1996 3 M. Collins and Y. Singer. 1999. Unsupervised models for named entity classification. In Proc. of the 1999 Joint SIGDAT Conference, College Park, MD, pages 100--110. 4 Ann Copestake and Ted Briscoe. 1995. Semi-productive polysemy and sense extension. Journal of Semantics, 12:15--67.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 5 Steffan Corley, Martin Corley, Frank Keller, Matthew Crocker, and Shari Trewin. 2001. Finding syntactic structure in unparsed corpora: The Gsearch corpus query system. Computers and the Humanities, 35(2):81--94. 6 Ted Dunning, Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence, Computational Linguistics, v.19 n.1, March 1993 7 Dan Fass. 1997. Processing Metaphor and Metonymy. Ablex, Stanford, CA.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 8 Christiane Fellbaum, editor. 1998. WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database. MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 9 William Gale, Kenneth Church, and David Yarowsky. 1993. A method for disambiguating word senses in a large corpus. Computers and the Humanities, 26:415--439. 10 Sanda Harabagiu. 1998. Deriving metonymic coercions from WordNet. In Workshop of the Usage of WordNet in Natural Language Processing-Systems, COLING-ACL'98, pages 142--148, Montreal, Canada. 11 Jerry R. Hobbs , Mark E. Stickel , Douglas E. Appelt , Paul Martin, Interpretation as abduction, Artificial Intelligence, v.63 n.1-2, p.69-142, Oct. 1993 12 Shin-ichiro Kamei , Takahiro Wakao, Metonymy: reassessment, survey of acceptability, and its treatment in a machine translation system, Proceedings of the 30th annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, June 28-July 02, 1992, Newark, Delaware 13 Klaus Krippendorff. 1980. Content Analysis: An Introduction to Its Methodology. Sage Publications.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> 14 George Lakoff and Mark Johnson. 1980. Metaphors We Live By. Chicago University Press, Chicago, Ill.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> 15 Maria Lapata, A corpus-based account of regular polysemy: the case of context-sensitive adjectives, Second meeting of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics on Language technologies 2001, p.1-8, June 01-07, 2001, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 16 Understanding metonymies in discourse, Artificial Intelligence, v.135 n.1-2, p.145-198, 02/01/2002 17 Katja Markert and Malvina Nissim. 2002. Towards a corpus annotated for metonymies: the case of location names. In Proc. of the 3rd International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation; Las Palmas, Canary Islands, 2002. 18 David Martinez , Eneko Agirre, One sense per collocation and genre/topic variations, Proceedings of the 2000 Joint SIGDAT conference on Empirical methods in natural language processing and very large corpora: held in conjunction with the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, p.207-215, October 07-08, 2000, Hong Kong 19 Hwee Tou Ng , Hian Beng Lee, Integrating multiple knowledge sources to disambiguate word sense: an exemplar-based approach, Proceedings of the 34th annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.40-47, June 24-27, 1996, Santa Cruz, California 20 Geoffrey Nunberg. 1978. The Pragmatics of Reference. Ph.D. thesis, City University of New York, New York.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> 21 Ted Pedersen, A simple approach to building ensembles of Naive Bayesian classifiers for word sense disambiguation, Proceedings of the first conference on North American chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, p.63-69, April 29-May 04, 2000, Seattle, Washington 22 Ted Pedersen, A decision tree of bigrams is an accurate predictor of word sense, Second meeting of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics on Language technologies 2001, p.1-8, June 01-07, 2001, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 23 James Pustejovsky. 1995. The Generative Lexicon. MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> 24 David Stallard, Two kinds of metonymy, Proceedings of the 31st annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.87-94, June 22-26, 1993, Columbus, Ohio 25 Gustav Stern. 1931. Meaning and Change of Meaning. Gteborg: Wettergren &amp; Kerbers Frlag.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> 26 Cornelia Verspoor. 1996. Lexical limits on the influence of context. In Proc. of the 18th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society; La Jolla, Cal., 12--15 July 1996, pages 116--120. 27 Cornelia Verspoor. 1997. Conventionality-governed logical metonymy. In H. Bunt, L. Kievit, R. Muskens, and N. Verlinden, editors, Proc. of the 2nd International Workshop on Computational Semantics, pages 300--312, Tilburg, The Netherlands. 28 David Yarowsky, Unsupervised word sense disambiguation rivaling supervised methods, Proceedings of the 33rd annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.189-196, June 26-30, 1995, Cambridge, Massachusetts 29 David Yarowsky. 1997. Homograph disambiguation in speech synthesis. In R. Sproat, J. Olive, and J. Hirschberg, editors, Progress in Speech Synthesis, pages 159--175. Springer-Verlag.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

