<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="W02-1404">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
References
1 Lars Borin, You'll take the high road and I'll take the low road: using a third language to improve bilingual word alignment, Proceedings of the 18th conference on Computational linguistics, p.97-103, July 31-August 04, 2000, Saarbrcken, Germany
2 Pascale Fung, A Statistical View on Bilingual Lexicon Extraction: From Parallel Corpora to Non-parallel Corpora, Proceedings of the Third Conference of the Association for Machine Translation in the Americas on Machine Translation and the Information Soup, p.1-17, October 28-31, 1998
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> 3 William A. Gale , Kenneth W. Church, A program for aligning sentences in bilingual corpora, Proceedings of the 29th annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.177-184, June 18-21, 1991, Berkeley, California 4 Jin-Xia Huang , Key-Sun Choi, Chinese-Korean word alignment based on linguistic comparison, Proceedings of the 38th Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.392-399, October 03-06, 2000, Hong Kong 5 Martin Kay , Martin Rscheisen, Text-translation alignment, Computational Linguistics, v.19 n.1, March 1993 6 S. J. Ker and J. S. Chang. 1997. Aligning more words with high precision for small bilingual corpora. Computational Linguistics and Chinese Language Processing, 2(2):63--96.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> 7 O. Y. Kwong and B. K. Tsou. 2001. Automatic corpus-based extraction of Chinese legal terms. In Proceedings of the 6th Natural Language Processing Pacific Rim Symposium (NLPRS 2001), pages 669--676, Tokyo, Japan. 8 O. Y. Kwong. 2002. Toward a bilingual legal term glossary from context profiles. In Proceedings of the 16th Pacific Asia Conference on Language, Information and Computation (PACLIC 16), pages 249--258, Jeju, Korea. 9 Gideon S. Mann , David Yarowsky, Multipath translation lexicon induction via bridge languages, Second meeting of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics on Language technologies 2001, p.1-8, June 01-07, 2001, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 10 I. Dan Melamed, A word-to-word model of translational equivalence, Proceedings of the eighth conference on European chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, p.490-497, July 07-12, 1997, Madrid, Spain 11 S. Piperidis, S. Boutsis, and I. Demiros. 1997. Automatic translation lexicon generation from multilingual texts. In Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on Multilinguality in Software Industry: The AI Contribution (MULSAIC'97), Nagoya, Japan. 12 M. F. Porter. 1980. An algorithm for suffix stripping. Program, 14(3):130--137, July.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 13 Philip Resnik , I. Dan Melamed, Semi-automatic acquisition of domain-specific translation lexicons, Proceedings of the fifth conference on Applied natural language processing, p.340-347, March 31-April 03, 1997, Washington, DC 14 M. Simard, G. F. Foster, and P. Isabelle. 1992. Using cognates to align sentences in bilingual corpora. In Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Theoretical and Methodological Issues in Machine Translation (TMI-92), pages 67--81. 15 Frank Smadja , Kathleen R. McKeown , Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou, Translating collocations for bilingual lexicons: a statistical approach, Computational Linguistics, v.22 n.1, p.1-38, March 1996 16 D. Wu and X. Xia. 1995. Large-scale automatic extraction of an English-Chinese translation lexicon. Machine Translation, 9(3--4):285--313.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 17 Dekai Wu, Aligning a parallel English-Chinese corpus statistically with lexical criteria, Proceedings of the 32nd annual meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p.80-87, June 27-30, 1994, Las Cruces, New Mexico</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

