<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C96-1015">
<Title>Monotonic Paradigmatic Schemata in Italian Verb Inflection(*)</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="77" end_page="78" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
&amp;quot;I'I')NI,)I~I? V ~N { I{H
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> presupl)osition relation l:m.radigms also exhibit systematic interlexemic redundancies in stem selection (Pirrelli and Federici tg.q/I). '\['li',NE\]Zl.E and VENH{.I!3 ('come'), in spite of I:heir 1)elonging to difDrent eon~iugationa.\] classes (resl)~,ctively second and third), exhibit an identical I)attern of stem alternation, as illustrated in the Imradigmarie sclw.ma of grid ?1 below, where sanlencss of index expresses sa.meness of stem form a.tion: The grid is also a.pplicable to the present indicative of I)OLEIU'; ('hurt') given above, independently of |;Ire substantial variatio|l in phonological content between the stems of 1)OLEI-{E and those of VF, NIIU); and TEN\]);I{I)'. When things are o1&gt; served el. the proposed level of a.l)stra.etion, surprisingly f(~w paradigmatic schcJnata, unspecified for phonological eontent and eolllbillcd with appropriate conjugational classes of endings, suffice to generalize ()vet: the entire II;a.lia.n conjugation system (Spencer 1988, Pirrelli l.q.q3).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> There exists a direct relationship between the number of st;am a.lternants of a verb and the paradigmatic schema tire verb con%tins to. Under the assuml~tion that three stem alternants rl. r2 and &amp;quot;r3 are used for present indieative, they most often distribute according to grid I al)ove. Similarly, the present indieatiw', of' a two-stem verb rarely departs from grid 2.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> There is a noneml/ty int, ersee~io|~ between schemata I and 2 (grid :3): a cet't.a.in amount tin l,hc paradigm of Cofllim'C/ |.he st;era alt.e,.rnang cogl- is tin'ned into cogli- in l;hc t.hirdq)c,'son singu Ira&amp;quot; and second-person plural of tim /)rese.nl; indicative by some sepm'atc readjustment, l'tll(!S.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> of combine|eric redundancy carries over fl'ont a three-stem paradignl to a two-stem paradigm, hi particular, i) the same stem shows up in the first-person singular and third-person plural, ii) r/has the same distribution in the two schemata, iii) 'rl occupies the slots left empty by the missing third stem alternant, so that I, he constraint that stem atterna.nts in eells 2s and 3s are assigned 1,he same index is not violated. A quick look a.t the.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> lmra.digm of completely regular verbs (i.e. w'xbs with no stem alternation) confirms this trend: r2 disappears, but its slots are taken over by rl. \[n a nutshell, rl is the default surface stem alternant ~md normally occupies slots which are left empty by nonexisting Mternants.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> The descriptive economy obta.ined by describing infleetional paradigms through paradigmatic schemata, is considerable. I)ue to tim distributional overlapping between three-stem paradigms and paradigms with fewer altenmnts, a. single schema, specified for the ma.xim||m number of possibile stern all, ernants, su\[fi(:es to aee.ount for \[,he distribution of an entire class of verb alternants, when the following simplitied General Indexing Convention ((HC) is resorted to: a) assign thc d@ult index rl to the ste'm, occurring in the (:ell of the second-person plural of present indicatiw',; b) assign r2 to the stem of the first-person singular of present indlcatiw~; c) assign r3 to the stem of the second-person singular of present indicative.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> In the following section we will detail a straightfbrward monotonic formalization of a), b) and c) in a typed l&gt;ature-structure formalism. Sulli&lt;:e it to say now that GIC makes reference to dislh'ilint|ohM properties only, specified in terms of the number of stem alterna.nts that a lexeme exhibits.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> No mention is made either of tile alteration Which the stem undergoes or of the form or' the eorrc spending infleetiomd ending. This is grounded on the Indexing Autonomy Hypothesis (IAtl), a.ccording to which &amp;quot;stem pairs exhibiting an identical contrast in formation needn't exhibit an iclentical contrast in indexing&amp;quot; (Stump 1995). At first glance, the parallel distributional and Ibrma.l behaviour of stem altermmts in the present indica.live of Tli;NERE and VENIRE seems to falsify IAII. Other evidence, however, shows that IAH is indeed descriptively adequate. Consider, \['or concreteness, the alternation itTl stem pairs s||ch as croeifigg-etc ('you crucify')/ e'rocifiss-i ('\[ crucified'), infliog-ete ('you inflict')/ i,gliss-i ('\[ lull|clod'). In spite of' their similarity in stem f'o&gt; mat|on, matched by paxtial distributional re&amp;mdancies, any direct correlation between phonolog- null ica.l alltl dist.t'ibut.ioual ,'eg,tlarii.i&lt;'s w+.Jhl load I.o in(:orv(':cl. Imra.(ligi+ta.l.h ' st.al.(qne~l.s, as slv.)wn I&gt;3: the c&lt;ml.rasl, b(C/w(~(m l.h,e past. l)arl+icil)Ic .?'o+iji,~;.~,') ('(:r,|cili(&gt;d') a,+l t,h+&gt; past./)at't.icil&gt;l+' m./l+ll-o ('in Ilict,ed') wh(~re yet. a..m:&gt;l;h(~r st.(~t +tlt.erl~ant. :-.h()ws Ul). Nol.e l+lutt. IAII ,.loes uof cxclu&lt;h' t;h(' l~{+ssil&gt;ilit.y t.hal; ;~+. ,+lirec\[. cot:r,'daLi,.)u l&gt;+&gt;l,w+&gt;+'t~ l'~+rt~ att~l iH,::I(~x ing can I;e sl, il)l,tla,t,+&gt;d C()IIVCII'iCqII, I3'. A iiiOl'C higllly valu(&gt;d lexic+)u, M~ottld ;l..l+'+:o I&gt;,:' ald+' t~&gt; cai&gt;l,tlre fit+: st. rJl,:iug sil&lt;tila.ril.y b&lt;&gt;l:,v,:&gt;(&gt;u th(&gt; l)l'eSe~tl, ilMicat.i',:e o1' I&gt;ot, h 'FEN I&amp;quot;,I~,I&amp;quot;, and \:I,',NI I~1'+ sl,owH above, \'Ve will consider t.his I)ossil&gt;ilit.y it~ t.he lit+al t&gt;art, of I, he Pa, i)e\]'+</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

