<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J96-1004">
<Title>From Conceptual Time to Linguistic Time</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="92" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> In speaker-generated texts, reference is made to facts taking place in time. To use the same kind of references in automatically generated text, the mechanisms that govern the expression of temporal concepts must be identified. There is no simple or direct mapping between conceptual time, as it is perceived in the real world, and linguistic time, which refers to the way time is formulated in language. There may be different ways to present the same temporal concept in a text, and a single linguistic marker can be used to convey different temporal meanings.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> For example, the discourse below (Discourse 1) is a text generated by Pr4texte, a system we developed for implementing the expression of temporal localization in French texts 1. It is a slightly modified version of an example used by Bras (1990) for the extraction of temporal information in text analysis. The sentences report occurrences that are facts taking place in time. We have inserted labels in parentheses to distinguish the twelve occurrences reported in the text.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Hier l'avion a effectu6 un vol (ol). A 8h00 il a quitt6 Paris (02). Quand il a survol6 Barcelone (o3), le r6acteur fonctionnait (o4).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> ~, 10h15, un voyant a clignot6 (o5). Auparavant, il s'6tait allure6 (o6). Puis il s'6tait 6teint (o7). Pendant 35 minutes, l'avion a survol6 lamer (o8). Puis il a atteint la c6te (o9). Jusqu'a 10h50, il a survol6 l'Alg6rie (o10). A llh30 il 6tait sur la piste (o11). A ce moment-la le r6acteur a explos6 (o12).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Yesterday the plane made a flight (ol). At 8:00 A.M. it left Paris (o2). When it flew over Barcelona (o3), the engine was working (o4). At 10:15, a warning light flashed (o5). Previously it had come on (o6). Then it had gone out (o7). For 35 minutes the plane flew over the sea (o8). Then it reached the coast (o9). Until 10:50 it flew over Algeria (olo). At 11:30 it was on the landing runway (o11). At this moment the engine exploded (o12).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Discourse 1 * 3535 Queen-Mary, Bur. 420, Montr6al (Quebec), Canada H3V 1H8, Tel: (514) 733-3959. E-maih gagnon@iro.umontreal.ca. This article was written while the author was at &amp;quot;Laboratoire Langue, Raisonnement et Calcul&amp;quot; of IRIT, Toulouse, France. J- D6partement cl'informatique et de recherche op6rationnelle, C. P. 6128, Succ. Centre-Ville, Montr6al (Qu6bec), Canada H3C 3J7. E-mail: lapalme@iro.umontreal.ca. 1 The French text shown on the left in Discourse 1 was generated by Pr6texte; we give an English translation on the right.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> @ 1996 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 22, Number 1 In Discourse 1, we find two types of temporal markers: verb tense and what we call adverbials of temporal location (ATL). An ATL is an adjunct, such as yesterday, until 10:50, or when it flew over Barcelona, that provides information about the temporal localization of an occurrence or its duration, or both at the same time. For verb tense, we distinguish different ways of indicating localization in the past. Three French verb tenses can be used: pass~ composG imparfait, and plus-que-parfait; their closest equivalents in English are the simple past, past progressive, and past perfect. The passf compos~ il a survold 'it flew over' presents the occurrence as an event and localizes it in relation to the time of speech. With the plus-que-parfait il s'dtait allum~ 'it had come on', the occurrence is also presented as an event, but localized in relation to a perspective point other than speech time. The imparfait le r~acteur fonctionnait 'the engine was working' presents the occurrence as being in progress. For present and future tenses there are fewer options than for past tense, but more than one form is available for theses tenses as well.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> For ATLs, temporal localization can be achieved in many ways; for example, in relation to the time of speech (hier 'yesterday'), by designating an absolute temporal location (~ 8hO0 'at 8:00 A.M.'), or in relation to another fact (puis 'then', ~ ce moment-ld 'at this moment', quand il a survold Barcelone 'when it flew over Barcelona'). To this variety in the semantics of localization we must add the variety of syntactic forms. Localization can be expressed by an adverb (puis 'then'), a prepositional phrase (jusqu'd 10h50 'until 10:50'), a nominal phrase (le lendemain 'the day after') or a subordinate clause (quand il a survold Barcelone 'when it flew over Barcelona').</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> No text generator has yet been developed to solve the problem of the expression of time. The ones that have tackled this problem have focused on the production of verb tenses, without solving the choice of temporal adverbs. The work presented in this paper addresses the problem of generating the elements that convey temporal localization in French, including both verbs and temporal adverbs.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> In a previous paper (Gagnon and Lapalme 1992), we proposed a method of integrating the expression of temporal concepts into the text-generation process. In particular, we showed how to produce different types of text in French from a single representation of events. Unfortunately, the method governing the planning process was too determined by temporal concepts, so it was difficult to link this planning process with other frameworks, such as the schema proposed by McKeown (1985) or Rhetorical Structure Theory (RST) (Mann 1991; Hovy 1991).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> As we were not really successful in integrating the expression of time in French into the text-generation process, we decided to pursue our research with a different perspective. We designed a system covering many of the possibilities of expressing time in French, our hypothesis being that the achievement of this task would facilitate the design of a text-planning process. We believed it would be easier to organize the structure of the discourse with a better understanding of the way temporal information can be expressed by adverbs and verb tenses. We started from the work of Bras (1990), who proposes a method of extracting the temporal structure of a text, according to Discourse Representation Theory (Kamp 1981), that relies on an analysis of adverbials of temporal location made by Molin6s (1990).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> To implement the production of ATLs and verb tenses, we have chosen Systemic Grammar (Halliday 1985; Berry 1975, 1976), which formulates the syntactic structure of a sentence as the result of a sequence of semantic choices. We developed a grammar interpreter inspired by Nigel (Matthiessen and Bateman 1991), but departing from it in many respects; in particular, our representation of the production of verb tenses and adverbs is quite different.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="12"> In this paper, we discuss the elements required to produce a text such as Dis- null The global process.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> course 1. The process starts from a conceptual representation that encodes the facts to be reported in the text, associated with their position in time. The information at this objective conceptual level must be translated into a semantic representation where the facts are presented according to a subjective perspective. The semantic representation is then used to produce the text. We have concentrated our attention on this last stage, but we cannot avoid the problem of determining how the representation used at this level is obtained from previous levels. In the following sections, we describe the two stages of the text-generation process.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

