<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="T75-2025">
<Title>Step I: Select a phenomenon: CONTRADICTION Step 2: Select an input form: ENGLISH SENTENCES Step 3: Select an output form: ENGLISH SENTENCES THAT CONTRADICT THE INPUT SENTENCES</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
SCOPE
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This is a position paper on understanding and improving the curreht styles and methods of scientific work in the application of computers to texts composed of elements from human languages, such as stories, dialogues and sentences. It deals only with kinds of research in which acoustic issues are secondary or absent. It is written specifically to precede discussion at the Workshop on Technical Issues in Natural Language Processing.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> There are various orientations toward value that tend to get assumed rather than discussed at this point. They need not conflict, but some selectivity is necessary. Very roughly, there is an orientation toward understanding and scientific knowledge, and there is an orientation toward application and practical use. Many people regard understanding as a nearly-necessary prerequisite to practical accomplishment.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> That's the view in this paper, so we therefore concentrate on scientific values without denying the others.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> There is a great diversity of acbivities that are carried out by recognizable methods, for which serious questions of methodology could be raised.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> There are tool-building and laboratory setup activities. We do not build linear accelerators or observatories, but we put large efforts into tools anyway. There are speculative and exploratory activities that influence the course of later, more formal work. Choice of phenomena to study is an absolutely crucial one of these activities.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> There are administrative activities for which methods are important. Staffing and seeking funds are also vital. All of these anticipate and support the creation of specific results and are vital to success.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> The activities that produce the knowledge that keeps the work going are of a different kind. IT IS THESE CONSUMMATORY</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

