<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C69-5601">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="10" end_page="31" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
6.0 Results
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> in the final plotting (see figures I, 2, 3 and 4) several groupings can be discerned.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> First, in the multidimensionalsealin~ analysis, we can speak roughly of 3 groups: two form a sort of a nucleus in the center and the third (distributed in two subgroups also) surrounds it. On the external group we have Old Church Slavic, and close by Common Slavic. Then spread around mostly Serbo-croatlan dialects, with some other idioms (e.g. 7-vowel Mom~ilovci Bulgarian,(9#Nasal) vowels Barile Tosk Albanian, 8-vowel Meglenitie, 7-vowel E. Bosnia Serbo-croatian). This group seems to include only dialects with the feature of tenseness. Except for the Albanian dialect, all group members are dialects located  in the Central Balkans, i.e. we have here an areal grouping.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Four out of six Albanian systems (all of the dialects within the geographic area of the Balkans) fall in one group and are closer to Macedonian and Bulgarian than to Rumanlan.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Greek dialects are quite diffused but stay within the two nuclear groups (this includes Classical Attic and Medieval Greek.) In the diz~eter method (figure 4), the most interesting grouping is that of all seven systems with the 5-vowel pattern (irrespective of additional features such as length - nasality - tone) on the same side of the initial bifurcation.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Another subgrouplng includes only systems which use flatness to distinguish a second series of hack vowels (Rhodope Bulgarlan, Kra~ova I Serbo-croatian, Bulgarian Saraka~an Greekp and Hrupi~ta Arumenian).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Among the other interesLing results are the following: contrary to Old Church Slavic and Common Slavic, which in both analyses stand apart, Attic Greek is classed as very similar to the bulk of the systems analyzed: in the diameter method throug h early Joining of the branching tree, and in the multidimensional sealing by being located in the middle of the one of the two central constellations. This is all the mere intriguing in the light of the fact that in a similar statistical correlation (see figure 5) of some Balkan and other  systems expressed in the Harary-Paper model for binary phoneme combinations. Attic was also in the center of the group and OCS (as well as Czech) quite distant from it. Is this not a strong indication of convergence of South Slavic towards a pattern characteristic of Greek since the time of Attic? If anythlng, one would intuitively class the old idioms (Common Slavic, OCS and Attic) as belonging to roughly the same C/ype~: large systems, length, toner accent etc. as additional features. What &amp;quot;latent&amp;quot; structures are responsible for the outcome of the statistical analysis?</Paragraph>
<Section position="1" start_page="31" end_page="31" type="sub_section">
<SectionTitle>
7.0 Some Concluslons
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> It is hoped that the advantages, possible uses and problems of this approach for typological classification as well as some uses of the latter, were sufficiently demonstrated, It is also hoped that criticism and suggesttovs on all aspects will further the ~ttlity and vigor of the approach. 9 Among the main objectives is a better anchorleg of the model on mathematical theory and, parallel to this, better explanation of the linguistics behind the findings and in adapting the model. While thls last is obvious, the search for a model mathematically well grounded is imperative if the approach is to profit more i0 As a from the power of a fully developed mathematical theory.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> concrete step in this direction, a Stochastic Process Model for the same problem is currently investigated, as well as other models applied to different ~speets of phonologle structure.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> No t e_.._._~s See bibliography for particular works on typology. On mathematical models especially pertinent is the work of Spang-Hanssen, Harary and Paper, Ungeheuer, and more recently a series of studies by Soviet Linguists e.g. Revzin; V the work of other Soviet and East European linguists (Saum~an, Marcus, Kulagina etc.) is very interesting and could be applied to typological investigations. For an overview see Kiefer, 1968.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> On statistical techniques, Pierce (1957, 1962), Saporta (1957), Spang-Hanssen, Herdan; in Eastern Europe extensive work, of which one can mention Kr~msky who typifies some of the Prague research and Andreyev's group in the Soviet Union.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> For general discussions, see Birnbaum 1966, 1968, 1969, Edmundson 1967, Greenberg 1957, Horne 1966, Ku~era and Monroe 1968, Plath 1963, Spang-Hanssen 1961-1964, Uspenskij 1966. For a historieal-phonetih typology see Grimes 1961.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Of course Jekobson's work as well as that of Trubetzkoy is of a typological nature. Such is for instance Trubetzkoy's Gz~zuge der P;~nolo~e as well as his articles on vocalic or consonantal systems. For a discussion of the typological nature of  It seems that no two &amp;quot;mirror&amp;quot; systems could be distinguished by this typology. A theoretical shortcoming in spite of the fact that not terribly many such cases exist.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> Much of the data analysis used for the present paper was done at the Johns Hopkins University, as part of my doctoral research which culminated in a thesis (May 1968).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> The idea of a maximal system thus defined can also be found in Voegelin 1963. Uspenskij (1965:63) defines it as follows, opposite to a minimal system: &amp;quot;Jazyk-~talon pervogo tipa (i.e. minimal) mo~zno ponlmat' kak teoretiko-mno~es tvennoj e proizvedenije %~sex xarakterlz\]&amp;jemyx (v opredelennom aspekte) jazykov (modeleJ), t.e. kak invariantnuju dlja vsex ~tix jazykov model'; jazyk-~talon vtorogo tipa (i.e. maximal) V mozno ponimat' kak teoretlko-mnozestvennuju summu usex priznakov opisyvaemyx jazykov (modele~). Pri ~tom u ka~estve to~ki ot~eta pri tipologi~eskix sravnenijax dolmen ispol 'zovat 'sja j~zyk-6talon minimal 'nogo tipa; tem samym jazyk-6talon ~togo tipa mo~et ~&amp;quot; ' &amp;quot; cc~tat ssa osnovnym. Uspenskij points out that the minimal system in a sense &amp;quot;catches the essence&amp;quot; of the languages to be compared. See also the Ph.D. dissertation by Afendras, The Balkans as a Linguistic Area:  for establishing and discussion of the maximal and minimal vocalic and consonantal systems in the Balkans.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> Birnbaum (1966:20) in his discussion of Uspenskij above also expounds on the notions of maximal (:Boolean sum) and minimal (Boolean product) typological systems.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> Actually, much the same is implicit in some of the American typologies (of course Voegelin's, mentioned above) for instance. Pierce's, with its &amp;quot;omnipresent&amp;quot; consonants, the basic core : minlm~, and total collection of any consonants occurring in at least one language = maximum.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> See, for instance, in the statistical correlation (KRUSKAL</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="13"> our findings.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="14"> Grimes (1962), for instance, analyzes phonetic divergence (: &amp;quot;scatter&amp;quot;) within Romance and finds French and RumanXan display &amp;quot;high scatter&amp;quot; from expected innovations, therefore distances from the rest. &amp;quot;It is tempting to guess that the scatter In Rumanian could reflect the influence of non Romance speech communities that have interacted with the Rumanian community (or communities) '' .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="15"> Now since in our analysis Rumanian is quite close to the other Balkan languages (unlike, for instance Serbocroatian) one could say that Grimes' study and this present complementary and mut~lly supportlng results.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="16"> Edmundson's section on mathematical models In Borko 1967 provides a starting point with the must and must nots of the researcher, the does and the does nots of the model.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Section>
</Paper>

