<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C69-0201">
<Title></Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
I. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> To a great extent, the lack of large-scale effective solutions to problems of computatlonal linguistics can be traced to the lack of an adequate linguistic theory that could be used as a framework for computational work. Most of the linguistic theorizing that has taken place in the United States has been done under the banner of Transformational grammar. Fundamental to transformational theory is the sharp distinction between 'competence' and !performance'.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> This distinction between competence and performance provides for transformatlonallsts the platform from which to make their statements about transformations. 'Competence', according to Chomsky is what the speaker-hearer knows about his language, as opposed to his use of that knowledge, labeled 'performance'. Chomsky includes in his discussion of what a 'performance' model should do, factors such as memory limitations, inattentlon~ distraction, and non-linguistlc knowledge. He thus leaves for 'competence' the formalization of linguistic processes representative of the speaker-hearer's knowledge of the language.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> This relegation of competence makes a basic mistake however. It is necessary to differentiate the problem of formalization of linguistic knowledge and processes, i.e., competence, from the simulation of linguistic knowledge and processes, which we shall call 'simulative performance'. There is a difference between the simulation of knowledge and processes ('simulative performance') and the simulation of actual verJ null bal behavior (Chomsky's 'performance'). It is here that we must speak, as chomsky does, of the ideal speaker-hearer. Clearly the ideal speaker-hearer is not inattentive or distracted. He does however have memory  -Ilimitations and non-linguistle knowledge. This is certainly what must be simulated as an inclusive part of linguistic theory. The kind of theory of 'performance' of which Chomsky speaks may well be in the far distant future to which Chomsky relegates it (1965). However, a theory of simulative performance is not so far off. It would seem very reasonable that the possibility of the construction of a linguistic theory that both accounts for the data and does this in such a way as to appear to be consonant with the human method for doing so, is not so remote. Clearly, such a theory must deal with non-linguistic knowledge and problems of human memory as well as the problems that Chomsky designates as 'competence'. Thus, it seems that the sharp distinction between competence and performance is artificial at best. In particular, after elimination of some of the behavioristic problems such as distraction, we can expect to find a linguistic theory that is neither one of 'competence' nor 'performance' but something in between and therefore inclusive of both.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Chomsky (1965:139) has stated: 'thus it seems absurd to suppose that the speaker first forms a generalized Phrase-marker by base rules and then tests it for well-formedness by applying transformational rules to see if it gives, finally, a well-formed sentence.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> But this absurdity is simply a corollary to the deeper absurdity of regarding the system of generative rules as a point-by-point model for the actual construction of a sentence by a speaker.&amp;quot; We could, on the other hand, attempt to formulate a system of rules that are a point-by-point model for the actual construction of a sentence by a speaker. Furthermore, we might expect that that system could also be a point-by-polnt model for the actual analysis of a sentenee by a hearer. These claims, however, would be largely unverifiable  -2except by the use of computers as simulative devices.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Chomsky (1965:141) has further stated that: 'She gralmnar does not, in itself, provide any sensible procedure for finding the deep structure of a given sentence, or for producing a given sentence, just as it provides no sensible procedure for finding a paraphrase to a given sentence. It merely defines these tasks in a precise way. A performance model must certainly incorporate a grammar; it is not to be confused with grammar.&amp;quot; Insofar as the notion of a performance model here can be taken as being somewhere between Chomsky's notion of competence and performance, our notion of grammar also lies somewhere between Chomsky's notion of a grammar and the incorporation of a grammar.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6">  -3-II. Conceptual Dependency The Conceptual Dependency framework (see Schank \[ 1969\] ) is a stratified linguistic system that attempts to provide a computational theory of simulative performance. The highest level of the stratificatlonal system (similar to Lanab \[ 1966\], Sgall \[1965\] and others) employed by the Conceptual Dependency framework is an interlingua consisting of a network of language-free dependent concepts, where a concept may be considered to be an unambiguous word-sense, (except see Schank,\[1968\]). (The notion of dependency used here is related to those of Hays (1964) and Klein (1965), however, the dependencies are not at all restricted to any syntactic criterion.) The graumaar of a language is defined by the framework as consisting of Realization Rules that map conceptual constructs into syntactically correct language on the 'sentential level' The linguistic process can be thought of, in Conceptual Dependency terms, as a mapping into and out of some mental representation. This mental representation consists of concepts related to each other by various meaning-contingent dependency links. Each concept in the inter-lingual network may be associated with some word that is its realizate on a sentential level.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> The conceptual dependency representation is a linked network that can be said to characterize the conceptualization inherent in a piece of wrltten language. The rule of thumb in representing concepts as dependent on other concepts is to see if the dependen t concept will further explain its governor and if the dependent concept cannot make sense without its governor.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> For example, in the sentence, '~he big man steals the red book  -4from the girl.&amp;quot; the analysis is as follows: 'The' is stored for use in connecting sentences in paragraphs, i.e., 'the' specifies that 'man' may have been referred to previously. 'Big' refers to the concept 'big' which cannot stand alone conceptually. The concept 'man' can stand alone and is modified, conceptually by 'big', so it is realized in the network as a governor with its dependent. 'Steals' denotes an action that is dependent on the concept that is doing the acting. A conceptualization (a proposition about a conceptual actor) cannot be complete without a concept acting (or an attribute statement), so a two-way dependency link may be said to exist between 'man' and 'steal' That is, they are dependent on each other and govern each other. Every conceptualization must have a two-way dependency llnk. 'Book' governs 'red' attributively and the whole entity is placed as objectively dependent on 'steals'. The construction 'from the girl' is realized as being dependent on the action through the conceptual object. This is a different type of dependency (denoted by 4). There are different forms of this 'prepositional dependency', each of which is noted by writing the preposition over the llnk to indicate the kind of prepositional relationship. (Although a language may use inflections or nothing at all instead of prepositions to indicate prepositional dependency, we are discussing a language-free system here and it is only the relation of the parts conceptually that is under consideration.) The conceptual network representation of this sentence is then as follows:</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> The conceptual level works with a system of rules (shown in the Appendix) that operate on conceptual categories. These rules generate all the permissible dependencies in a conceptualization. Multiple combinatlon of conceptualizations in various relationships are intended to account for the totality of human language activity at the conceptual level.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> The conceptual categories are divided into governing and assisting groups:</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

