<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C94-2200">
<Title>TIIE EVOLUTION OF MACIIINE- I RA(. I AIII, L DIC~TIONARIES</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
TIIE EVOLUTION OF MACIIINE- I RA(. I AIII, L DIC~TIONARIES
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Dictionaries (MTDs) ill atlCtilllatic SCllSe taggillg el running text ix clearly demonstrated in Tong, el ill., (1993). While previous work (Yarowsky, 1992: Gale, el al., 1092, 1903) lelies heavily on tile role of statistics, TOllg'S sysienl illilkes use of (Ill(: MTD as well as m&lt;~ Machine Readable l)iciionarles (MRI)s) in gin example-based reasonillg process ill laggint~, sellsC Ilillllbers l() llovel words, eompollnds ~,\,ords, gilld pJllHSes in tile input text. The hit rate of correcl ,~,Cll:-;c lagging rtlnS ax high as 90%. The lewes! IlJl rtllC/ c:tcr iecordcd was 70%. The sysieill is eotlsidercd a necessaiy inechanisin for the construcihm ()1 annotated Chinese \]~#ollilor C.'orlJora (SillCILIIC, If) t) I) I1o111 IlllllliIllL (;hilleSe tc',t .</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> l'~girlier work (Wilks, et al., 1'090) identified a dislii101ion belwcell MRI)s and NqTJ)s. This ealx'r recogllizes a further distinction between two types el MT1)s&gt; i.e., Type I and Type il MTDs. Type l MTI)s arc built ()ll the definition priiniiivcs (fi on0 pgirii0ulal MRD wtlerea,,-; Type I1 MTI)s are btlilt ',In the semanli0, prmlitives of one |lgiiciellJar ilgiCtlr:.ll IgillpIlage. The MI'D functitnling ill T,,mg's sysCenl belongs co die l'ype I category. The evolution frlmi Type I t(~ Type I1 MTI)s iopiesents all evoitiCiOli ()1 the i)riinitives ti~c MT1)s arc constrtlcted o11. Th0 atithors believe that, although it is leasible lo derive gi llalllral sol (11 delinilion prilnilixc~ fr(lill o11o parlicti\[gir MRD, a descriptive set of Selllantl0 primitives (Wiiks, 1977) of Olle pariicuhir imlura\] ILingilat2e is prefcigibly deri~ed irl)ill inol'e than t)llC ila\[tll'aJ s(ltlrc0 Sllch :t.s :1 diction',u'y. This p.os;ilip.n rcpresellis gi bgickoll frolll the previous olle Ihgil ctailns tile dcrivalion of a natural set el senlanli0 piinlici',es lrolll oile partietliar MRI), parth:ulgiri)lhe Jz)#1~,l#1fHl  liflmts to dcri~e natural ~;0ts ~)1 semantic prilnilivos lll/nl Typt; I MTDs girt Ihcn des0rihcd These inclll(le work (Ill detccting 0Jr0 tl\]ar dcl ill tiOllS witln n t)llC parliciilgir MT1), work on colnplllhlg the coinpaiil~iliiy I/I word SellSCS beCw0cfi IW() IIW~noJillgtlal di0tiongirics, and the most recent step at der{vmg a ilatura\] set o! Chincse senlaniic primilives Into1 Typ0 i M'I'Ds (11 (Jhinese. The work ~as done on ~tii1.4 worksigiiions with the (7 eoinF, tlter lallgUgige.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

