<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J94-2004">
<Title>Tracking Point of View in Narrative</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> Imagine that a language understander encounters the following passage while reading a novel:</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> HHe \[Sandy\] wanted to talk to Dennys. 1'2How were they going to be able to get home from this strange desert land into which they had been cast and which was heaven knew where in all the countless solar systems in all the countless galaxies? \[UEngle, Many Waters, p. 91\] In this passage, the author is not objectively narrating events or describing the fictional world, but is presenting the thoughts and emotions of a character. It is to Sandy that the land is strange, and it is Sandy's uncertainty that is expressed by the question and the expression 'heaven knew where.' Unless the language understander realizes these things, it hasn't fully understood the passage.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Passages such as (1) take a character's psychological point of view and are composed of subjective sentences--sentences that present the thoughts, perceptions, and inner states of characters in the story. Notice that nothing in (1.2) explicitly specifies that the sentence is Sandy's thought. In general, only a narrative parenthetical, such as 'Dennys thought' in (2), serves to explicitly indicate both that a sentence is subjective and who its subjective character is.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  * Department of Computer Science, New Mexico State University, Box 30001/Dept. CS, Las Cruces, NM 88003-0001. E-mail: wiebe@nmsu.edu. (~) 1994 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 2 (2)  Certainly, Dennys thought, anything would be better than this horriblesmelling place full of horrible little people. \[UEngle, Many Waters, p. 25\] In all other cases, one must rely on less direct sources of information to determine the psychological point of view.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> This paper presents an algorithm for recognizing subjective sentences and identifying their subjective characters in third-person fictional narrative text. The algorithm is based on regularities, found by extensive examination of naturally occurring text (i.e., published novels and short stories) in the ways that authors manipulate point of view. It has been implemented, and some preliminary empirical studies, which lend support to the algorithm, have also been performed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> The algorithm is described in the body of the paper and is given in full in Appendix A. Sections 2-5 give background information and describe my approach to the problem. Sections 6 and 7 present an overview of the algorithm, specifying the input and output of the basic components and identifying the components focused on in this work. Sections 8-10 present the bulk of the algorithm, addressing the problem of identifying subjective characters before the problem of recognizing subjective sentences. Section 11 describes the algorithm's treatment of sentences about private-state actions, such as sighing and looking. Sections 12-14 conclude the paper with a summary of tests of the algorithm and discussions of the relationship between tracking point of view and anaphora resolution and of directions for future research. The algorithm is given in Appendix A, demonstrations of its implementation are given in Appendix B, and the results of a test of the algorithm are given in Appendix C.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

