<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="C86-1072">
<Title>GENERATING SI~A~rlC STRUCTURF~ IN EUR(Ylq~A-D ERI6~ |ST~INER Ihl - EUROTRA - D MARTIN-L~I~ER-STRASSE 14 D - 6600 Saarbrficken</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="305" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
CONDITION
CONCESSIVE
CONSEQUENCE
CAUSE
CONCERN
QUALITY ~TOTUN
ACCORD
ACCOMPANIMENT
INSTRUMENT
MEASURE
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> According to current EUROTRA legislation, these gRs are assigned to dictionary entries of verbs (and other word classes, which will be disregarded in this paper) by coders, and through these entries to clauses in a pattern matching process.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> This approach, while certainly valid in principle, leads to the problem of inter-coder-consistency, at least as long as the means for identifying SRs are paraphrase tests for SRs. In EUROTRA-D, we have for some time now been experimenting with a set of SRs, or PRs, which are identified with tile help of syntactic criteria. This approach will be outlined in the following. Its roots, are to be found in the literature on semantic cases in general (cf.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Fillmore.1968 and 1977, Starosts 1977, Somers.198B) and more particularly, in ideas from Systemic Linguists (cf. Fawcett.1980 and forthcoming, HaIliday.1967-68 and \]985, Sl:einer.1983 and 1985, Winograd. 1983).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> 2. Definition of basic concepts To start with, we need a small set of basic concepts, which will be define(\[ in the following. There is a basic distinction between Participant Roles and Circumstantial Roles on the semantic \]eve\], which the ELS-3 specifications do not contain. There is the further distinction between inherent and non-inherent roles, which is also not explicitly made in ELS-3 and may be necessary at some point.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4">  Participant Role: A participant role is a semantic constituent of a clause which is syntactically reaIized as a complement rather than as a modifier. Circumstantial Role: A circumstantial role is a  semantic constituent which is, on clause level, realized as a modifier rather than as a complement ~oq~ Participant Role: A semantic constituent which is, on clause level, realized as obligatory complement O~ional Participant Role: A semantic constituent which is, on clause level, realized as an optional complement Inherent Role: Inherent roles are obligatory participant roles and those participant roles which, Jf they are not realized in a clause, lead to look up in the preceding text or situation for a referent, Cf,: (20) David wax watching.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

