<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="N06-4003">
<Title>SmartNotes: Implicit Labeling of Meeting Data through User Note-Taking and Browsing</Title>
<Section position="1" start_page="0" end_page="261" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
Abstract
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> We have implemented SmartNotes, a system that automatically acquires labeled meeting data as users take notes during meetings and browse the notes afterwards.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> Such data can enable meeting understanding components such as topic and action item detectors to automatically improve their performance over a sequence of meetings. The SmartNotes system consists of a laptop based note taking application, and a web based note retrieval system. We shall demonstrate the functionalities of this system, and will also demonstratethelabeleddataobtainedduringtyp- null ical meetings and browsing sessions.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> 1 Goals of the SmartNotes System Most institutions hold a large number of meetings every day. Several of these meetings are important, and meeting participants need to recall the details of the discussions at a future date. In a previous survey (Banerjee et al., 2005) of busy professors at CarnegieMellonUniversityweshowedthatmeeting participants needed to recall details of past meetings on average about twice a month. Performing such retrieval is not an easy task. It is time consuming; in our study participants took on average between 15 minutes to an hour to recall the information they were seeking. Further, the quality of the retrieval is dependent on whether or not the participants had access to the notes at the meeting. On a scale of 0 to 5, with 5 denoting complete satisfaction with retrieval results, participants reported a satisfaction of 3.4 when they did not have notes, and 4.0 when they did.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> Despite the prevalence of important meetings and the importance of notes, there is a relative paucity of technology to help meeting participants take notes easily at meetings. Some commercial applications allow users to take notes (e.g. OneNote1) and even record audio/video (e.g. Quindi2), but no product attempts to automatically take notes. Our long term goal is to create a system that makes note-taking easier by performing tasks such as automatically highlighting portions of the meeting that are likely to be important to the user, automatically detecting &amp;quot;note-worthy&amp;quot; phrases spoken during the meeting, etc.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> To perform such note taking, the system needs to form an understanding of the meeting. Our short term goal is to create a system that can detect the topics of discussion, the action items being discussed, and the roles of the meeting participants. Additionally, these components must adapt to specific users and groups of users since different people will likely take different notes at the same meeting. Thus we wish to implement the note taking system in such a way that the user's interactions with the system result in labeled meeting data that can then be used to adapt and improve the meeting understanding components.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> Towards these goals, we have built SmartNotes which helps users easily record and retrieve notes.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6">  The system also records the user interactions to form labeled meeting data that can later be used to automatically improve the meeting understanding components. In the next section we describe the meeting understanding components in more detail. Next we describe SmartNotes itself, and show how it is currently helping users take and retrieve notes, while acquiring labeled data to aid each of the meeting understanding components. Finally we end with a discussionofwhatfunctionalityweplantodemonstrate null at the conference.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

