<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Paper uid="J00-4002">
<Title>Bidirectional Contextual Resolution</Title>
<Section position="2" start_page="0" end_page="0" type="abstr">
<SectionTitle>
1. Introduction
</SectionTitle>
<Paragraph position="0"> This paper has several aims. Firstly, it outlines a formalism within which quasi-logical form-based theories of contextual interpretation of sentences can be stated in a way which is completely reversible; that is to say, theories expressed within the formalism can be used to provide interpretations for (utterances of) sentences containing contextually dependent constructs, given a context; and, given an interpretation and a context, to generate a sentence which has that interpretation in that context. Processing in both directions is done using exactly the same grammar, and the same set of contextual interpretation rules.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="1"> To give an extremely simplified example, the aim is to have a way of interpreting the sentences in the left-hand column below as expressing the logical forms in the middle column, given that they are encountered in that order in an otherwise neutral context: and the reverse--given a sequence of logical forms as in the middle column, to be able to generate (among others) the sequence of sentences in the left-hand column, rather than the unnatural although literally correct version given in the right-hand column.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="2"> Joe sneezed, sneeze(joe) Joe sneezed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="3"> He laughed, laugh(joe) Joe laughed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="4"> Bill laughed too. laugh(bill) Bill laughed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="5"> We will assume that if the context is loosely specified enough to permit alternative realizations of the same content, then different versions of the same text could be generated or analysed: (1) Joe sneezed and laughed. Bill laughed too.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="6"> Joe sneezed. Joe and Bill laughed.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="7"> Joe sneezed. He laughed. So did Bill.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="8"> Somerville College, Oxford OX2 6HD. E-mail: stephenpulman@linguistics-phildegldeggy'degxac'uk Q 2001 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 26, Number 4 Secondly, we illustrate the formalism and the general approach by developing an account of contextual interpretation based on a kind of quasi-logical form and giving an account of a fragment (in the sense of Montague \[1974a\]) that treats several core phenomena of English contextual dependence.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="9"> We also have some theoretical objectives: the particular approach illustrated here, like most computational approaches to contextual interpretation, uses an intermediate quasi-logical form representation level. Using such a level of representation incurs an obligation to say what it means (&amp;quot;no notation without denotation&amp;quot;). We try to show how the theory presented here leads to a natural semantics for these quasi-logical forms, and indeed leads to a truth theory for contextually dependent interpretation that supports a natural consequence relation, and one appropriate for cases where interpretations are not fully specified. We relate this approach both to the classical tradition of formal linguistic semantics exemplified by Davidson (1972) and Montague (1974b) and more recent literature on the use of underspecification in semantics. null The structure of the paper is as follows: In the next section we give an outline of the formalism and illustrate with the small fragment of English that has been implemented within this framework. We present analyses of the contextual interpretation of pronouns, definites, ellipsis, focus, and quantifier scope. There is far more to say about each of these phenomena, of course, and the analyses here are by no means claimed to be definitive. The aim is merely to show that we can, to a first approximation, provide a reasonably fully worked out description of these phenomena in a truly bidirectional way.</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="10"> We then go on to compare the current approach with that of some other theories with similar aims: the &amp;quot;standard&amp;quot; version of quasi-logical form implemented in the Core Language Engine, as rationally reconstructed by Alshawi and Crouch (1992) and Crouch and Pulman (1994); underspecified Discourse Representation Theory (Reyle 1993); and the &amp;quot;glue language&amp;quot; approach of Dalrymple et al. (1996).</Paragraph>
<Paragraph position="11"> Finally, we discuss some of the semantic and logical issues raised by the approach described here, in particular the extent to which the theory meets the desiderata for accounts of underspecification outlined by van Eijck and Jaspars (1996), and the extent to which the theory supplies a methodologically satisfactory account of truth and interpretation for sentences involving contextually dependent constructs.</Paragraph>
</Section>
</Paper>

